<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../SI_Ref_and_Resp.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, January 30th 1820</title>
            <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>
          
            <editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor>
            
            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor>
              <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor> 
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                  <persName>Alexandra Drayton</persName>
               
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt><edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and "should contain phrases describing the edition or version: First digital edition in TEI, date: 4 June 2013. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp><persName>Who?</persName></respStmt>
         
         </editionStmt>
         
        
         
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability>
            
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         
         <notesStmt><note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
         <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         
         <sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository>Reading Central Library</repository> <idno>MS number</idno></msIdentifier> <head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date>30 January 1820</date>.</head></msDesc></sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl><p>Describes our editorial practice.</p></editorialDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text> 
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <!-- In a different hand (black ink) on the top right of the page it says 'To Sir W. Elford' -->
                  <name type="place">Bertram House</name>
                  <date when="1820-01-30"> <choice><abbr>Jan<am>y</am></abbr><expan>Jan<ex>uary</ex></expan></choice> <!-- January is abbreviated, have I shown this correctly? --> 30<emph rend="superscript">st</emph>1820.</date> 
               </dateline>
             </opener>
            <p> I have just this moment received your 
               most kind &amp; entertaining letter, <rs type="person" ana="Elford">my dear friend</rs> , &amp; I hasten 
               to answer it on the full gallop that I may catch our flying                   
               M.P.<persName>Mr <sic>Fysh </sic><corr>Fyshe</corr>Palmer</persName><!-- looks like it was supposed to be written Fyshe - hard to tell if she left 'e' off as misspelling or bad writing --> - who was in Reading yesterday &amp;<unclear><supplied>ink blot</supplied></unclear> <!-- how do you code an ink blot (it's a blot, not written...) --> 
               (Deuce take that blot - more haste worse speed!)  our moveable
               <rs type="person" ana="Fyshe Palmer">Member</rs> who was in Reading yesterday &amp; <emph rend="underline">therefore</emph> will not be 
               there tomorrow. First let me express how unfeignedly sorry 
               I am - we are - for the sickness you have had to encounter at <placeName>Birkham</placeName> - I hope this will find your daughter recovering both her
               strength &amp; her looks - &amp; that your cough will disappear in this
               mild weather - melt &amp; go off like the snow. <rs type="person">Mama</rs> &amp; I have kept
               quite well this unhealthy winter - <rs type= "person">Papa</rs> has not - he has had a 
               great deal of <sic>head ach</sic><corr>headache</corr> &amp; heavy cold - &amp; as he takes no manner
               of care of himself - comes down from <placeName>London</placeName> at <time>four <sic>oclock</sic><corr>o'clock</corr></time> in the
               morning on the outside of a coach - &amp; other tendencies of the same 
               nature (I hope he is looking over my shoulder) can scarcely
               expect to be free from complaint. M<emph rend="superscript">rs</emph>Dickinson is not yet
               confined &amp; keeps pretty well as to health though a good deal
               troubled with superstitious forebodings which I do all in 
               my power to drive out of her head by gay <unclear>&amp;</unclear> nonsense. Now 
               you have our bulletin<unclear>s</unclear> all round. <gap rend="squiggle"></gap>What you say of 
               <title>Ivanhoe</title> is admirably just and true - <persName ref="#Rowena">Rowena</persName> is a mere
               woman of straw - a peg to hang <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del>love upon - as almost all <rs type="person" ana="Sir Walter Scott">his</rs> heroines are - of that horrible old woman I had before
               made dishonourable mention -- &amp; those two scenes of burning
               &amp; of torture are quite unworthy of so great a Poet - He picked
               up that love of representing bodily suffering though, where<pb n="2"/>
               <!-- ??? --> by word syllable by syllable - it is their <emph rend="underline">fault</emph>, that they are of <!-- page obscured in photograph - check in library letter --> 
               Poems the most recherchés - Moreover <persName>Madame de Genlis</persName> makes <title>Petrarque</title> out an angel &amp;then says she is just like him! Really
               these French women are vain of their own vanity! - Do you ever read <persName>Miss Burney</persName>'s novels? I mean the lesser <persName>Burney</persName> - not 
               <persName>Madame D'Arblay</persName> but her sister whom I like better. We are
               reading one now - <title>Country Neighbours</title> - pretty enough I think. <gap reason="illegible" unit="word" quantity="1"/> <!-- this should be easy to find in the original -->
               by millions - a heroine who is so young so wise so good so beauti <gap rend= "
               ="></gap>ful <!-- beautiful is split over a line, looks like beauti=ful -->  &amp; so accopmlished that she makes one sick even before she
               saves her lover's life, an iniquity so <persName>Miss-Porterish</persName> <!-- Miss Porter a name or a character? --> that I
               quite wonder at Miss Burney's lighting upon it - the plot too
               is exceedingly disagreeable &amp;entangled - all in a <emph rend ="underline">snarl</emph> as the
               cotton-spinners say, &amp; mighty difficult to undo. But <!-- word hard to read - perhaps eventually? -->
               the book is pretty - there is some good observation in it - &amp;
               a sarcastic old lady whom I like exceedingly - to say nothing of a 
               most amiable old maid - Well I think I have talked enough of 
               novels - Did you ever read a little book which has been lately reprinted <bibl><title>The Captivity of Captain John Knox  <sic>in</sic><corr>on</corr>the Island of Ceylon</title></bibl>?<!-- Account of the Captivity of Robert Knox and Other Englishmen, in the Island of Ceylon: And of the Captain's Miraculous Escape and Return to England in September 1680, After Detention on the Island of Nineteen Years and a Half ???  -->It is charming - If one did not know it to be nothing but
               a real true history told by the very man to whom it happened
               one should take it for one of the enchanting fictions of before - 
               Nothing but <title>Robinson Crusoe</title> was ever so vividly real<gap rend="squiggle"></gap>
               I thought I had done with books - but I find I have not - <persName>Ben
               Jonson</persName>'s <title>Sad Shepherd</title> is a fragment of a Pastoral Drama said
               to have been left unfinished in consequence of the ill success of his
               friend <persName>Fletcher</persName>'s exquisite <title>Faithful Shepherdess</title> - only
               two acts of a scene remain, but they are enchanting - not in 
               old Ben's common Dramatic style, so stiff &amp;artificial - but
               in the sweet &amp; tender manner of some of his beautiful lyrics <!-- an underscore here (looks like "_" -->
               If finished it would have been one of the finest things in the 
               language - the story relates to <title>Robin Hood</title> - <title>Gammer Gurton's Needle</title> is quite another matter - you know that it is the oldest
               English play - &amp; really it is one of the most diverting - coarse
               enough to be true but exceedingly fresh &amp; frolicsome &amp; funny
               &amp; not at all unintelligible - <persName>Miss James</persName> who is <del rend="crossout">by far</del><hi rend="superscript"> one of</hi> the most elegant person of my acquaintance says she likes it better
               than any comedy in the language - one of the characters in it\always put me in mind of <persName ref="#Edie_Olchiltree">Edie Ochiltree</persName> - not in <hi rend="superscript">his</hi> supernatural 
               capacity - <gap rend="scribble"><!-- illegible word --></gap> which you dislike so much - but in his better
               vocation of a merry old beggar - that <title>"Antiquary"</title> after all is my
               favourite of the whole set of Scotch novels 
           
                  
          
               
               
               
               
               
               
               ELISA's LETTER BELOW
               the husband
               was to be she should never <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> get
               him. There was no saying a word after that you know. By the bye nothing but the sort of
               sacred air &amp;that breathes around Bridecake--so that to steal that would be to invade the
               sweetest &amp; amp; holiest of our affections &amp; sympathies--nothing but this fine
               &amp; general feeling could have preserved your munificent present, &amp; brought it safe
               to us. By some accident it was sent not by a Reading Coach but a Newbury one, &amp; found
               its way to Three Mile Cross, after being carried half way to Newbury, through the
               intervention of all manner of men &amp; women--Post boys--&amp; Chambermaids &amp; keepers
               of Turnpike gates. But every thing belonging to such a Wedding &amp; such a Honeymoon as
               yours will turn out right depend on it. You see that your good luck extends even to your
               friends--&amp; travels about with your bride-cake. Oh it will never forsake you! Never! I
               think that last honeymoon letter written whilst the fair Bride was sitting working &amp;
               smiling at your side, was prettier even than the first. Did you read it to her as you
               wrote it? or <pb n="2"/> shall I send her a copy? It was worthy even of that charming
               seal. How much you must both have felt in going into your painting room!--Will the Lazarus
               be finished against next season? If any thing could improve your genius it would be living
               in such a sunshine of love &amp; beauty.</p>
            <p>Miss James is very anxious to have the pleasure of being known to Mrs. Haydon--She
               mentioned your note with great delight, &amp; talked of calling--but was not I suppose
               certain of the time you would return to <placeName><district ref="#Lisson_Grove">Lisson
                  Grove</district></placeName>. She is by this time back again at Richmond. I wished her
               very much to call on you Sunday or Monday that she might leave with you my poor Tragedy
               which <unclear><supplied>I have</supplied></unclear> should of all things have wished you
               to read--indeed I begged her to take the chance--I have such an opinion of your judgment.
               But it is now out of her hands. Only think of my shocking ill luck in having written on
               the same subject with <persName ref="#Byron"> Lord Byron</persName>--The story of
               <persName ref="#Doge_F_hist">Foscari</persName>--I am so distressed at the idea of
               a competition, not merely with his Lordship's talents, but with his great name, &amp; the
               strange awe in which he holds people, &amp; the terrible scoffs &amp; sneers in which he
               indulges himself, that I have written to <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName>
               requesting him to consult another <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"
               /></del> friend on the propriety of entirely suppressing my play, which had gone to Town
               to be presented to the Manager the very day that <bibl corresp="#The_Two_Foscari">the subject of <persName
                  ref="#Byron">Lord Byron's</persName></bibl> announced. I rather think now
               that it will not be offered--that <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName> will
               suppress it--&amp; I heartily wish he may. <app>
                  <lem wit="#ebb">
                     <!-- App Lemma start: what follows is missing from L'Estrange -->My poor Tragedy has
                     been a work of great labour &amp; is certainly complete enough in its own small way,
                     but it is abundantly womanish &amp; feeble, &amp; does not at all adhere to the
                     literal historic truth--which would be a great disadvantage in case the noble author
                     <pb n="3"/> should have done so, &amp; have made the public familiar with the facts.
                     I hope it will not be offered. What do you think of <persName>Lord Byron's</persName>
                     dramatic power? <title ref="#Manfred">Manfred</title> was very fine certainly--perhaps
                     the finest thing he ever did--&amp; <title ref="#Marino_Faliero">Marino
                        Faliero</title> certainly the worst. But <persName ref="#Doge_F_hist"
                           >Foscari</persName> is a story of real human sympathy--not of factitious
                     sentiment--He will certainly succeed in that. If this play
                     <!-- App Lemma concludes. L'Estrange reads: If it be sent back... --></lem>
                  <rdg wit="A. G. J. L'Estrange">If it</rdg>
               </app><!-- List person entry for A.G.J. L'Estrange somewhere -->be sent back to me
               unoffered I shall immediately begin another on some German story &amp; shall take for the
               opening the exquisite first act of the <title ref="#Orestes">Orestes</title> of <persName
                  ref="#Euripedes">Euripides</persName>--which I saw acted so finely a fortnight ago,
               &amp; which it is quite wonderful to think has never been transferred to the English
               stage. What astonishing people those Greek dramatists were! I am just now reading
               <!-- IDENTIFY REF! Potter's Aeschylus -->Potter's Aeschylus with the intensity of
               admiration with which you <damage type="portion_of_seal"/> would look at the frescoes of
               Michael Angelo <del type="crossout">&amp;</del> Happening to express something of this
               enthusiasm to a scholar of very great name he answered--"The
               <!-- IDENTIFY PROMETHEUS REF: presumably connected with Potter's Aeschylus -->Prometheus?
               Yes the Prometheus is rather pretty--prettyish--one of the prettiest!" Now what business
               has this man to know Greek! And what business have I to be intruding so long on you?--Good
               bye my dear Sir[.] My Father &amp; Mother join [carat insertion above line]<add
                  rend="metamark" place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="carat"
                  />me </add> in every kind remembrance &amp; kinder wish to you &amp; to
               <!-- IDENTIFY THE HAYDONS: husband and wife -->Mrs Haydon. </p>
            <closer>
               <lb/>Ever most sincerely your's<lb/> <signed>MM
                  Mitford.</signed><lb/> 
               Do not mention my Foscari unless it should really be likely to come out of which
               you shall have the earliest notice. But of that there is very little chance. Once more God
               bless you. We have just been drinking your health &amp; your dear Mary's. Again Good bye 
               <pb n="4"/><!-- ADDRESS LEAF AND POSTMARKS FOLLOW -->
               <!-- Figure out how to indicate Postmarks -->   B. R. Haydon Esqre<lb/>
               St. John's Place Lisson Grove North<lb/>
               Regent's Park<lb/>
               London</closer>
         </div>
      </body>

     
     <back>
       
           <listPerson type="fict">
              <person xml:id="Rowena">
                 <persName>Rowena</persName>
                 <note resp="#ebb">Character in <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName>'s <title ref="#Ivanhoe">Ivanhoe</title>.</note>
              </person>
              
           </listPerson>
     </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
