<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="SI_Ref_and_Resp.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Copy of a letter to <persName ref="#Macready_Wm"></persName>, August 12<hi rend="superscript">st</hi>1825.</title>
            <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
            <respStmt>   
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#csc">Catherine S Cox</persName>
                  </respStmt>
            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <encodingDesc>
               <editorialDecl>
                  <p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at
                     the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where
                     Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order
                     to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg"
                     to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of
                     Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford
                     English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
               </editorialDecl>
            </encodingDesc>
            <p>Sir--severe indisposition has prevented my earlier attention to your letter.--In answer to your enquiries I can only say that I knew nothing of the article in question </unclear></supplied>file</supplied> I saw it with great regret a few days after the publication in Blackwood's Magazine. Truth &amp; error are so mixed up in that Narrative that it is difficult to separate them.--That you did send for me on the perusal of Rienzi;  That you suggested many &amp; material alterations; That you assured me, at least that I understood you to assure me, that if altered </gap> to your satisfaction you could &amp; would bring out the play; That you subsequently caused <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName> to write to me desiring that I myself would bring up the piece to prevent the delay even of a day in case further changes were requisite; &amp; that when I waited on you at the time appointed you told me that there was no hurry for that you had another Tragedy in the Theatre;--all this appears to us true--&amp; without using much hard words or harbouring such hard thoughts as "deceiving or betraying," the disappointment was bitter. </p> 


</TEI>

