<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

<teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="MRM1742">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William
               Elford</persName>, <date when="1819-07-28">July 28, 1819</date></title>
            <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>
            <editor ref="#ds">Daniel Schierenbeck</editor>
            <editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor>
            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#ds">Daniel Schierenbeck</persName>
               <persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName>
               <persName>Allison McConlogue</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><!--2017-12-31 repaired munged date listing. NOTED: This letter is NOT COMPLETE. -->
               <persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!-- updates to header only. LMW 2015-10-08 -->
               <!-- list all proofreaders here. -->
               <!--LMW and AVM:  transcription now complete, coding IP, working on SI entries. 2018-04-30-->
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2015-04-26">26 April
                  2015</date>. P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp>
               <orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName>
               <resp> photo files: <idno>DSCF9476.jpg, DSCF9477.jpg, DSCF9478.jpg, DSCF9479.jpg,
                     DSCF9480.jpg, DSCF9481.jpg, DSCF9482.jpg. DSCF9483.jpg. DSCF9484.jpg.
                     DSCF9485.jpg</idno></resp>
            </respStmt>
            <!-- Change to reflect photo file names for your letter (as you see here, including .jpg extension).  -->
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central
                     Library</orgName>.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository>
                  <collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection>
                  <idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 377</idno>
                  </msIdentifier>
               <head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1819-07-28">July 28, 1819</date>.</head>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                       <support>
                           <p>One sheet of folio <material>paper</material>, four surfaces
                              photographed.</p>
                          
                           <p>Address leaf bearing black postmark, partially illegible, reading
                                    <stamp><lb/><placeName>READING</placeName><lb/></stamp>.</p>
                           <p>A large 3 denoting the posting fee has been written in black ink by
                              the postal service across the address
                           leaf.</p>&gt;
                        </support>
                        <condition>
                           <p>Sheet (pages three and four) torn on right edge of page three where
                              wax seal was removed.</p>
                        </condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <sealDesc>
                     <p>Red wax seal, complete, adhered to page four.</p>
                  </sealDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a
               different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing
               diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly
               across Mitford's writing.
               A
               red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the first three leaves. On
               leaf four, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right across each of the two
               text blocks. There is no red crayon across the address text block.</handNote>
            <handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford,
               perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and
               numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection.
               <!-- Don't change the preceding sentence if this letter has grey pencil. In the following sentence, describe penciled numbers or change/add whatever text you see written in pencil. -->This
               letter is numbered "13" in the top left of the first leaf. </handNote>
         </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="P1020242.JPG"/>
            <opener>
               <add hand="pencil_Rylands">To Sir W. Eld. Begin with these lines</add>
               <add hand="#pencil">13</add>
               <dateline>
        
                  <date when="1819-07-28">July 28, 1819</date>.
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p><lb/>Why <choice><sic>Wizzard</sic><reg>Wizard</reg></choice> thus disturb my dormant life
               <lb/>And raise me through the water's misty strife
               <lb/>Oh cease! Your high behests with speed disclose
               <lb/>With speed dismiss me to my dread repose</p><!--LMW: Can we identify whether Elford published these lines? AVM: So far no evidence. 2018-05-22-->
            <p>It is not from laziness believe me, my dear Friend, that I have sent your four lines unaltered. I have been altering them all the morning--turning &amp; twisting them twenty different ways--&amp; on an impartial survey of the several readings am convinced that your version is much the best. Mine all look <emph rend="underline">patched</emph>. Indeed I write verses so seldom now that I have lost the little power I once possessed. The reason of my not sending you any of my attempts is, that I fear your modesty or your politeness might tempt you to prefer my bad lines to your good ones &amp; I would not put such a risk in your way. Surely the last line is very <del rend="squiggles" n="1" unit="word"><unclear/></del> good--the repetition strengthens it. In addition to the greater clearness of these last verses which we both prefer, they remind me much less of those in <title ref="#Manfred_play">Manfred</title> for which you know I took the first you sent me, &amp; as your Picture though strikingly coinciding in subject with this fine conception of <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName>'s is not taken from it--has I suppose neither the cascade-rainbow nor the Alpine scenery of his Drama you would of course not wish your nymph to be confounded with the <title>"Witch of the Alps."</title></p><metamark rend="jerks"/><p>Now that our something like business is dispatched, let me thank you a thousand times for your charming letter &amp; all its kindness. You have before now received my doleful epistle, &amp; know that we cannot come to <placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName>. I wish I was setting out for it this very moment. I did not want that dear letter to remind me of all that I love. And yet it has very much <choice><sic>encreased</sic><reg>increased</reg></choice> my regret. I shall do nothing for a whole week but pity myself &amp; hate <persName ref="#Elliott_Mr">Mr. Elliot</persName>. What pleasure I should have had in seeing with you such scenery as you describe--in meeting <persName ref="#Welsford_Miss">Miss Welsford</persName> who is so good to me &amp; whom I look upon as a ready made friend--in making acquaintance with your daughters who are I hope equally well disposed towards me--&amp; even in hearing <orgName ref="#Balcombe_family">the Balcombe family</orgName> talk of my <pb n="2" facs="P1020244.JPG"/>hero. (Do send me word what they say of him.)--I must not think of what I lose or I shall become quite fretful &amp; repining. I must talk of something else. You are certainly a critic of the very first water my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName> deny it as you may--&amp; neither <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hofland</persName> nor I flatter you in the least. As to <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs. Hof:</persName> I don't think she can flatter--she does not know how &amp; says things sometimes in the way of truth-telling that startle a whole company like the sudden going off of a gun--and as to me--I may sometimes in my enthusiasm <emph rend="underline">think a leetel <!--a quotation? See The Discovery by Frances Sheridan (a play))--></emph> more than exists, but I never said a word more than I believed even of you on <persName ref="#Napoleon">Buonaparte</persName>. (how do you like the conjunctions?) Now that I have cleared my ground I may be believed when I tell you how much I admire all that you have said of these <title>Tales of my Landlord</title>.<note resp="#lmw">Mitford refers to Walter Scott's <title ref="#Bride_of_Lammermoor_WS">The Bride of Lammermoor</title>.</note> The shifts &amp; contrivances of the servant<!--LMW: Caleb Balderstone--> (always excepting the admirable detail of the cooper's menage which they are the means of introducing--the only piece of real life in the story) are not only false &amp; poor &amp; worthless--a bad imitation of some farce that I have seen--abortive humour which is worse than anything--they are not only detestable in themselves, but by bringing back the imagination <metamark rend="caret" place="below"/><add place="above">with a jerk</add>to all that is low &amp; pitiful completely destroy the illusion which the Author intended to produce by the romantic &amp; supernatural tone of the story. He certainly as you so well observe does believe himself in all manner of second-sight &amp; Faëry--&amp; if he had had Fairfax's <!--Edward Fairfax, translator of Tasso, mentioned in Walter Scott's Letters on Demonology and WItchcraft--> good luck &amp; lived in days when such a belief would not have been laughed at, &amp; pilloried in reviews &amp; <del rend="squiggles" n="1" unit="word"><unclear/></del>pelted in newspapers he would have been as great or greater than Fairfax in his own way.
               Prevailing poet whose undoubting mind<lb/>
               Believed the magic wonder that he sung<lb/> <!--Check the quotation. William Collins, "Ode on the Popular Superstitutions of the Highlands of Scotland"-->--but being by his evil stars condemned to make his fortune in a sneering &amp; a skeptical age, he is obliged to cover his strong under current &amp; of credibility with little fluctuating waves of mock-unbelief, &amp; affected levity which entirely counteract one effect, without actually producing the other. I wonder he does not feel &amp; know how <del rend="squiggles" unit="word" n="1"><supplied resp="#lmw">entirely</supplied></del><add place="above">completely</add> the artificial state of<pb n="3" facs="P1020245.JPG"/> of mind excited by a powerful representation of supernatural <del rend="squiggles" unit="chars" n="2"/> subjects must be destroyed by anything light or ludicrous--anything which breathes or suspends even for a moment the gloomy &amp; passionate feeling. Everything in ghost stories depends on continuity--one cannot lay down the book to snuff the candle without letting some part of the awe escape--The hair which has been standing to charmingly an end with fright fallsdown flump--&amp; won't get up again.--The nymph of the fountain is very pretty &amp; I think original. If you like such water sprite stories you should read <title ref="#Undine">Undine</title> (Do you remember how you attracted my handwriting about that word?)<!--make note to previous letter.--> There is in that the prettiest mixture of childishness &amp; witchery that can be imagined with a deep &amp; intense moral feeling--and very short--only one small volume.</p><metamark rend="jerks"/><p> I am very stupid tonight--worse than usual--&amp; I can guess why. I have been reading a fine thick metaphysical book--<persName ref="#Brown_Thos">Professor Brown</persName> on <title ref="#Inquiry_CauseEffect">Cause &amp; Effect</title>--&amp; to use the learned professor's own phraseology I suppose that the general <q>"consequent"</q> of such an <q>"antecedent"</q> as reading his book is stupidity. I must tell you how <del rend="cut"/><supplied>I</supplied><!--page torn, perhaps "I"--> was betrayed into such a headachy lecture this warm weather. <!--unclear, small writing above; can't figure it out--><!--I think it's an early editor supplying what's missing:  James lent?  Miss James was her friend.--> Miss James [page torn, perhaps "gave"]--&gt; me the book--&amp; she knows and likes the author &amp; wanted to say something nice to him about his work--but being too wise to read it herself sent it to me to read for her. Is not she a pretty fellow?</p><metamark rend="jerks"/><p>Did I tell you in my last for really I don't remember Deuce take Professor Brown's great book!) that I have got a new pet? All this warm weather I sit out of doors in the Plantations--just on one side of my seat is a filberd tree the branches of which spread quite across my feet &amp; on these branches every day comes a young red breast--first of all he appeared at a distance--then he came nearer then he fed close to me &amp; now the moment I call <q>Bobby</q><!--she probably names him Bobby as short for Robin, as in Robin Redbreast, traditional name.--> he comes. <persName ref="#Mossy_pet">Mossy</persName> himself is not more tame or more fond--he comes on my feet &amp; my gown--feeds almost on my hand (not quite) &amp; has by example tamed his Papa &amp; one or two of his brothers &amp; sisters who come like him &amp; feed from a board on the tree quite close to me but do not like my own Bobby come when they are called. Is this unusual in the summer? I know they are tame in the winter--but this is quite a young bird has never known cold or hunger, he had not a red feather in his breast a fortnight ago. He likes very much to be talked to in a soft monotonous &amp; caressing tone<pb n="4" facs="P1020246.JPG"/> Bobby! Bobby! Bobby! &amp; turns his head in the prettiest attitudes of listening that you can imagine &amp; generally finishes by taking two or three flights across me so close as almost to touch my face. I shall be so long to leave him--I think that I shall try to get it put in the deeds that <persName ref="Eliott_Mr">Mr. Elliot</persName> must feed Bobby.</p><metamark rend="jerks"/><p>. How very good you were to transcribe for me Mr. Cranstown's account of young Napoleon.--though perhaps one had rather that he were more like a boy--one does not imagine his father to have been so sedate a person at his age. But Princes poor things never can be children--their luckless station will not let them--&amp; that I suppose is one reason why so few of them turn out great men. Did you ever hear that a damsel of his own rank &amp; age--a little Princess of the Netherlands is desperately in love with their own <persName ref="#Napoleon">Buonaparte</persName>. She vows she will never marry anyone else--she will have him--she is as violently in love with him as most <del rend="squiggles" n="4" unit="word"><supplied>damsels of her age</supplied></del> heroines of her years are with a doll or a dumpling. I understand the young lady is a very promising subject--a charming haughty refractory child--full of self will &amp; attraction.--Adieu. <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> continues quite well &amp; joins with <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName> in kindest remembrances--
                  <lb/>Ever most affectionately your's
                  <lb/>M.R.M.</p>
            <!--needs to be tagged as a postscript--><p>I do not wait for a frank lest I should detain the picture--Pray write soon.--I am so glad to hear <persName ref="#Welsford_Miss">Miss Welsford</persName> is better.-Does my fair Sister Poetess ever write now.--once more Adieu my dear Friend.
           </p> 
           <closer>
               <address>
                  <!-- In this section, change to include any text written on the address leaf; use a separate "addrLine" for each line. -->
                  <addrLine>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford Bar<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></persName></addrLine>
                  <addrLine><placeName ref="#Bickham_village">Bickham</placeName></addrLine>
                  <addrLine><placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine>
               </address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         
         <!--NEW XML:ID's to be RESEARCHED:
            Elford poem. did he ever publish it?  Google search lines.
            Manfred by Byron
            Miss Welsford, "sister poetess"
            the Balcombe family
            "think a leetle" qu. Fr Sheridan?
            Tales of my Landlord by W. Scott,.which series/volume ddoes she mean?
            Edward Fairfax
            Collins quotation
            Professor Brown and his work, Cause and Effect
            filbert tree
            robin redbreast
            Bobby ( a ka Robin)
            Cranstoun or Cranstown on Napoleon (ck. SI)
            little Princess from the Netherlands.-->
            
         <!-- In this section, place any NEW xml:id's generated by this letter (ie, id's not already included in our SI), then research and write entries for each. Under resp="", use your xml:id. -->

         <listPerson type="hist">
          
                  <listPerson>
                     <person xml:id="proposed_new_ID" sex="f"><!--Project sex codes are "m", "f", "o" for other, and "u" for unknown.-->
                        <persName>
                           <surname><!--last name--></surname>
                           <forename><!--first name --></forename>
                           <forename><!--middle name --></forename>
                           <forename><!--if necessary, more middle names--></forename>
                        </persName>
                        <persName><!--alternate persName, such as a nickname?--></persName>
                        <persName><!--Use as many of these as necessary to catch alternate names of this person.--></persName>
                        <birth when="yyyy-mm-dd"><placeName><!--place of birth--></placeName></birth>
                        <death when="yyyy-mm-dd"><placeName><!--place of death--></placeName></death>
                        <!--Other tags can go here: See Codebook for more details.-->
                        <note resp="#Your_Editor_ID"><!--Biographical notes of interest. You don't need to tell the person's life story if they're already well-known, like Napoleon. But do indicate the person's significance in Mitford's world. More on this in the Site Index.--></note>
                     </person>
                     <person xml:id="proposed_new_ID2"><!--Here's a minimal entry-->
                        <persName>...</persName>
                        <note resp="#Your_Editor_ID"><!--Some information here.--></note>
                     </person>
                  </listPerson>
                  
                  <listPlace>
                     <place xml:id="proposed_new_ID3">
                        <placeName><!--best-known name of the place--></placeName>
                        <placeName><!--alternate place name--></placeName>
                        <location><geo><!--Latitude followed by longitude, separated by a white space like this:
              53.226658 -0.541254
              --></geo></location>
                     </place>
                  </listPlace>
                  <listBibl>
                     <bibl xml:id="proposed_new_ID4">
                        <title><!--Title--></title>
                        <author><!--Author--></author>
                        <editor><!--if indicated--></editor>
                        <pubPlace><!--where published--></pubPlace>
                        <publisher><!--publisher--></publisher>
                        <date when="yyyy"><!--Date. The @when attribute can be yyyy, yyyy-mm, or yyyy-mm-dd.--></date>
                     </bibl>
                  </listBibl>
                  <!--A few other kinds of lists apply. See Codebook and Site Index at http://digitalmitford.org/si.xml for guides.-->
            <person xml:id="Nicholls_John">
               <persName><forename>John</forename><surname>Nicholls</surname></persName>
               <note resp="#lmw">Author</note>
            </person>
         </listPerson>

         <listPerson type="fict">
            <!-- Use for fictional characters. -->
            <person xml:id="Catherine_Ab">
               <persName><forename>Catherine</forename></persName>
               <note resp="#lmw">Character in <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName>'s
                  novel <title ref="#Abbot_WS">The Abbott.</title></note>
            </person>
         </listPerson>

         <listPlace>
            <!-- Use for lists of new PLACES. -->
            <place xml:id="Chippenham">
               <placeName>Chippenham</placeName>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Bickham_village">
               <placeName>Bickham</placeName>
            </place>
         </listPlace>

      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>