<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt> 
            <title xml:id="MRM1773">Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1820-11-27">November 27, 1820</date></title>
            <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>
            <editor ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</editor> 
            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor>
              <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                  <persName ref="#sbb">Sylvan Baker</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Date last checked: <date when="2017-12-31">December 31, 2017</date>
               Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><!--ebb: I repaired and updated the SI references. -->
               <persName ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</persName>
               <persName ref="#sbb">Sylvan Baker</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2017-02-01">February 1, 2017</date>. P5.</edition> 
            <respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt>
            <respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>DSCF8062.jpg, DSCF8063.jpg, DSCF8064.jpg, DSCF8065.jpg, DSCF8066.jpg, DSCF8067.jpg, DSCF8068.jpg, DSCF8069.jpg, DSCF8070.jpg, DSCF8071.jpg, DSCF8072.jpg, DSCF8073.jpg, DSCF8074.jpg, DSCF8075.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.--&gt;
               </p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc> 
               <msIdentifier> 
                  <repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository>
                  <collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1820</collection>
                  <idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 424</idno><!--SCW: checked this shelfmark from spreadsheet 3/24/17--> <!--Consult Mitford letters spreadsheet (MitfordMS.xslx). Change to reflect the xml:id and shelfmark information for this ms. collection and letter. For RCL, ff. numbers differ for each letter.-->
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1820-11-27">1820 November 27</date>.
               </head> 
              
               <physDesc>
               <objectDesc>
                  <supportDesc>
                     <support> <p>  Text describing the document. Include information on the material, usually thus: <material>paper</material>7 page surfaces photographed, folded in half lengthwise, half width-wise, and again in thirds for posting, 30cm by 18cm</p>
                     </support>
                     <condition>
                        <p>Sheet torn on right edge of page seven where wax seal was removed and smudging on pages five and six.</p> 
                     </condition>
               </supportDesc>
               </objectDesc>
                  <sealDesc>
                     <p>Red wax seal, adhered to pages 4 and 5</p> 
                  </sealDesc> 
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
           <handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. A red line is drawn from top left to bottom right of each of the first three leaves. On leaf four, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right across each of the two text blocks. There is no red crayon across the address text block.</handNote>
           <handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "22" in the top left of the first leaf.
           </handNote>
        </handNotes>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
              <p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p> 
           </editorialDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener> 
               <add hand="pencil">The number "22" written in the top left of the first leaf.</add> 
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place" ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</name> 
                  <date when="1820-11-27">Nov<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> 27<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1820</date>. 
               </dateline>
               <salute>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm"/>Sir W. Elford</salute>
            </opener>
            <p> Ah my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>, we were forced to illuminate--think of that!  An illumination at <placeName>Three Mile Cross</placeName>! Forced to put up two dozen of candles upon pain of pelting &amp; rioting &amp; all manner of bad things. So we did--we were very shabby though compared to our neighbours.--one--a retired publican just below--had a fine transparency composed of a pocket handkerchief with the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>'s head upon it--a very fine head in a hat &amp; feathers cocked quite knowingly on the side--Our neighbour the Wheeler above was finer still--he had a shell work grotto in his window gaily lighted up, with the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName> in it for a hermit in the shape of a wax doll with a Friar's gown &amp;a long veil. I ventured all through the squibs to look at these curiosities, &amp; did not get blown up to the moon, as had very nearly been the case with a particular friend of mine in <placeName ref="#Oxfordshire">Oxfordshire</placeName> who was set on fire last week with a stray rocket &amp; almost frightened &amp;out of her wits. I did not go to <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>--the <emph rend="underline">squibbery</emph> there was too much to encounter, &amp; they had only one good hit in <rs type="place" ref="#Reading_city">that illustrious town</rs>. A poor Publican had had a whole length transparency of the <persName ref="#Wellington_Duke">Duke of Wellington</persName> for the Peace illumination, &amp; not knowing what to get how, he as a matter of economy hung up the <persName ref="#Wellington_Duke">noble Duke</persName> again topsy turvy--bottom upwards--a mixture of drollery &amp; lovingness which took my fancy much--&amp; certainly bad as <rs type="person" ref="#Queen_Caroline">she</rs> is, she has contrived to trip up the heels of the ministers. One of the best things that I have heard on this occasion was said by our <foreign>cidevant</foreign> neighbour the <persName ref="#Geo_SpencerChurchill">Duke of Marlborough</persName>. <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> <hi rend="superscript">You know</hi> we are famous <pb n="2"/>for <unclear><supplied>laugh</supplied></unclear> laugh <rs type="person">Duke</rs>'s hereabouts.  On being asked his opinion of the <abbr>K</abbr> and <abbr>Q</abbr>. He said <said who="#Geo_SpencerChurchill">"One's bad &amp; the other's worse"</said> <said>"Which does <persName ref="#Geo_SpencerChurchill">your Grace</persName> put first?</said> <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> "Either".--This with his stutter as <persName ref="#Marsh_Henry">Harry Marsh</persName> gives it, is an amusing piece of truth.--Another for <foreign>bon mot</foreign> of <persName ref="#Hobhouse_JC">Mr. Hobhouse</persName>'s I heard the other day--Perhaps you have <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>seen</del> <hi rend="superscript">heard</hi> it--They were accusing her of bribing the <title ref="#Times_news">Times</title> newspaper &amp; <said who="#Hobhouse_JC">he said--"Well--they have given her the <title ref="#Courier_news">Courier</title> for six years &amp; it's hard she can't have the <title ref="#Times_news">Times</title> for six months"</said>--By the way did you see a very clever parody of the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>'s <quote><soCalled>"answers"</soCalled></quote> in the Courier?  They caught Mr. <unclear reason="illegible"/> bombast exactly--I never saw better burlesque  <del rend="strikethrough"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>I</del> <hi rend="superscript">But I</hi> have the honor to wish <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>queen</del> <hi rend="superscript">her</hi> <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Majesty</persName> a good night we shall talk of a pleasanter subject. <add><metamark rend="jerk"/></add></p>
           <p> Have you seen Turner's <title ref="#Tour_Normandy">Tour in Normandy</title>? It's a pretty book to look at tales of Gothic Architecture.--&amp; not amiss to read.  There is not much new in it--but it talks away agreeably enough of old castles &amp; old Churches &amp; old walls &amp; old tombs, &amp; the charm of the subject carries one through.  Nobody can know less <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret">than</metamark>&gt;</add> I do of Gothic architecture (or any architecture) &amp; yet I love it passionately devotedly--An old cathedral is in its effect on my spirits just like <persName ref="#Milton">Milton</persName>'s poetry--absorbing, elevating <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>capturing</del>, overpowering.--If ever I get into one I don't know how to get out.--<persName ref="#Russell_M">Mother</persName> has been lately at <placeName ref="#Winchester_city">Winchester</placeName>, where they are restoring the cathedral under the directions of <persName ref="#Nott_GeorgeFr">Dr. Nott</persName>. It will be very grand when completed, &amp; they are making new discoveries every day.  Above all they have realized a supposition of <persName ref="#Milner_John">Mr. Milner</persName>'s which because it was in that entertaining mass of miracles &amp; papistry <rs type="person" ref="#Milner_John">his</rs> history of <placeName ref="#Winchester_city">Winchester</placeName> nobody believed--They have discovered under the old tower a Roman foundation--real genuine masonry--thus giving a colour to the <pb n="3"/>worthy Bishop's notion that the Church was built on the <unclear><supplied resp="#SBB">piles</supplied></unclear> of a Roman Temple--&amp; in clearing out the <unclear reason="illegible"/> which had been filled up for years with all sorts of rubbish several very fine mitred heads (&amp; their bodies too as far as I know) have been discovered--the most perfect specimen monastic <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> sculpture that have been found--they are taking casts of them. In the meantime the Chapter are vowing vengeance against <persName ref="#Nott_GeorgeFr">Mr. Nott</persName> for spending so much money-- &amp; <rs type="person" ref="#Nott_GeorgeFr">he</rs> on his part now that all has been pulled about &amp; <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> must be set to rights again, feels quite secure in his vocation &amp; has been <unclear><supplied resp="#SBB">terrifying</supplied></unclear> about <placeName>Normandy</placeName><!--SBB: I'm assuming htis is meant to be Normandy, France?  Not in SI--> <rs type="person" ref="#Nott_GeorgeFr">himself</rs> picking up new old ideas &amp; setting his prebendal brethren at defiance.--The Cathedral was to have <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>been so</add> opened this Autumn with a musick meeting--instead of which it is all to pieces, cannot possibly be finished for these two years &amp; will very probably not be completed in half a dozen.  I am heartily glad of this, for these Prebends are all as rich as Jews (few of them I believe with less than four or five thousand a year Church Preferment) &amp; its a fine thing to see that noble &amp; almost loss but flourishing again under the auspices of the Church <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> its ancient and munificent patroness. Don't you think so? <add><metamark rend="jerk"/></add> </p>
            
            <p> <rs type="person" ref="#Elford_SirWm">My dear friend</rs> do you read magazines?  If you do not pray begin--all the best writing is in them--the best criticism &amp; the best essays--the best fun.  I don't mean the old magazine of course, nor half of the new--but some are capital.  There's <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood</title>'s <title ref="#EdinburghRev_per">Edinburgh</title> for instance with its audacious impudence &amp; its deep &amp; most <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> intensely felt articles on German literature--its exceedingly good in <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood</title>'s magazine-- <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Scott's</persName> wife's in it you know, (<persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Sir Walter</persName>)--&amp; <persName ref="#North_Christopher">Wilson</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Lockhart_JG">Lockhart</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Gillies_Rob">Gillies</persName> &amp; all the <title ref="#EdinburghRev_per">Edinburgh</title> young wits--youth indeed is its prime characteristic--there is an infusion of new blood in <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood</title>'s magazine the effect of which is strongly felt in reading one of his numbers just after a number of the <title ref="#EdinburghRev_per"/>--one feels that the review is grown sober &amp; elderly &amp; gray haired--it walks with a stick &amp; wears spectacles.--Then there is a magazine that I like better still than <title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood</title>'s, <persName ref="#Baldwin_R">Baldwin</persName>'s <title ref="#LondonMag">London</title>--The impudence there is quite as great but more polished--there is all the difference between <title ref="#LondonMag">London</title> <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> &amp; a provincial town-- <persName ref="#Baldwin_R">Baldwin</persName>'s brass is of the finest sort of  Corinthian brass--<title ref="#Blackwoods">Blackwood</title>'s is of baser metal. <persName ref="#Lamb_Chas">Charles Lamb</persName> writes there too with his delicate humour, so quiet &amp; graceful &amp; genial &amp; full of fine humanities--&amp; <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName>--always so delightful. I would not give up the <title ref="#LondonMag">London</title> magazine (<persName ref="#Baldwin_R"><emph rend="underline">Baldwin</emph></persName>'s <title ref="#LondonMag">London</title> for there is <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> another <hi rend="superscript">Simon Pure</hi>)--no--not for the Scotch novels!--Then there is the <title ref="#New_Monthly_Mag">New Monthly</title> which used to be so bad--My particular friend &amp; crony <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName> had taken that in hand since last February &amp; his articles are exquisite-- particularly his dramatic criticisms--Those &amp; indeed all that he writes are distinguished by a peculiar spirit of cordiality &amp; indulgence-- <rs type="person" ref="#Talfourd_Thos">he</rs> is as various &amp; distinguished in his praise, as other critics are in their censure--you feel that all that he says is fine to the very essence --his likenesses are perfect but <rs type="person" ref="#Talfourd_Thos">he</rs> takes people at their best &amp; sets forth their beauties instead of their defects. I never met--not even in <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName> with just lenient sympathy--such indulgence to human frailty--or such cordial delight in the beautiful &amp; the good.  With all this <rs type="person" ref="#Talfourd_Thos">his</rs> writings are quite as entertaining as if he cut all he touched to mince meat like <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName>.  But it is the nature of the man--he has a talent for admiration &amp; enjoyment--He is to be called to the Bar next term &amp; I prophesy that the world will soon hear of him. I am <pb n="4"/>sure of his ultimate success but I particularly wish him to make his way soon, because he has been engaged these three years to a sweet young woman, one quite worthy of him, &amp; those long engagements are <unclear><supplied resp="#sbb">hardwearing</supplied></unclear> things. In case you or <persName ref="#Elford_MrsE">Mrs. Elford</persName> should see the <title ref="#New_Monthly_Mag">New Monthly</title> I enclose you a list of his articles--for except his there are none worth reading. You will forgive the flattery about me. We are old friends you know. <add><metamark rend="jerk"/></add> </p>
              
            <p>Do you ever paint game and dogs?  An adventure happened to my little pet <rs type="animal" ref="#Molly_pet">Molly</rs>--(the pretty little Spaniel with long curling hair--so white &amp; delicate &amp; ladylike, that you admired so much when I had last the happiness of seeing you) which would make a pretty picture. <rs type="animal" ref="#Molly_pet">Molly</rs> was beating a hedgerow about a month ago &amp; jumped upon a pheasant--caught hold of it's tail--&amp; held so fast that the bird being a strong old cock &amp; making great efforts for <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> <hi rend="superscript">his</hi> life fairly lifted her up in <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> the air--the struggle lasted till the feathers gave way &amp; the pheasant flew off leaving the honors of his plummage as spoil to poor Molly. <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> says the sight was beautiful-- that it happened in a very fine spot just under an oak pollard with ivy &amp; holly &amp; fern--contrasting its <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> <hi rend="superscript">orange leaves</hi>, &amp; the dog &amp; the bird both glittering like gold &amp; silver in a bright autumnal sun.--Goodnight my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName>--I shall finish in a day or two--Goodnight--God bless you, <rs type="person" ref="#Elford_SirWm">my dear friend</rs>--<add><metamark rend="line"/></add></p>
                 
            <p>Tuesday Evening--I really am ashamed of this hand writing though I have found a delicious precedent for illegible calligraphy (is that fine word right?) In Fleury's <title ref="#Napoleon_memoir_nonfict">Memoires de Napoleon</title>--He had prepared in Elba proclamatiions for his landing &amp; gave them to his secretary &amp; soldiers to copy when on board the <unclear><supplied resp="#sbb">King</supplied></unclear>--they could not read them, &amp; gave them to him begging him to decipher such &amp; such words--He could <pb n="5"/> not read a syllable of them--but after puzzling for a moment threw them into the sea &amp; began to dictate afresh those eloquent addresses which will last as long as the language.  What a foundation to write a bad hand!  Is it not?  But <emph><foreign>chez les aveugles un langue<!--SCW: I can't identify this word in the ms--> est roi</foreign></emph><!--SCW: I corrected a couple of words in this French passage, only one I can't identify. I think what she's saying is something to the effect of "Among the blind, the one-eyed man is king"-->--so I pass for a good writer here <unclear reason="illegible"/> <unclear reason="illegible"/> you--you have no notion of the style of manuscript that prevails in this South of<placeName ref="#Berkshire">Berkshire</placeName>--all the young ladies letters look like lines of ms &amp; <unclear><supplied resp="#sbb">us</supplied></unclear>--&amp; one in particular--that identical friend of mine who was half blown up the other day comes every week to exactly the same disgrace with <persName ref="#Napoleon">Napoleon</persName>. Not content with knowing French very well in the old way she is learning it over again in a Monsieur Da-Da (I don't know his name--<persName>Dafief</persName>--I believe--or something like it) Monsieur Da's newfangled method-- <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>by</del> in which the patient (I beg pardon the pupil--one is so apt to mistake one kind of quackery for another) first writes a French sentence &amp; then reads it aloud--how poor Eliza never could read her own writing in her life--so she stands suspected of being a dunce (which is  great mistake) every Saturday night.--I shall certainly send you on one of her notes some day just as a foil to set off my clearness.--Or rather to show you that there are people who write worse--a fact respecting which you are rather sceptical.  In the mean time I rely on your indulgence &amp; <persName ref="#Elford_MrsE">Mrs. E. Elford</persName>'s--she who is so very good to <rs type="person" ref="#MRM">your poor little friend</rs>. <add><metamark rend="jerk"/></add></p>
            
            <p>I see <persName ref="#Elford_MrsE">Mr. Elford</persName> is emancipated from his parlimentary chains--those chains of roses of which every body but yourself is so fond--they're I think the jigging backwards &amp; forwards this Summer &amp; Autumn must have fired the distant members exceedingly--Even <persName ref="#Monck_JB">Mr. Monck</persName> who lives so near began to complain.--By the way I hope that excellent person will look to his parting this time--for I shall put it in his power to make a notable mistake an opportunity which to do him justice he very seldom makes. I have just finished a packet for <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> &amp; hers &amp; yours will go to him together--How you will share or you get <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName>'s.  She &amp; I have a perpetual small commerce of needle work-- I am the better artist on muslin--she is a consummate milliner--so I work her frills &amp; flounces &amp; she makes my hats &amp; caps--The present packet consists first of breadth of a frill with directions how to join it to the other half (which went last week) &amp; how to make it up.-- Secondly of thanks for an announced new bonnet--&amp; hints for the construction of the same--(Lord how you would laugh at all this grave palaver about gauze &amp; satin!)--Thirdly of a long engagement about coaches &amp;--(<rs type="person" ref="#James_Miss">She</rs> is coming here in February on her return from <placeName ref="#Birmingham_city">Birmingham</placeName> <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="chars"/> had hoped she come going).  Fourthly of an offer to he <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="chars"/> sister Emily of seeds for her garden (sweetpeas--China aster &amp; mignonettes &amp; such varieties)-- fifthly of an able article, though I say it that should not say it, on <persName ref="#Brown_Thos">Sir Thomas Brown</persName>'s Vulgar Wars (<rs type="person" ref="#James_Miss">She</rs> is as old English mad as I)-- There's a package for you--if you should get it!!!-- Goodbye <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">my dear friend</persName>! Kindest regards from all here, &amp; my most respectful compliements to <persName ref="#Elford_MrsE">Mrs. E. Elford</persName>.--I write very soon &amp; very long--you see how obedient I am--</p> 
               
        
            <closer>&amp; believe me ever<lb/>
               very affectionately your's<lb/> 
               <persName ref="#MRM">M. R. Mitford</persName>. 
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
     
     <back>
        <div>
             
      <!--2017-12-31 ebb: I've posted all the new site index entries from this letter in the site index.-->
    
          
     </div>
     </back>
  </text>
</TEI>