<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>**Page 1** ?? Sir. W. Elford           ???
                                          Jan.y 3rd 1822.
                           This is the first real absolute letter ?
            that are ? ? ? ? ? and so forth ?
            ? in their ? and the first genuine letter that I have set 
            down to write in 1822 and ? ? ? ? to one of the 
            kindest ? of my correspondents. Your very long and delightful
            letter gives the best ? ? of life and spirits, and I
            adore(?) you, my dear Sir William, it is quite a consolation
            to think of a dear friend who is well and happy. ? ?
            ? ? I ? ? has been fatal to many of my
            oldest and most valued ? - In three weeks I have to
            console(?) with three correspondents on the death of a father or a
            mother - my kindest ? ? friend ? ? being
            one of them - Well I will not sadden you by talking of sad
            things ? so you have a real ? to see my ? -
            I have the strongest ? ? to ? you and if
            ? by ?, ?, stealing or otherways(?) procure a Reading
            paper of that week you shall have it. My own copy I have seen
            ? out of in a very atrocious manner - But I certainly
            will get one for you if I can, because ? like you to see
            ? ? epilogue(?) which is capital(?) in one way, and my
            critique which is ? ? famous in another - I think you cannot
            fail to be ? at the very ? face and ? and ?
            dignity which I put on for the occasion - you have no
            notion what as easy thing it is to seem learned(?). - As to my
            own play - what part of my tragic-comical ? did I
            tell you? Where were we in that equally ? and comical
            ? ? ? ? you that the play was written ? ?
            **Page 2** which seemed excellent for three principal characters - young
            Charles ? and ? - that Charles ? from
            disgust at the other two had ????, and that in correspondence(?)
            of alterations ressorted(?) by for ? Mr. Young's character
            had become too ? for a man of his dignity - in
            in language of a ? my second had ? with
            my first and my third - and my third had my first.
            The consequence of all this was easy to foresee - the play was
            presented to ? ?, and after a great deal of hesitation
            ? in terms of that praise and admiration, as would have
            ? ? any ? who wrote from Vanity - IN(?) ? ?
            for my consolation that no refusal was ever so much like 
            an acceptance - that ? ? actually ? it to a 
            Tragedy which he has taken(?) - and that, in short, it has been
            ? merely because the state of the performers is such
            that it could not be acted with a fair chance of ?. This
            is you see very poor(?) consolation - Indeed a am not ? whether
            ? have come so very near the ? is not more ?
            than to have ? failed - One comfort however there is - this
            play has certainly cleared the way for most respectful attention
            to any price that I may send in ? - And I have accordingly
            already begun another Tragedy on a story ? imagining 
            which I intend to write without any ? for the ? ? ? 
            Charles ?, with one leading character for Mr. ?
            and a number of inferior ones which may be filled up my any
            walking (?) gentleman - walking(?) ? they might call them - which
            the Theatre may happen to have in ?. Don't you think I am
            very ? and ? ? ? praise ? - and pity me - I am
            forced to pity myself sometimes ? ? never het on ?
            - I have entirely lost the ? which I need to ? ten years
            **Page 3** ago and write with a ? a ? a ? that
            seem almost ? - besides ? every thing ? -
            - nothing but the certain convicion that I should fail hinders me
            from trying a Comedy. ? ? says ? succeed (?) - but I
            cannot think so - I will at all events try another Tragedy first
            ? Have you read the Pirate (?) And do you like it? I think
            you will say no to both questions - you have not probably yet
            had time to read it - and you have heard enough of the story to be
            pretty sure that you shall not like it. I don't at all. There is
            a great deal too much about ? ? and ?
            manners (?), and ? ? - and there is an old witch who
            would of herself be enough to spoil the finest thing that
            ever was written. What a ? the great ? ? for a
            witch! ? believe this ? is the 9th or 10th of that
            ? which he has produced - and of all of them she is the
            worst (?), by far the worst (?) - he has given her a poem in prose
            to recite after the fashion of ? ? ? and those 
            sort of people - and there is ? a quantity (?) of her too! Altogether
            ??? is perhaps nearly on a par (?) with the later works (?) - for there
            has been nothing very great since ? (notwithstanding
            the beauty of one or two ? in the ?) - nothing like
            the ? and ? ? ? and ? -
            the ? being to my taste (?) the one and ? of them
            all. (My the bye in an article (?) which ? strangely at
            ? ? of the ? ? in the last ? ?
            ? and ? and the high comic character called the
            "fool" and "the ?" - What manner of taste (?) call you this?)
            - One of the best things in the ? is some excellent ?
            on the subject of breeding (?) ? and ? - and the best
            ? seems to be that where ? ? produces her boiled goose (?)
            **Page 4** to feast ? ? but then the witch comes in - ??
            end on(?) - as ? ? would say - I thoroughly agree wtih
            you, for your reasons and others, as to the certainty of the ?
            being written by ? ? ?, and thank you very much for your
            transcript(?) ??'s charming anecdote. ? yes the
            second Vol. of the sketch book is certainly a little Americanist
            - a little heavy - a little ? - and very ? and unfaithful(?) in
            his ? details - Mr. Washington ? is excellent in
            humour(?), and in old watch ? and other American diversities - but
            he must not meddle with ? us proud English - I wish he would
            give an American novel(?) with all the peculiarities the vulgarities
            adn the affectations of that ridiculous country. We have a fine
            specimen of New York manners close by - a rich friend of ours was
            taken in by ? ? ?'s fine plausible(?) his (there's a glorious
            illustration of my system(?) for you - that book of ? ? ?
            ? as Robinson(?) ?!) and intending to embark some ? or ? 40,000(?)
            in the Illinois, sent out a son of seventeen to ?. ?
            ?'s fine antidote and other accounts soon determined him to keep
            him money in England - but the son staid on - not in the Illinois
            that disagreed with him - but in New York - and is only lately
            returned - a very good sort of young man I believe, but the most
            complete transatlantic ? that ever eyes beheld. He is
            somenm, smooth and smirking - smiling like ?'s though not
            like him ? - superficial as a newspaper or a ?
            talking in a strange outlandish jargon(?) half of it too fine for ?
            wear and half too ? - a mixture of ? and ? cloth - ?
            to a ? degree - he never sees you seated but he ? ?
            ottoman under your feet, or standing, or walking ? ? a
            chair down behind you - so that the singer(?) at a piano ?
            finds herself blockaded by a double row of ? seats -  ? his
            cloakings and ? are worse than any cow(?) and he walks in a dancing ?
            
            **Page 5**Jan.y 9th I have at last succeeded in borrowing a Reading 
            paper -- but as I can(?) only get it on promising to return it I 
            must give you the ? to send it back to me when you ?
            read it. you ? find mention made of a little boy of the name
            of Richardson who ? a part in the ?, ?, and 
            the epilogue (?)-- I never saw in my life so much promise of dramatic 
            talent-- talk of the young ? ! Look at little Richardson--
            he is the ? of ? master at reading; who on their 
            ? signed in the ?, and really one of the most 
            delightful facts of the evening was to watch the ?
            ? master's ? of joy which followed every ? sword(?)
            and movement of this lovely boy - I have just been reading
            Lord Byron's plays - The Two ? of ? was the first
            object with me - but he has taken ? the ? just where I 
            left it off, so that it was not at all ? with ?. The ?
            is well ? I think - but young ? notwithstanding ?
            good speeches is utterly imbecile - an ultra fundamental ?
            ? no one knows why or ? with a love like ? to the
            country which has disgraced ? and ? and finishes by killing
            him - and his wife ? is mere scold(?). Both ? and ?
            are ? wise(?) drawn(?) and ? ? - one is really quite ?
            in reading them(?). Cain(?) is of a higher strain - and yet though there
            is nothing in it ? then Milton(?) has put into the month of
            his ? one is ? shocked at ?'s ???
            mever happens in Paradise Lost. The ? is different - 
            I don't know why but it is so. Altogether it seems to me that the
            Drama is not his ? - he has mo spirit of dialogue(?) - no beauty(?)
            in his groupings(?) - none of that fine misture of the ?
            with the ? which constitutes stage(?) effect in ? the
            best ? of the ? - and a long series of ? ? speeches. I(?)
            
            **Page 6** ? antitheses(?) will very ?? for the want of that
            excellence which we find in Sophocles and in Shakespeare and ?
            you will call ? and I shall call back(?) - ? ? you ?
            ? animals? We have a Greyhound called May-Flower of excellencce ?
            grace and ? symmetry - just of the colour of the May blossom(?) - like
            marble(?) with the ? upon it - and she kills every ? she sees
            
            takes them up in the middle of the back and swings(?) them in her mouth
            to my father and lays them down at his feet - ? ? she ?
            a ? whilst bringing the ? - the fine contrast of colour - her
            beautiful position, head and tail up and her long(?) neck arched like
            that of a ? - with the ? shifting upon her beautiful limbs(?)
            and her black eyes really emitting light. I wish you could see May-
            Flower. Farewell my dear friend - I have only soon to ? how much ? always(?)???
         </p> 
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
