<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng"
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng" 
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
        

         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="#OV">Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title>
            <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>


            <editor ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</editor>
            <editor ref="#ad">Alexandra Drayton</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#jmh">Jonathan M. Horanic</persName>
               <persName ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--2017-01-10 ebb: We need to change this sourceDesc to indicate we’re checking each text and altering it to represent the 1824 edition as published in NCCO. -->
            <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
            <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                  <title ref="#OV">Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third
                     Edition</edition> by <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author><pubPlace ref="#London_city">London</pubPlace><publisher ref="#Whittaker_Geo">Geo. B.
                     Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
               </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first
               edition published in 1824. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="sketch">
            <pb n="250"/>
            <head><title level="a" ref="#Aunt_Martha_OV">AUNT MARTHA</title>. <!--ebb: If there’s a subtitle use an <lb/> element to separate -->
            </head>
            <p>One of the pleasantest habitations I have ever known is an old white house, built at
               right angles, with the pointed roofs and clustered chimneys of <persName ref="#ElizI">Elizabeth</persName>’s day,
               covered with <rs type="plant" ref="#rose">roses</rs>, <rs type="plant" ref="#vine">vines</rs>, and <rs type="plant" ref="#passion_flower"/>passion-flowers, and parted by a green sloping meadow
               from a straggling picturesque village street. In this charming abode resides a more
               charming <orgName ref="#AuntMartha_family_OV">family</orgName>: a <persName ref="#AuntMartha_patriarch_OV">gentleman</persName>, <quote> “<l>Polite as all his life in courts
                  had been,</l> <l>And good as he the world had never seen;</l>“ </quote><note resp="#scw">This quotation is an adaptation of lines 3-4 of <persName ref="#Lyttelton_Geo">George Lyttleton</persName>'s <title level="a" ref="#Verses_EpitaphSameLady_Lyt">Verses Making Part of an Epitaph on the Same Lady</title>. In the original poem, the subject is gendered female.</note> <orgName ref="#AuntMartha_nieces_OV">two daughters</orgName>
               full of sweetness and talent; and <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">aunt Martha</persName>—the most delightful of old maids! She
               has another appellation, I suppose,—she must have one;—but I scarcely know it: <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">Aunt
                  Martha</persName> is the name that belongs to her—the name of affection. Such is the universal
               feeling which she inspires, that all her friends, all her acquaintances, (in this
               case the terms are almost synonymous,) speak of her like her own family:—she<pb n="251"/> is every body’s <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">Aunt Martha</persName>—and a very charming <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">Aunt Martha</persName> she is.</p>
            <p>First of all, she is, as all women should be if they can, remarkably handsome. She
               may be—it is a delicate matter to speak of a lady’s age!—she must be five-and-forty;
               but few beauties of twenty could stand a comparison with her loveliness. It is such a
               fulness of bloom, so luxuriant, so satiating; just tall enough to carry off the
               plumpness which at forty-five is so becoming; a brilliant complexion; curled pouting
               lips! long, clear, bright grey eyes—the colour for expression, that which unites the
               quickness of the black with the softness of the blue; a Roman regularity of feature;
               and a profusion of rich brown hair.—Such is <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">Aunt Martha</persName>. Add to this a very gentle
               and pleasant speech, always kind, and generally lively; the sweetest temper; the
               easiest manners; a singular rectitude and singleness of mind; a perfect
               open-heartedness; and a total unconsciousness of all these charms; and you will
               wonder a little that she is <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">Aunt Martha</persName> still. I have heard hints of an early
               engagement broken by the fickleness of man;—and there is about her an aversion to
               love in one particular direction—the love matrimonial—and an overflowing of affection
               in all other channels, that it seems as if the natural course of the stream had been
               violently dammed up. She has many lovers—admirers I should say,—for there is, amidst
                  her<pb n="252"/> good-humoured gaiety, a coyness that forbids their going farther;
               a modesty almost amounting to shyness, that checks even the laughing girls, who
               sometimes accuse her of stealing away their beaux. I do not think any man on earth
               could tempt her into wed-lock;—it would be a most unpardonable monopoly if any one
               should; an intolerable engrossing of a general blessing; a theft from the whole
               community.</p>
            <p>Her usual home is the white house covered with roses; and her station in the <orgName ref="#AuntMartha_family_OV">family</orgName>
               is rather doubtful. She is not the mistress, for her <orgName ref="#AuntMartha_nieces_OV">charming nieces</orgName> are old enough
               to take and to adorn the head of the table; nor the <persName ref="#AuntMartha_housekeeper_OV">housekeeper</persName>, though, as she is
               the only lady of the establishment who wears pockets, those ensigns of authority, the
               keys will sometimes be found, with other strays, in that goodly receptacle: nor a
               guest; her spirit is too active for that lazy post; her real vocation there, and
               every where, seems to be comforting, cheering, welcoming, and spoiling every thing
               that comes in her way; and, above all, nursing and taking care. Of all kind
               employments, these are her favourites. Oh the shawlings, the cloakings, the
               cloggings! the cautions against cold, or heat, or rain, or sun! the remedies for
               diseases not arrived! colds uncaught! incipient tooth-aches! rheumatisms to come! She
               loves nursing so well, that we used to accuse her of inventing maladies for other
               people, that she might have the pleasure<pb n="253"/> of curing them; and when they
               really come—as come they will sometimes in spite of <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">Aunt Martha</persName>—what a nurse she is!
               It is worth while to be a little sick to be so attended. All the <orgName ref="#AuntMartha_cousins_OV">cousins, and
                  cousins’ cousins</orgName> of her connection, as regularly send for her on the occasion of a
               lying-in, as for the midwife. I suppose she has undergone the ceremony of dandling
               the baby, sitting up with the new mamma, and dispensing the caudle, twenty times at
               least. She is equally important at weddings or funerals. Her humanity is
               inexhaustible. She has an intense feeling of fellowship with her kind, and grieves or
               rejoices in the sufferings or happiness of others with a reality as genuine as it is
               rare.</p>
            <p>Her accomplishments are exactly of this sympathetic order; all calculated to
               administer much to the pleasure of her companions, and nothing to her own importance
               or vanity. She leaves to the sirens, her <orgName ref="#AuntMartha_nieces_OV">nieces</orgName>, the higher enchantments of the
               piano, the harp, and the guitar, and that noblest of instruments, the human voice;
               ambitious of no other musical fame than such as belongs to the playing of quadrilles
               and waltzes for their little dances, in which she is indefatigable: she neither
               caricatures the face of man nor of nature under pretence of drawing figures or
               landscapes; but she ornaments the reticules, bell-ropes, ottomans, and chair-covers
               of all her acquaintance, with flowers as rich and luxuriant as her own beauty. She
               draws patterns for the igno-<pb n="254"/>rant, and works flounces, frills, and
               baby-linen, for the idle; she reads aloud to the sick, plays at cards with the old,
               and loses at chess to the unhappy. Her gift in gossiping, too, is extraordinary; she
               is a gentle newsmonger, and turns her scandal on the sunny side. But she is an old
               maid still; and certain small peculiarities hang about her. She is a thorough
               hoarder: whatever fashion comes up, she is sure to have something of the sort by
               her—or, at least, something thereunto convertible. She is a little superstitious;
               sees strangers in her tea-cup, gifts in her finger-nails, letters and winding-sheets
               in the candle, and purses and coffins in the fire; would not spill the salt <quote>“for all
                  the worlds that one ever has to give;”</quote><note resp="#scw">This is a slight misquote from <title level="m" ref="#Emma_JA">Emma</title>, volume II, chapter 10. It is spoken by <persName ref="#Churchill_Frank_JA">Frank Churchill</persName> to <persName ref="#Fairfax_Jane_JA">Jane Fairfax</persName>.</note> and looks with dismay on a crossed knife and
               fork. Moreover, she is orderly to fidgetiness;—that is her greatest calamity!—for
               young ladies now-a-days are not quite so tidy as they should be,—and ladies’ maids
               are much worse; and drawers are tumbled, and drawing-rooms in a litter. Happy she to
               whom a disarranged drawer can be a misery! Dear and happy <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">Aunt Martha</persName>!</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listPerson sortKey="fictPersons">
            <person xml:id="AuntMartha_patriarch_OV" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#AuntMartha_patriarch_OV">Aunt Martha patriarch</persName>
               <note resp="#scw">The beloved patriarch of the household in which <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">Aunt Martha</persName> lives in <title level="a" ref="#Aunt_Martha_OV">Aunt Martha</title>. He may be the fictionalized portrait of <persName ref="#Webb_James">James Webb</persName>.</note>
               
            </person>
            <person xml:id="AuntMartha_housekeeper_OV">
               <persName ref="#AuntMartha_housekeeper_OV">Aunt Martha housekeeper</persName>
               <occupation type="service" subtype="housekeeper"/>
               <note resp="#scw">Character of the housekeeper mentioned in <title level="a" ref="#Aunt_Martha_OV">Aunt Martha</title>.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Churchill_Frank_JA" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Churchill_Frank_JA">Frank Churchill
                  <surname>Churchill</surname>
                  <forename>Francis</forename>
                  <forename type="nick">Frank</forename>
               </persName>
               <note resp="#scw">Character in <title level="m" ref="#Emma_JA">Emma</title> who flirts with the title character.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Fairfax_Jane_JA" sex="f">
               <persName ref="#Fairfax_Jane_JA">Jane Fairfax
                  <surname>Fairfax</surname>
                  <forename>Jane</forename>
               </persName>
               <note resp="#scw">Character in <title level="m" ref="#Emma_JA">Emma</title> who has little money or prospects.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Martha_Aunt_OV" sex="f">
               <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">Aunt Martha
                  <surname>not given</surname>
                  <forename>Martha</forename>
               </persName>
               <note resp="#scw">Title character of <title level="a" ref="#Aunt_Martha_OV">Aunt Martha</title>, who is described as a beloved unmarried member of a <persName ref="#AuntMartha_patriarch_OV">a gentleman</persName> and <orgName ref="#AuntMartha_nieces_OV">his daughters</orgName>' household. It has been speculated that she is a fictionalized portrait of <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_elder">Mary Webb</persName>.</note>
            </person>
            
         </listPerson>
         
         <listPerson sortKey="histPersons">
            <person xml:id="Lyttelton_Geo" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Lyttelton_Geo">George Lyttleton
                  <surname>Lyttelton</surname>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <roleName><date from="1756" to="1773"/>1st Baron Lyttelton</roleName>
                  <roleName>Sir George Lyttelton, 5th Baronet<date from="1751" to="1773"/></roleName>
               </persName>
               <birth when="1709-01-17"><placeName>Hagley, Worcestershire</placeName></birth>
               <death when="1773-08-22"><placeName>Hagley, Worcestershire</placeName></death>
               <occupation type="government"/> 
               <occupation type="literary" subtype="poet"/>
               <note resp="#scw">Whig Member of Parliament for Okehampton between <date when="1735">1735</date> and <date when="1756">1756</date>, Lyttelton held several political positions, including Chancellor of the Exchecquer from <date when="1755">1755</date> to <date when="1756">1756</date>. He was also a poet and patron of artists and other poets, praised by <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Alexander Pope</persName>, and the dedicatee of <title level="m" ref="#TomJones_HF">Tom Jones</title>. While his own works were generally published in edited anthologies, during the nineteenth century, he was chiefly remembered for his elegies written for his first wife.</note>
            </person>
         </listPerson>
         
         <listOrg sortKey="fictOrgs">
            <org xml:id="AuntMartha_cousins_OV">
               <orgName ref="#AuntMartha_cousins_OV"/>
               <note resp="#scw">The group of characters mentioned in <title level="a" ref="#Aunt_Martha_OV">Aunt Martha</title> who call for the title character to help them with their lyings-in.</note>
            </org>
            
            <org xml:id="AuntMartha_family_OV"><!--scw: comparing more closely the facts of the Webb family with this sketch, I think Needham's speculation that this sketch is based on the Webbs is suspect. However, in the SI, the info is framed as his speculation, not as fact.-->
               <orgName ref="#AuntMartha_family_OV">Aunt Martha family</orgName>
               <note resp="#scw">The family with whom <persName ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">Aunt Martha</persName> lives in <title level="a" ref="#Aunt_Martha_OV">Aunt Martha</title>. While they are unnamed in the sketch, it has been suggested that they are the fictional counterparts of <persName ref="#Webb_James">James Webb</persName>'s family, all of whom were good friends of <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>. The sketch mentions two daughters, but the Webbs had three: <persName ref="#Webb_James">James Webb</persName>, <persName ref="#Webb_Jane">Jane</persName>, <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName>, and <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName>.</note>
            </org>
            
            <org xml:id="AuntMartha_nieces_OV">
               <orgName ref="#AuntMartha_nieces_OV"/>
               <note resp="#scw">In <title level="a" ref="#Aunt_Martha_OV">Aunt Martha</title>, these are the <rs type="person" ref="#Martha_Aunt_OV">title character</rs>'s two nieces in whose household she lives. These characters may the fictional counterparts of two of the Webb girls, <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName>, <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName>, or <persName ref="#Webb_Jane">Jane</persName>.</note>
            </org>
            
            
         </listOrg>
         
         <list sortKey="plants">
            <item xml:id="passion_flower"/>
            <item xml:id="vine"/>
         </list>
         
         <listBibl sortKey="schol">
            <bibl xml:id="Our_Miss_Austen">
               <title level="a" ref="#Our_Miss_Austen">Our Miss Austen: Jane Austen and Mary Russell Mitford--A New Appraisal</title>
               <title level="j">Persuasions: The Jane Austen Journal</title>
               <author>Azar Hussain</author>
               <date when="2018">2018</date>
               <biblScope unit="volume">40</biblScope>
               <biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="254">238-254</biblScope>
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl xml:id="Verses_EpitaphSameLady_Lyt">
               <title level="a" ref="#Verses_EpitaphSameLady_Lyt">Verses Making Part of an Epitaph on the Same Lady</title>
               <title level="m">A Collection of Poems in Six Volumes. By Several Hands.</title>
               <author ref="#Lyttelton_Geo">George Lyttelton</author>
               <editor>Robert Dodsley</editor>
               <publisher>J. Hughs</publisher>
               <pubPlace ref="#London_city"><date when="1757"/></pubPlace>
               <note resp="#scw">A twelve-line elegy to <persName ref="#Lyttelton_Geo">George Lyttelton</persName>'s first wife, which also became the inscription on her tombstone. It was much-quoted (and misquoted) into the nineteenth century, often with the gender changed to male and outside the context of elegy.</note>
            </bibl>
            
         </listBibl>
         
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>