<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>"Introduction" to Dramatic Works [1854]</title>
            <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>

            <editor>Lisa M. Wilson</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName>

            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><!--ebb: 6 July 2014 Code has been proofed so far. Text still needs review. Requesting addition of editorial notes.--> <!-- Text proofed by RN, summer 2015 -->
           <persName ref="#rnes">Rebecca Nesvet</persName>
               <persName ref="#ds">Daniel Schierenbeck</persName><!--DS:  REVIEWED against ms., 2016-10-04 --><!--LMW: made corrections. Finished 2016-10-05-->
               <!--LMW: made additional corrections 2017-06-24 -->
               
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and "should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version": First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 July 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName/>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Our text is based on <bibl><title ref="#Intro_DW">"Introduction" to <title ref="#Dramatic_Works_of_MRM">The Dramatic Works of Mary
                     Russell Mitford</title> in 2 vols.</title> by <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author>
               <pubPlace ref="#London_city">London</pubPlace><publisher><orgName ref="#Hurst_Blackett_pub">Hurst and Blackett</orgName></publisher>,
                  Publishers, Successors to <orgName ref="#H_Colburn_pub">Henry Colburn</orgName>, <placeName>13, Great Marborough
                        Street</placeName>
                  <date when="1854">1854</date>
               </bibl></p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <!--LMW: Elisa, I put in page break tags as usual; the original uses roman numeral pagination and the first body paragraph begins on volume one, page ii (not one). -->
         <div type="book">
            <head>Introduction</head>

            <p>EVER since <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Pope</persName>'s famous couplet, the solemn protestations of authors that they print at the <quote>request of friends,</quote> has been held to be a false and cowardly pretence, and scorned and derided accordingly. <note resp="#lmw">In <bibl><title ref="#PopetoArbuthnot"><q>An Epistle from Mr. Pope to Dr. Arbuthnot</q></title></bibl> <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Pope</persName> writes of a starving author who <quote>Rymes e're he wakes, and prints before Term ends,/Oblig'd by hunger and Request of friends</quote> (ll. 43-44).</note>Now and then, however, that most improbable assertion happens to be true--in the present instance it undoubtedly is so. For the publication of these volumes, <rs type="person" ref="#Bennoch_Fr">the excellent friend</rs>to whom they are inscribed <note resp="#lmw">The Dedication reads <quote>Francis Bennoch, Esq. in whose life great public services blend so happily with all that is graceful and genial in private hospitality: who, munificent patron of poet and of painter, is the first to proclaim every talent except his own: to him, valued alike as companion and as friend, these volumes are most respectfully and affectionately inscribed by The Author</quote>.</note> is solely accountable: a heavy weight of responsibility which he will redeem, some day or other, by giving to the world lyrics of his own writing that nobody will wish shorter.</p>
            
            <p>How he chanced upon these plays of mine, I hardly know. I think he picked them up in the library of a great <choice><sic>country-house</sic><reg>country house</reg></choice> where he was visiting. They had fallen into such utter oblivion, <pb n="2"/>that I also might have forgotten them, but for an occasional dream, too vague to be called a hope, that in the brief moment of kindly indulgence, which follows the death of any one who has contributed, however slightly, to the public amusement, some friend might gather them together in the same spirit that prompts the stringing verses into an epitaph. To <choice><sic>edite</sic><reg resp="#lmw">edit</reg></choice> <note resp="#lmw">Alternate spelling in original. The <title ref="#OED">OED Online</title> cites a <persName ref="#Southey_R">Southey</persName> use of <quote>"re-edite"</quote> from 1807; there is no entry for <quote>"edite."</quote></note> these tragedies myself, seems a kind of anachronism, not unlike engraving the inscription upon my own tombstone. I can only pray that my poor plays may be as mercifully dealt with as if they were indeed published by my executor, and the hand that wrote them were laid in peaceful rest, where the sun glances through the great <choice><sic>elm-trees</sic><reg resp="#lmw">elm trees</reg></choice> in the beautiful <choice><sic>church-yard</sic><reg resp="#lmw">churchyard</reg></choice> of <placeName ref="#Swallowfield_village">Swallowfield</placeName>.</p>
            
            <p>And here I might well close my preliminary observations, were it not that all dramatists who have printed plays, from <persName ref="#Dryden">John Dryden</persName> to <persName ref="#Hugo_Victor">Victor Hugo</persName>, have delighted to take their ease in the permitted egotism of a rambling preface; and I have no mind to forfeit so pleasant a privilege, although my egotism may probably prove of a different sort. The Prefaces of the <rs type="person" ref="#Dryden">great Laureate</rs>indeed would be difficult to imitate, inasmuch as they contain some of the finest prose in the language. They consist, for the most part, of noble and generous criticism, strangely mingled with theories dear to the <rs type="person" ref="#ChasII">Merry Monarch</rs>, with vindications of the practice of interfusing <pb n="3"/>licentious farce amidst regal tragedy, and preference of the rhymes of <persName ref="#Corneille">Corneille</persName> to the blank verse of <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName>. That <persName ref="#Dryden">Dryden</persName> could have written Tragedy, is proved by the two striking scenes of quarrel and of reconciliation in <title ref="#Don_Sebastian_play"><q>Don Sebastian</q></title> and <title ref="#All_For_Love_play"><q>All for Love</q></title>.<note resp="#lmw">The principle of putting quotation marks around titles of works is applied inconsistently in this work; quotation marks appear in this edition as they did in the 1854 printed edition.</note> The cause of his failure may be found in these theories. But theory, right or wrong, especially as applied to the work in hand, forms the <choice><sic>ground-work</sic><reg>groundwork</reg></choice> of most dramatic Prefaces, largely blended with <choice><sic>skilful</sic><reg resp="#lmw">skillful</reg></choice> specimens of the noble art of self-justification, with vehement attacks upon critics, and perpetual grumblings against managers and actors, and all that was done and all that was not done for the pieces that follow.</p>
            
            <p>Now, although there be some dignity in having been ill-used--a dignity akin to that which made honest <persName ref="#Dogberry_MA">Dogberry</persName> proud of being <quote>"a man who had had losses,"</quote> <note resp="#lmw">A reference to the comic character in <title ref="#Much_Ado_play">Much Ado About Nothing</title> (IV.ii); the phrase had become proverbial.</note> and I am not absolutely prepared to relinquish my claim to such a distinction--I yet hold it to be one which it is a point of discretion and of comfort to forget. The gentlest reader has small sympathy with such grievances; and in that want of sympathy does but follow one of those instincts which it is seldom wise to disobey. No one has a right to gratify a prickly, defiant and sensitive self­love by speaking unkindly of another, especially when the waves of thirty years have rolled between. So instead of reciting long categories of theatrical troubles, I shall endeavour to explain to myself and <pb n="4"/>to others, what has often caused me some astonishment, the causes that drove a shy and retired woman, whose days had passed chiefly in the calm seclusion of a country village into the ambitious and perilous paths of dramatic literature.</p>
            
            <p>Where my passion for plays began, it is difficult to say. Perhaps at the little town of <placeName ref="#Alresford_Hamps">Alresford</placeName>, when I was somewhat short of four years old,<note resp="#lmw">Around <date when="1790">1790</date> or <date when="1791">1791</date>, since <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> was born in <date when="1787">1787</date>.</note> and was taken by <rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">my dear father</rs> to see one of the greatest tragedies of the world set forth in a barn. Even now I have a dim recollection of a glimmering row of candles dividing the end which was called the stage from the part which did duty as pit and boxes, of the black face and the spangled turban,<note resp="#lmw">A reference to the face paint and head dress conventionally worn by nineteenth-century actors playing <persName ref="#Othello_O">Othello</persName>.</note> of my wondering admiration, and the breathless interest of the rustic audience.</p>
            
            <p><rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">My dear father</rs>! how, to the very last, he loved to take his pets to the play! More than fifty years must have passed since that evening in the barn, when, happening to dine at <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>, attended by the beautiful little brown spaniel, who followed him everywhere, he, and of course <persName ref="#Flush_pet">Flush</persName>, accompanied his host to the theatre, to see the charming actress and charming woman, <persName ref="#Orger_MA">Mrs. Orger</persName>. They <choice><sic>sate</sic><reg resp="#lmw">sat</reg></choice> <note resp="#lmw">Alternative spelling for past tense of "sit," characteristically used by <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>.</note> in the place of honour close to the stage. <persName ref="#Flush_pet">Flush</persName>, with his paws on the front of the box, his large earnest eye fixed on the actors, and his long silky ears brought forward on either side of his face, as is the custom of those intelligent dogs on great occasions,<pb n="5"/> looked and listened all through the piece with a sedate fixity of attention, which greatly endangered the gravity of the persons on the stage. <persName ref="#Orger_MA">Mrs. Orger</persName> told me the next day that she had never in her life had so much difficulty in keeping her countenance. It is to be presumed that the little girl of four years old would have pretty much the same appreciation of <title ref="#Othello_play"><q>Othello</q></title> that the beautiful spaniel had of <persName ref="#Maggs_Sally_DP">Sally Maggs</persName>, only with <persName ref="#Flush_pet">Flush</persName> the impression was solitary, and wore away; with me, repeated as often as opportunity offered, it deepened.</p>
           
            <p>Sixty years ago, in the early times of the great war,<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> refers to the 1790s and thus to the French Revolutionary wars in Europe.</note> the drama filled a very different place amongst the amusements of a country town from that which it holds now. Concerts were rare, lectures unknown, and the theatre patronised by the leading families, and conducted in the good town of <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> (to which we had removed) with undeviating propriety, formed the principal recreation of the place. The new comedies of those old times, the comedies of <persName ref="#Holcroft_Thos">Holcroft</persName> and <persName ref="#Morton_Thos">Morton</persName>, of <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">Colman</persName><note resp="#lmw">Reference may be to Colman the Elder, but the Younger seems more likely, as the Elder died in 1794, when Mitford was only seven years old.</note>and <persName ref="#Sheridan_RichardB">Sheridan</persName>, followed by the farces of <persName ref="#Foote_Samuel">Foote</persName> and <persName ref="#OKeefe">O'Keefe</persName>, and the musical entertainments of <persName ref="#Dibdin_TJ">Dibdin</persName>, formed the staple of the house. I wonder whether anybody remembers, <choice><sic>now-a-days</sic><reg resp="#lmw">nowadays</reg></choice>, the pleasant extravagances of <persName ref="#OKeefe">O'Keefe</persName>, who, soar to what comical absurdity he would, was sure to carry his audience with him; or the ease, the neatness, the racy humour of <persName ref="#Foote_Samuel">Foote</persName>'s dialogue, equal, in point and finish, to the finest <pb n="6"/> scenes of <persName ref="#Congreve_Wm">Congreve</persName>! or his translations of <persName ref="#Moliere">Molière</persName>, almost as good as the originals themselves! <persName ref="#Foote_Samuel">Foote</persName> was one of those men whose great gifts as an actor and a mimic have injured his reputation as an author. The world is incredulous of versatility, and does not readily admit that anybody can excel in two ways. Because he acted his own parts with so much talent, the parts have died with him. They are well worth revising and reviving; above all, they are worth studying. Well! I did not look at them, I suppose, quite so critically then; but such were the performances which, varied by an occasional visit from a star, prepared my mind for the glories of the metropolitan boards.</p>
            
            <p>It was during the five years from ten years old to fifteen,<note resp="#lmw">From about 1797 to 1802, since <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford was born in 1787.</persName>.</note> which passed at a <rs type="place" ref="#StQuintin_School"><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> school</rs>, that my passion for the acted drama received its full development. At this <rs type="place" ref="#StQuintin_School">school</rs> (well known afterwards as the residence of poor <persName ref="#Landon_LE">Miss Landon</persName>),<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> likely refers here to "poor" Miss Landon in an oblique reference to Landon's tragic death in 1838 at the age of thirty-six, after only two months of marriage.</note> there chanced to be an old pupil of the establishment who, having lived, as the phrase goes, in several families of distinction, was at that time disengaged, and in search of a situation as governess. <rs type="person" ref="#Rowden_Fr">This lady</rs> was not only herself a poetess (I have <title ref="#Pl_Friendship #St_Botany">two volumes of verse</title> of her writing,) but she had a knack of making poetesses of her pupils. She had already educated <persName ref="#Lamb_Caro">Lady Caroline Ponsonby (the Lady Caroline Lamb, of <title ref="#Glenarvon_fict"><choice><sic>Glenalvon</sic><corr resp="#lmw">Glenarvon</corr></choice></title><note resp="#lmw">A misprint for Lamb's novel <title ref="#Glenarvon_fict">Glenarvon</title>. <persName ref="#Glenalvon">Glenalvon</persName> is a character in the play <title ref="#Douglas_play">Douglas</title>.</note><!--LMW Elisa: I coded these choice/sic/corr because it looks like a genuine error (possibly the printer's and not Mitford's). Thoughts?--> celebrity)</persName>, and was afterwards destined to give her first instruction to poor <persName ref="#Landon_LE">L. E. L.</persName>, and her <pb n="7"/>last to <persName ref="#Kemble_Frances">Mrs. Fanny Kemble</persName>.<note resp="#lmw">After her <date when="1849">1849</date> divorce, the actress used the stage name <q>Mrs.</q> Fanny Kemble.</note> <rs type="person" ref="#Rowden_Fr">She</rs> was, however, a clever woman, and <rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">my father</rs> eagerly engaged her to act by me as a sort of private tutor--a governess out of <choice><sic>school-hours</sic><reg>school hours</reg></choice>.</p>
           
            <p>At the time when I was placed under her care, her whole heart was in the drama, especially as personified by <persName ref="#Kemble_JP">John Kemble</persName>; and I am persuaded that she thought she could in no way so well perform her duty, as in taking me to <placeName ref="#Drury_Lane_Theatre">Drury Lane</placeName> whenever his name was in the bills.</p>
            
            <p>It was a time of great actors. <persName ref="#Bannister_Jack">Jack Bannister</persName> and <persName ref="#Johnstone_Jack">Jack Johnstone</persName> (they would not have known their own names if called John), <persName ref="#Fawcett_John">Fawcett</persName> and <persName ref="#Emery_John">Emery</persName>, <persName ref="#Lewis_William_Thomas">Lewis</persName> and <persName ref="#Munden_Joseph_Shepherd">Munden</persName>, <persName ref="#Davenport_MA">Mrs. Davenport</persName>, <persName ref="#Pope_Jane">Miss Pope</persName>, and <persName ref="#Jordan_Dorothea">Mrs. Jordan</persName>, most exquisite of all, made comedy a bright and living art, an art as full as life itself of laughter and of tears; whilst the glorious <orgName ref="#Kemble_family">family of Kemble</orgName> satisfied alike the eye and the intellect, the fancy and the heart.</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="#Kemble_JP">John Kemble</persName> was, however, certainly <persName ref="#Rowden_Fr">Miss Rowden</persName>'s chief attraction to <placeName ref="#Drury_Lane_Theatre">Drury Lane Theatre</placeName>. She believed him--and of course her pupil shared in her faith--the greatest actor that ever had been, or that ever could be; greater than <persName ref="#Garrick_David">Garrick</persName>, greater than <persName ref="#Kean_Edmund">Kean</persName>.<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Rowden_Fr">Rowden</persName>'s views would not have been shared by her contemporaries; the only role in which he was considered comparably great was <persName ref="#Macbeth_M">Macbeth</persName>. Although he was admired as one of the most polished actors of his generation, his talents were overshadowed by those of his sister <persName ref="#Siddons_Sarah">Sarah Siddons</persName>, as <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> suggests below.</note> I am more catholic now; but I still hold all my admiration, except its exclusiveness.</p>
            
            <p>If <persName ref="#Foote_Samuel">Foote</persName>'s reputation have been injured, as I think it has, by his own double talent as an actor and a mimic, so the fame of <persName ref="#Kemble_JP">John Kemble</persName>--that perishable actor's fame--has suffered not a little by the contact with <rs type="person" ref="#Siddons_Sarah">his great sister</rs>. Besides her uncontested and incontestable power, <persName ref="#Siddons_Sarah">Mrs. Siddons</persName> had one advantage not always allowed for--she was a woman. The actress must always be dearer than the actor; goes closer to the heart, draws tenderer tears. Then she came earlier, and took the first possession; and she lasted longer, charming all <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> by her reading, whilst he lay in a foreign grave.<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Kemble_JP">Kemble</persName> died on <date when="1823-02-26">26 February 1823</date> in Lausanne, Switzerland; <persName ref="#Siddons_Sarah">Sarah Siddons</persName> lived until <date when="1831-06-08">8 June 1831</date>, outliving her brother by more than eight years. <persName ref="#Kemble_JP">Kemble</persName> retired from the stage in <date when="1817">1817</date>, and, although <persName ref="#Siddons_Sarah">Siddons</persName> formally retired in <date when="1812">1812</date>, she continued to give special performances and dramatic readings, as Mitford indicates.</note> Add that the tragedy in which they were best remembered was one in which the heroine must always predominate, for <persName ref="#Macbeth_Lady">Lady Macbeth</persName> is the moving spirit of the play. But take characters of more equality--<persName ref="#Katharine_H8">Katharine</persName> and <persName ref="#Wolsey_H8">Wolsey,</persName> <persName ref="#Hermione_WT">Hermione</persName> and <persName ref="#Leontes_WT">Leontes,</persName> <persName ref="#Coriolanus_C">Coriolanus</persName> and <persName ref="#Volumnia_C">Volumnia,</persName> <persName ref="#Hamlet_H">Hamlet</persName> and <persName ref="#Queen_Hamlet">the Queen</persName>--and surely <persName ref="#Kemble_JP">John Kemble</persName> may hold his own. How often have I seen them in those plays! What would I give to see again those plays so acted!</p>
           
            <p>Another and a very different test of <persName ref="#Kemble_JP">John Kemble</persName>'s histrionic skill was the life and body which he put into the thin shadowy sketches of <persName ref="#Kotzebue">Kotzebue</persName>, then in his height of fashion. <persName ref="#Canning_George">Mr. Canning</persName>, by the capital parodies of the <title ref="#Anti-Jacobin"><q>Anti-Jacobin,</q></title> demolished the sentimental comedy of the German school, a little unmercifully perhaps, for with much that was false and absurd, and the bald gibberish of the translator, for which the author is not answerable, <pb n="8"/>the situations were not only effective, but true. As <persName ref="#Thackeray_WM">Mr. Thackeray</persName> has somewhere observed, the human heart was there, and <persName ref="#Kemble_JP">John Kemble</persName> contrived to show its innermost throbbings. <note resp="#lmw">Quotation unidentified; the claim made here about Kemble was a common nineteenth-century truism about fine playwriting and fine acting. <persName ref="#Thackeray_WM">Thackeray</persName> satirized a provincial performance of <title ref="#Stranger_play">The Stranger</title>, Benjamin Thompson's 1798 adaptation of Kotzebue, in chapter four of <title ref="#Pendennis">Pendennis</title>; no mention is made of Kemble, however. <persName ref="#Canning_George">George Canning</persName> had written a parody of <title ref="#Stranger_play">The Stranger</title> in <title ref="#Anti-Jacobin">The Anti-Jacobin</title>.</note>In <persName ref="#Penruddock_WF">Penruddock</persName> (for <bibl><title ref="#Wheel_Fortune_play"><q>The Wheel of Fortune</q></title></bibl> is of German origin, although written by an Englishman), in <persName ref="#Rolla_P">Rolla</persName>, in <persName ref="#Abbe_de_L_Epee_DD">the Abbe de l'Epée</persName>, three creations essentially various in form and in matter, nobody that has seen him can forget his grace, his pathos, or the manner in which he lent a poetry of feeling to the homeliest prose. In <rs type="person" ref="#Abbe_de_L_Epee_DD">the old French philanthropist</rs> particularly, a part which is nothing, the smallness of the means, the absence of all apparent effort, produced that perfection of art which looks like simple nature. Such were my first impressions of <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> acting.</p>
            
            <p>After my return home, came days of eager and solitary poring over the mighty treasures of the printed drama, that finest form of poetry which never can be lost. At school, I had been made acquainted, like other <choice><sic>school-girls</sic><reg>schoolgirls</reg></choice>, with <persName ref="#Racine">Racine</persName>. Little did <persName ref="#d_Aubigné_Françoise">Madame de Maintenon</persName>, proud queen of the left hand, think, when the gentle poet died of a courtly frown, that she and <placeName ref="#St_Cyr">St. Cyr</placeName> would be best remembered by <bibl><title ref="#Athalie_play">Athalie</title></bibl>! I had won, too, for myself the knowledge of bolder tragedies--of <bibl><title ref="#Cinna_play">Cinna</title></bibl>, of <bibl><title ref="#Horace_play">Horace</title></bibl>, of <bibl><title ref="#Cid_play">the Cid</title></bibl>, of <bibl><title ref="#Merope_play">Merope</title></bibl>, of <bibl><title ref="#Mahomet_play">Mahomet</title></bibl>, of <bibl><title ref="#Zaire_play">Zaïre</title></bibl>, and of the greatest Frenchman of his great age, the peerless <persName ref="#Moliere">Molière</persName>. Of <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> I say nothing. I had grown up--it is the privilege of English people to <pb n="9"/> grow up--in the worship of <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName>, and many of his favourite scenes I literally knew by heart. But whilst still almost a child, whilst thinking no evil, and therefore perhaps finding none, the Elizabethan poets, so nearly his contemporaries, had fallen in my way--poets second only to their great leader in tenderness, in sublimity, in all but purity.</p>

            <p><persName ref="#Lamb_Chas">Charles Lamb</persName> has given specimens of the early English Dramatists, containing as fine poetry as our language can show out of <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName>; and he and <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName> have rendered noble justice to <persName ref="#Webster_John">Webster</persName>, to <persName ref="#Marlowe_Chris">Marlowe</persName>, to <persName ref="#Dekker_Thos">Dekker</persName>, to <persName ref="#Ford_John">Ford</persName>, to all who were previously little known; whilst <persName ref="#Massinger_Phil">Massinger</persName>, so admirable for character and construction, and <persName ref="#Beaumont_Fr">Beaumont</persName> and <persName ref="#Fletcher_John">Fletcher</persName>, so affluent, so eloquent, so royally grand in certain scenes, so touchingly pathetic in others, have, as it seems to me, something less than their due measure of praise.<note resp="#lmw">Refers to <persName ref="#Lamb_Chas">Lamb</persName>'s <title ref="#Specimens_Dramatic_Poets">Specimens of English Dramatic Poets, Who Lived About the Time of Shakespeare. With Notes</title> <date when="1808">(1808)</date> and <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Hazlitt</persName>'s <title ref="#Lectures_Chiefly_Dramatic">Lectures Chiefly on the Dramatic Literature of the Age of Elizabeth, Delivered at the Surry Institution</title> <date when="1820">(1820)</date>.</note> <q>"Every child loves the violet of his own finding best."</q><note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> used this identical quotation in the <date when="1832">1832</date><title ref="#OV">Our Village</title> sketch <title ref="#Christmas_Amusements5_OV">Christmas Amusements, No. V</title>. Both are a loose quotation from <persName ref="#Edgeworth_Maria">Edgeworth</persName>'s <title ref="#Belinda_ME">Belinda</title>: <quote>"Every child thinks the violet of his own finding the sweetest"</quote>.</note> It is true that these great poets had their full meed of applause whilst still alive to enjoy it, and that so late as <persName ref="#Dryden">Dryden</persName>'s day he had said that the English language attained its perfection in their verse; but in my time they had gone completely out of fashion; and I think that I was unconsciously swayed by the axiom which I have quoted, and a little <choice><sic>over-rated</sic><reg>overrated</reg></choice> <rs type="person" ref="#Fletcher_John #Beaumont_Fr">the twin dramatists</rs>, because I fancied them <choice><sic>under-rated</sic><reg>underrated</reg></choice> by these eminent critics. It is certain that I, luxuriated in their abundance, <pb n="10"/>their profusion, the quantity of story and of incident which sometimes overlays their plots, but always keeps alive curiosity and interest; above all, in those whole scenes, sometimes whole acts, never whole plays, which might almost pass for <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName>. <persName ref="#Fletcher_John">Fletcher</persName> was my second favourite amongst the old dramatists; but in plays, as in actors, I was catholic, and had love for them all.</p>

            <p>Every third year, another noble form of tragedy, one with which women are seldom brought in contact, fell in my way. It happened that our family, although no longer living in a country town, kept up a close intimacy with that of the learned and excellent Master of <placeName ref="#Reading_School">Reading School</placeName>, <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Dr. Valpy</persName>; who, having himself no small love for the stage, had wisely substituted the representation of one of the stern Greek Plays for the speeches and recitations formerly delivered before the Heads of certain Colleges of <placeName ref="#Oxford_city">Oxford</placeName> at their Triennial Visitations. Many of the old pupils will remember the effect of these performances, complete in scenery, dresses, and decorations, and remarkable for the effect produced, not only on the actors, but on an audience, of which a considerable portion was new alike to the language and the subject. It is no offence to impute such ignorance to the Mayor and Aldermen of that day, who, in their furred gowns, formed part of the official visitors, or to the mammas and sisters of the <pb n="11"/>performers, who might plead the privilege of sex for their want of learning.</p>

            <p>For myself, as ignorant of Latin or of Greek as the smuggest alderman or slimmest damsel present, I had my own share in the pageant. In spite of all remonstrance and of all dissuasion, the dear <persName type="hist" ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName> would insist on my writing the authorised account of the play--the grand official critique which filled I know not how many columns of the <title ref="#ReadingMer_per"><q>Reading Mercury,</q></title> and was sent east, west, north, and south, wherever mammas and grandmammas were found, and cherished and hoarded by them as certificates of the genius and learning of their offspring. Of course it was necessary to mention everybody, and to commit all the injustice which belongs to an enforced equality by praising some too little and some too much. The too little was more frequent than the too much; for the boys, as a body, did act marvellously, especially those who filled the female parts; making one understand how the ungentle sex might have rendered the <persName ref="#Desdemona_O">Desdemona</persName>s and the <persName ref="#Imogen_C">Imogen</persName>s in <persName ref="#JamesI">James</persName>'s day. So famous, indeed, were the <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName>'s boys for their women, that I never could prevail upon him to get up that masterpiece, <title ref="#Philoctetes_play"><q>Philoctetes,"</q></title> where pity and hatred are moved almost as strongly as in <title ref="#King_Lear_play"><q>Lear,</q></title> not on account of the obvious objection of the physical suffering, but because there was no lady in the play. One circumstance only, a little injured the perfect grouping of the scene. The Visitation<pb n="12"/> occurred in October, not long after the conclusion of the summer holidays; and between cricket and boating, and the impossibility of wearing gloves incident to boys of fifteen, our <persName ref="#Helen_H">Helen</persName>s and <persName type="fict" ref="#Antigone_A">Antigone</persName>s exhibited an assortment of sunburnt fists which might have become a tribe of Red Indians. That did a little spoil the picture. <persName ref="#Sophocles">Sophocles</persName>, however, is <persName ref="#Sophocles">Sophocles</persName> nevertheless; and seldom can his power have been more thoroughly felt than in these performances at <placeName ref="#Reading_School">Reading School</placeName>.</p>

            <p>The good <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Doctor</persName>, full of kindness, and far too learned for pedantry, rewarded my compliance with his wishes in the way I liked best, by helping me to enter into the spirit of the mighty masters who dealt forth these stern Tragedies of Destiny. He put into my hands <persName ref="#Brumoy_Pierre">le Père Brumoy</persName>'s <title><q>Théâtre des Grecs,</q></title>and other translations in homely French prose, where the form and letter were set forth, untroubled by vexatious attempts at English verse--grand outlines for imagination to colour and fill up. There are better things than the unities to be learnt of those old Athenian Poets, as <persName ref="#Alfieri_Vittorio">Alfieri</persName> has shown, and would have shown better if he had imitated less.</p>

            <p>In the meanwhile, frequent visits to <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> had made known to me the successive glories of the <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre #Drury_Lane_Theatre">two great Theatres</placeName>. I had seen the boyish grace of <persName ref="#Master_Betty">Master Betty</persName>, and all the charm of womanly tenderness in <persName ref="#ONeill_Eliz">Miss O'Neill</persName>, and had watched the fiery impulse and <pb n="13"/> gushing pathos that had electrified the town in <persName ref="#Kean_Edmund">Edmund Kean</persName>. <title ref="#Honeymoon_play"><q>The Honeymoon,</q></title> most gracious and most graceful of modern comedies, had been acted as it never has been acted since by <persName ref="#Elliston_Robt">Elliston</persName>, and <persName ref="#Duncan_MR">Miss Duncan</persName>, and <persName ref="#Collins_little">little Collins</persName>; and <persName ref="#Knowles_Sheridan">Mr. Knowles</persName> had produced two vivid and original tragedies in <title ref="#Virginius_play"><q>Virginius</q></title> and <title ref="#WmTell_play"><q>William Tell</q></title>. Everything tended to encourage a poetical aspirant.</p>

            <p>About this time, too, my own prospects, so bright and sunny in early youth, became gradually over­clouded. A Chancery suit, the gaining of which cost eight years and eleven thousand pounds, was the climax of our misfortunes.<note resp="#lmw">The Chancery suit was resolved and the family finances collapsed further in the second half of 1819, although the <orgName ref="#Mitfords">Mitfords</orgName> did not leave <placeName ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</placeName> until <date when="1820-04">April 1820</date>. See <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>'s <date when="1819">1819</date> letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Elford</persName>.</note> We were now so poor, that it became a duty to earn money if I could, and how I could, and so I determined to write a play.</p>

            <p>In my very early girlhood, I had followed my destiny as a pupil of <persName ref="#Rowden_Fr">Miss Rowden</persName>, by committing the sin of rhyming. No less than three octavo volumes<note resp="#lmw">Refers to her <bibl><title ref="#Poems_1st_ed_MRM #Poems_2nd_ed_MRM #Christina #NarrativePoems">1810 Poems, the 1811 second expanded edition of her Poems, her long poem Christina, Maid of the South Seas, and her collection Narrative Poems on the Female Character, all published between 1810 and 1813.</title></bibl></note> had I perpetrated in two years. They had all the faults incident to a young lady's verses, and one of them had been deservedly castigated by the <bibl><title ref="#QuarterlyRev_per">"Quarterly."*</title></bibl> <note resp="#MRM">*This article was fortunate for the writer at a far more important moment. <persName ref="#Gifford_William">Mr. Gifford</persName> himself, as I have been given to understand, feeling that, however well deserved the strictures might be, an attack by his <bibl><title ref="#QuarterlyRev_per">great Review</title></bibl> upon a young girl's first book, was something like breaking a butterfly upon the wheel,<note resp="#lmw">A loose quotation from <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Pope</persName>'s<bibl><title><q>"Epistle to Dr. Arbuthnot,"</q></title></bibl> which had become proverbial in this form. <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> may be recalling this quotation from the <title ref="#QuarterlyRev_per">The Quarterley Review</title>'s use of it in its <date when="1824">1824</date> review of the <title ref="#Our_Village1st_ed">first volume of Our Village</title>. It is unknown whether <persName ref="#Gifford_William">William Gifford</persName> actually wrote the reviews himself, although he was the editor for the <title ref="#QuarterlyRev_per">The Quarterley Review</title> during this time.</note> made amends by a criticism in a very <!-- page break here in note-->different spirit as the <bibl><title ref="#Our_Village1st_ed">first series of <q>"Our Village,"</q></title></bibl> which was of much service to the work. I mention this, because it is honourable to the memory of one whom I never even saw, but who was probably, like many other people, kinder than he seemed.</note> Nevertheless, they had had their <pb n="14"/>praisers--as what young ladies' verses have not!--Large impressions had gone rapidly off; one had run into a <title ref="#Poems_2nd_ed_MRM">second edition</title>; they have been republished in <placeName ref="#USA">America</placeName>--always so kind to me!--two or three of the shorter pieces had been thought good enough to be stolen; and <persName ref="#Coleridge_ST">Mr. Coleridge</persName> had prophesied of the larger ones, that <persName ref="#MRM">the authoress of <title ref="#Blanch"><choice><sic><q>Blanche</q></sic><reg resp="#lmw">Blanch</reg></choice></title></persName> would write a tragedy.<note resp="#lmw">This spelling in original; spelled elsewhere <q>Blanch.</q> This long poem appeared in her 1813 <title ref="#NarrativePoems">Narrative Poems on the Female Character</title>, which had also been printed in a pirated New York edition. <persName ref="#Coleridge_ST">Coleridge</persName> had also read and admired <title ref="#Christina">Christina</title>.</note> So I took heart of grace, and resolved to try a play.</p>

            <p>My first attempt was a blank verse comedy on a pretty story, taken from a French <hi rend="ital"><lang xml:lang="fr">feuilleton</lang></hi>--a story so pretty, that it made <persName>the first manager</persName>, to whom, without any introduction, I ventured to send it, pause to consider; and after his final decision, tempted <persName>an amateur composer</persName> into requesting me to turn it into an opera; by which means I achived a double rejection of the same piece.<note resp="#lmw">These works are as yet unidentified.</note> Then, nothing daunted, I tried Tragedy, and produced five acts on the story of <title ref="#Fiesco_play"><q>Fiesco,</q></title> which would doubtless have been rejected also had they ever fallen into the hands of a manager.</p>

            <p>But just as, conscious of the feebleness of my attempts, of the smallness of my means, and the <pb n="15"/> greatness of my object, I was about to relinquish the pursuit in despair, I met with a critic so candid, a friend so kind, that, aided by his encouragement, all difficulties seemed to vanish. I speak of the author of <title ref="#Ion_TNTplay"><q>Ion,</q></title> <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Justice Talfourd</persName>,<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Thomas Noon Talfourd</persName>, jurist and author, and Mitford mentor. <q>"Justice"</q> here is a title rather than a forename. <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Talfourd</persName> had not yet written a play himself when he first began to advise <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>, although he had been writing theatrical reviews and had many contacts in the worlds of theatre and literary journalism. They began corresponding in <date when="1819">1819</date>; <title ref="#Ion_TNTplay">Ion</title> was produced in <date when="1835">1835</date>.</note> then a very young man, although old in literary reputation, and helping me, as he has helped many a struggler since, by the most judicious advice and the heartiest sympathy. <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay"><q>Foscari</q></title> was the result of this encouragement--a womanish play, which acts better than it reads. Indeed, being at <placeName ref="#Oxford_city">Oxford</placeName>, where an excellent company was performing during the long vacation, I heard that it contained no fewer than four fair <persName ref="#Camilla">Camilla</persName>s, who had acted my heroine in different circuits. <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay"><q>Foscari</q></title> was quickly followed by <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay"><q>Julian"</q></title> originally suggested by the first scene of the <title ref="#Orestes_play"><q>Orestes</q></title> of <persName ref="#Euripides">Euripides</persName>, which happened to be given that year at <placeName ref="#Reading_School">Reading School</placeName>.<note resp="#lmw">In 1821; see <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>'s letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Elford</persName> from <date when="1821-11-23">23 November 1821</date>.</note></p>

            <p>Both these plays were accepted and produced at <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre">Covent Garden</placeName>, although in an inverse order to that in which they were written; and but that I have promised myself and my readers not to enter into the vexed question of theatrical squabbles, a history of their adventures might be concocted quite as long as themselves. Suffice it to say, that poor <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay"><q>Foscari</q></title> had no less than five last scenes--I think I underrate the number, and that there were seven!--and that <rs type="title" ref="#Foscari_MRMplay #Julian_MRMplay">the two plays</rs> fought each other on the point of precedence during the best part of the season--<pb n="16"/>which was pretty much like a duel between one's right hand and one's left.<note resp="#lmw">Although both plays were accepted in <date when="1823">1823</date>, <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian</title> saw production first, starting in <date when="1823-03">March 1823</date>. <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay"> Foscari</title> was not produced until <date when="1826">1826</date>.</note></p>

            <p>Great, at the moment, were those anxieties and tribulations, the rather that money arrangements most important to those dearer to me than myself were staked on the issue. But it is good to observe in one's own mind, and good to tell to others who may be exposed to such trials, how inevitably, as according to some happy law of nature the keenest physical pain is known to be soon forgotten, whilst pleasure's light traces are indelible; so in mental vicissitudes, Time carries away the bitter and leaves the sweet. The vexations and the injuries fade into dim distance, and the kindness and the benefit shine vividly out. The warm grasp of <persName ref="#Kemble_MrsC">Mrs. Charles Kemble</persName>'s hand, for instance, when I saw her all life and heartiness at her house in <placeName ref="#Soho_Sq">Soho Square</placeName>, my first dramatic experience:--the excellent acting of <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay"><q>Foscari;</q></title> <persName ref="#Young_CM">Mr. Young</persName>, and <persName ref="#Kemble_C">Mr. Charles Kemble</persName>, so quiet and so touching in the concluding scenes; <persName ref="#Warde_Mr">Mr. Warde</persName> playing a secondary part so finely, that he led every body into thinking that he ought to play the first; <persName ref="#Serle_TJ">Mr. Serle</persName> lending to <persName ref="#Cosmo">Cosmo</persName> his own fine taste; and <persName ref="#Sloman_Mrs">Mrs. Sloman</persName>, who would have achieved the highest reputation but for the want of the indescribable thing called charm:--then <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay"><q>Julian,</q></title> on the other hand; how <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> stood alone under the weight of that tragedy, with how much talent, how much warmth, what untiring and <pb n="17"/>indefatigable zeal! These are the things one thinks of, when sitting calm and old by the light of a country fire; and if other recollections mingle with them, they are rather of the comic and the grotesque kind than of the bitter or the resentful.</p>

            <p>To one accustomed to the imposing aspect of a great theatre at night, blazing with light and beauty, no contrast can be greater than to enter the same theatre at noontide, leaving daylight behind you, and stumbling as best you may through dark passages, and amidst the inextricable labyrinth of scenery and lumber of every description; too happy if you be not projected into the orchestra, or swallowed up by a trap-door.</p>

            <p><persName ref="#Forbes_Capt">Captain Forbes</persName>, one of the proprietors, and a naval man, used to compare the stage with its three tiers of <choice><sic>under-ground</sic><reg>underground</reg></choice> <choice><sic>store-rooms</sic><reg>storerooms</reg></choice> and magazines, and its prodigious height and complexity of top hamper aloft to a first-rate man-of-war. That comparison is rather too flattering. To me--no offence to the <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre">Theatre Royal Covent Garden</placeName>--it always recalled the place where I first made acquaintance with the enchantment of the scene, by reminding me of some prodigious barn. A barn it certainly resembles, vast dusty, dusky and cavernous, with huge beams toppling overhead, holes yawning beneath, rough partitions sticking out on either side, and everywhere a certain vague sense of obscurity and confusion.</p>

            <p>When the eye becomes accustomed to the dark<pb n="18"/>ness, <reg resp="#lmw">darkness</reg> the contrasts are sufficiently amusing. Solemn tragedians--that is to say, tragedians who seem solemn enough in their stage gear at night--hatted and great-coated, skipping about, chatting and joking, and telling good stories like common mortals; indeed, the only very grave person whom I remarked was <persName ref="#Liston_John">Mr. Liston</persName>; tragic heroines sauntering languidly through their parts in the closest of bonnets and thickest of shawls; untidy <choice><sic>ballet-girls</sic><reg>ballet girls</reg></choice> (there was a dance in <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay"><q>Foscari</q></title>) walking through their quadrille to the sound of a solitary fiddle, striking up as if of its own accord from amidst the tall stools and <choice><sic>music-desks</sic><reg>music desks</reg></choice> of the orchestra, and piercing one hardly knew how through the din that was going on incessantly.</p>

            <p>Oh, that din! Voices from every part, above below, around, and in every key, bawling, shouting, screaming; heavy weights rolling here and falling there, bells ringing one could not tell why, and the ubiquitous <choice><sic>call-boy</sic><reg>call boy</reg></choice> everywhere! If one element prevailed amongst these conflicting noises, it was certainly the never-pausing strokes of the carpenter's hammer, which in our case did double duty, the new scenery of the morrow being added to the old scenery of the night. Double, too, were the cares not merely of the official before-mentioned, the <choice><sic>call-boy</sic><reg>call boy</reg></choice>, but of his superiors, the stage-manager and the prompter; for whilst we, the new tragedy, held after our strange scrambling fashion possession of the stage, the <pb n="19"/> comedy or opera of the evening was crowded into the <choice><sic>green-room</sic><reg>green room</reg></choice>, to the great increase of our confusion and their own; some of their people belonging to us, and some of ours to them, and neither party being ever in the proper place, so that there were perpetual sendings after their walking gentlemen and our walking ladies, the common property.</p>
            
            <p>The scenery too, that part which was fished up from the subterraneous galleries, was fertile in blunders. I have known a fine view of <placeName ref="#Rialto">the Rialto</placeName> with a bit of <placeName ref="#Charing_Cross">Charing Cross</placeName> for one wing, and a sliver of the <placeName ref="#Forest_of_Ardennes">Forest of Ardennes</placeName> for the other. Even the new scenes had their perils. Painter and manager would disagree as to the size of the moon, and a good half-hour was wasted one morning in experiments as to the best manner of folding the [muslin]<note resp="#lmw">Bracket insertion in original.</note> clouds over the face of that bright luminary.</p>
            
            <p>Then the turmoil about costume! A good deal of that squabbling was transacted in some remote part of the upper regions, where tailors and <choice><sic>dress-makers</sic><reg>dressmakers</reg></choice> held their court; but some of the difficulties descended upon the stage. There was a cloak in <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay"><q>Julian,</q></title> which having to act as a pall to the fair <persName ref="#Annabel_J">Annabel,</persName> never could be made wide enough; and all the predecents of all the Duke's <choice><sic>head-dresses</sic><reg>headdresses</reg></choice> in all the theatres of the world, from that in the <title ref="#Merchant_of_Venice_play"><q>Merchant of Venice</q></title> to that in <title ref="#Venice_Preserved_play"><q>Venice Preserved,</q></title> never could persuade me that the tall inverted drum assumed by <persName ref="#Young_CM">Mr. Young</persName> was the proper bonnet of the <persName ref="#Doge_F">Doge</persName>. This, <pb n="20"/>however, was my own private grief. Through all their courtesy, I had early made the discovery, that the less an author meddled in such matters the better. One dispute was open and general: it had reference to the proper time of assuming mourning. <persName ref="#Donato">Donato</persName> (we are still talking of <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay"><q>Foscari</q></title>) died in the third act: the question was, whether his <rs type="person" ref="#Cosmo">son</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="#Camilla">daughter</rs> should put on black in the fourth--that is, the next morning. Parties were divided: the anti-blacks holding that it is not customary to go into mourning before the funeral. The debate ended, as debates in higher places are apt to end in our good kingdom of <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>, in a compromise. The <persName ref="#Camilla">lady</persName> appeared in the deepest sables that the dressmaker could furnish; <rs type="person" ref="#Cosmo">her brother</rs> retained the radiant suit of satin and embroidery which he had worn from the commencement of the play; a manner of settling the dispute which, like the aforesaid compromises in higher places, had the effect of making both parties seem wrong.</p>
            
            <p>No end to the absurdities and discrepancies of a rehearsal! I contributed my full share to the amount, and began pretty early, so soon indeed as the very first words that I ever uttered behind the scenes. There is a gun in <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay"><q>Julian;</q></title> and I, frightened by one when a child, <quote>"hate a gun like a hurt wild-duck;"</quote><note resp="#lmw">A quotation from <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName>'s novel <title ref="#Antiquary">The Antiquary</title>: <quote>I hate a gun like a hurt wild duck--I detest a drum like a quaker--and they thunder and rattle out yonder upon the town's common, that every volley and roll goes to my very heart</quote> <bibl>(volume one, chapter six)</bibl>.</note> and the only time that I ever went to a review coaxed <rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">my father</rs> to drive me home before it began. I was only twelve years old then; but I had not much improved by <pb n="21"/> becoming a tragic authoress, for my first address to <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> was an earnest entreaty that he would not suffer them to fire that gun at rehearsal. They did fire nevertheless; as indeed if the gun had not gone off in the morning, it might have been forgotten at night; but the smiling bow of <rs type="person" ref="#Macready_Wm">the great tragedian</rs> had spared me the worst part of that sort of fright, the expectation.</p> 
            
            <p>Troubled and anxious though they were, those were pleasant days, guns and all; days of hope dashed with so much fear, of fear illumined with its fitful rays of hope. And those rehearsals, where for noise of every sort nobody can hear himself speak, where nobody is ever to be found where he is wanted, and nobody ever seems to know a syllable of his part; those rehearsals must have some good in them notwithstanding. In the midst of the crowd, the din, the jokes, and the confusion, the business must somehow have gone on; for at night the right scenes fall into the right places, the proper actors come at the proper times, speeches are spoken in due order, and, to the no small astonishment of the novice, who had given herself up for lost, the play succeeds.</p>
            
            <p>Not that I had nerve enough to attend the first representation of my tragedies. I <choice><sic>sate</sic><reg>sat</reg></choice> <note resp="#lmw">Alternative spelling for past tense of "sit," characteristically used by <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>.</note> still and trembling in some quiet apartment near, twice I think in a small room belonging to that good-natured person <persName ref="#Robins_Geo">Mr. George Robins</persName>; and thither some friend<pb n="22"/> flew to set my heart at ease. Generally the messenger of good tidings was poor <persName ref="#Haydon">Haydon</persName>, whose quick and ardent spirit lent him wings on such an occasion, and who had full sympathy with my love for a large canvas, however indifferently filled.<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> likely refers here to <quote>"poor"</quote> <persName ref="#Haydon">Haydon</persName> as alluding to his suicide in <date when="1846">1846</date>; she also slyly alludes to <persName ref="#Haydon">Haydon</persName>'s penchant for producing large, ambitious, (and difficult to sell) historical and religious paintings.</note></p>
            
            <p>Before leaving <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay"><q>Foscari,</q></title> it is well to say that two innovations began with my tragedies. The Epilogue by some accident arrived so late, that <persName>the lady</persName> by whom it was to be spoken complained that she had not time to study it.<note resp="#lmw">As yet unidentified.</note> She probably made the most of the delay. No fair comedian can be supposed to find much pleasure in being dragged to the theatre for so ungrateful a purpose every tragedy night; so <persName ref="#Fawcett_John">Mr. Fawcett,</persName> the stage-manager, a man, as his acting always evinced, of excellent judgment, proposed its omission. It was, he said, simply an added danger, could do no good in failure, and stopped the applause in success. So we discarded the Epilogue altogether; and afterwards, when bringing out <bibl><title ref="#Rienzi">"Rienzi,"</title></bibl> we also dropped the Prologue; in both cases, I believe, for the first time.<!--LMW: Is there a copy of the epilogue in ms. anywhere? Also, are these claims true? More research needed.--></p>
            
            <p>It was during the run of <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay"><q>Julian,</q></title> that seeing much of my dear friend <persName ref="#Franklin_Eleanor">Miss Porden</persName> (afterwards married to <persName ref="#Franklin_John">Sir John Franklin</persName>), and talking with her of subjects for a fresh effort, one or the other, I hardly know which hit upon <title ref="#Rienzi"><q>Rienzi;</q></title> a <rs type="person" ref="#Rienzi_Cola">personage</rs> at that time so little familiar to the public, that a great Law Dignity asked gravely, after seeing the <pb n="23"/>play, whether such a man had ever existed? and another eminent person, gathering from my Preface that the story might be found in <persName ref="#Gibbon_Edward">Gibbon</persName>, produced the <hi rend="ital">first</hi> volume of <title ref="#Decline_Fall"><q>The Decline and Fall,"</q></title> actually the <emph rend="caps">FIRST</emph>, which he told me he was about to take into the country, in order to compare my delineation with the actual man.<note resp="#lmw">Volume one of <title ref="#Decline_Fall">The Decline and Fall of The Roman Empire</title> covers Roman history from the second to the fourth century; <persName ref="#Rienzi_Cola">Cola di Rienzi</persName>, who lived during the fourteenth century, appears in volume six.</note></p>
            
            <p><persName ref="#Franklin_Eleanor">Miss Porden</persName> had herself written an heroic poem, called <title ref="#Coeur_de_Lion_poem"><q>Coeur de Lion,</q></title> which, if anybody <choice><sic>now-a-days</sic><reg>nowadays</reg></choice> could read an epic two volumes long, would be found remarkable as a promise; so she was far from being startled at my boldness, and took a vivid interest in my attempt. A year or two after, when in <placeName ref="#London_city">London,</placeName> negotiating about this very play, I saw her again as <persName type="hist" ref="#Franklin_Eleanor">Mrs. Franklin</persName>. <rs type="person" ref="#Franklin_John">Her husband</rs> was in <placeName ref="#Lincolnshire">Lincolnshire</placeName>, taking leave of his relations before setting forth on one of his adventurous voyages; and, in the midst of her warm and undiminished sympathy with my anxieties, she talked of that husband whose projects of polar discovery had filled her imagination, showed me his bust and their little girl, and a flag which she was working for him as her own <persName ref="#Berengaria">Berengaria</persName> had done for <persName ref="#RichardI">Richard</persName>. It was poetry in action--epic poetry--and I too sympathised with the devoted wife. But I saw, what at that time her own sister had not suspected, that she was dying. This warm-hearted and large-minded woman was of a frame and temperament the most <pb n="24"/>delicate and fragile. The agitation of parting was too much for her; and before <persName ref="#Franklin_John">Captain Franklin</persName>'s expedition was out of <placeName ref="#Eng_Channel">the Channel,</placeName> she was dead.</p>
            
            <p>When <title ref="#Rienzi"><q>Rienzi,</q></title> after a more than common portion of adventures and misadventures, did come out with a success rare in a woman's life, I missed the eager congratulations which I should have received from her who had taken so large a part in its previous history--missed her, the rather, perhaps, because no part of my success was more delightful than the pleasure which it excited amongst the most eminent of my female contemporaries. <persName ref="#Edgeworth_Maria">Maria Edgeworth,</persName> <persName ref="#Baillie_Joanna">Joanna Baillie,</persName> <persName ref="#Hemans_Felicia">Felicia Hemans</persName> (and to two of them I was at that time unknown), vied in the cordiality of their praises. In <persName ref="#Hemans_Felicia">Mrs. Hemans,</persName> this warmth was peculiarly generous, for <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay"><q>Julian</q></title> and <title ref="#Vespers_of_Palermo"><q>The Vespers of Palermo</q></title> had been placed, by circumstances, in such a position as might have made us rivals if we had not determined to be friends<note resp="#lmw">Both plays had Sicilian settings and were performed at <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre">Covent Garden Theatre</placeName> in <date when="1823">1823</date>; <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian</title> in <date when="1823-03">March</date>, <title ref="#Vespers_of_Palermo">Vespers of Palermo</title> in <date when='1823-12'>December</date>.</note> Kindness met me on every hand, from eminent men, from eminent women, still I missed her whose cheering prognostics had so often spurred me on, and whose latest interest in literature had been excited by this very play.</p>
            
            <p>And dramatic success, after all, is not so delicious, so glorious, so complete a gratification as, in our secret longings, we all expect to find. It is not satisfactory. It does not fill the heart. It is an intoxication, followed like other intoxications, by <pb n="25"/>a dismal reaction. The enchanting hope is gone, and is ill-replaced by a temporary triumph--very temporary! Within four-and-twenty hours, I doubted if triumph there were, and more than doubted if it were deserved. It is ill success that leads to self-assertion. Never in my life was I so conscious of my dramatic <choice><sic>short-comings</sic><reg>shortcomings</reg></choice> as on that day of imputed exultation and vainglory.</p>
            
            <p>Then came <title ref="#CharlesI_MRMplay"><q>Charles the First</q></title> and his calamities, of a very different sort from any of the former, since managers and actors were equally eager to bring out the play. The hindrance lay in <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">Mr. George Colman</persName>, the licenser, who saw a danger to the State in permitting the trial of an English Monarch to be represented on the stage, especially <rs type="person" ref="#ChasI">a Monarch</rs> whose martyrdom was still observed in our churches. It was in vain that I urged that my play was ultra loyal; that having taken the very best moment of <persName ref="#ChasI">Charles</persName>'s life and the very worst of <persName ref="#Cromwell">Cromwell</persName>'s; and having, moreover, succumbed to the temptation of producing, as far as in me lay, a strong dramatic contrast between the characters, I had, in point of fact, done considerable injustice to the greatest man of his age. <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">Mr. Colman</persName> was inexorable; and the tragedy, forbidden at <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre #Drury_Lane_Theatre">the two great houses</placeName>, was afterwards produced at <rs type="place" ref="#Vict_Theatre">a minor theatre</rs> with no ill effect to the reigning dynasty. I have retained the original Preface, as giving a curious view of a state of things now happily passed away. Let me add <pb n="26"/> that as consolations are to be found for most evils, if we will but look for them, so pleasanter associations present themselves even here in the kindness of <persName ref="#Duke_of_Devonshire">the Duke of Devonshire,</persName> of <persName ref="#Serle_TJ">Mr. Serle</persName>, and very recently of <persName ref="#Jerrold_Doug">Mr. Jerrold</persName>.</p>
            
            <p><title ref="#CharlesI_MRMplay"><q>Charles the First</q></title> had his calamities and <title ref="#Inez_deCastro_MRMplay"><q>Inez de Castro</q></title> <choice><sic>her's</sic><reg resp="#lmw">hers</reg></choice>, having been twice in rehearsal in different seasons, and twice, for different causes, withdrawn.</p>
            
            <p><title ref="#Sadak_Kalasrade"><q>Sadak and Kalasrade</q></title> was written to gratify <rs type="person" ref="#Packer_Chas">a young musician,</rs> and <title ref="#Gaston_deBlondeville"><q>Gaston de Blondeville</q></title> because I thought, and still think, that the story, taken from <persName ref="#Radcliffe_Ann">Mrs. Ratcliffe</persName>'s <bibl><title ref="#Gaston_novel">posthumous romance,</title></bibl> would be very effective as a mere spectacle--a play to look at--upon the stage.</p>
            
            <p>I should not wish to say exactly the same of <title ref="#Otto"><q>Otto of Wittelsbach,</q></title> of which the name and a few of the events may be found in an old German play.<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> likely refers to <bibl><title ref="#Otto_Babo">Otto von Wittlesbach</title>, a <date when="1782">1782</date> German tragedy by <persName ref="#Babo">Joseph Marius Babo</persName></bibl>, based on the historical figure <persName ref="#OttoII">Otto II of Wittelsbach, Duke of Bavaria</persName>.</note> It is just possible that hereafter some actor, powerful in mind and body, may think my drama worth trying. If so, I have to request that <persName ref="#Ulric_O">Ulric</persName>, (in whom there is, I fear, too strong a recollection of <persName ref="#Fletcher_John">Fletcher</persName>'s <persName ref="#Hengo_B">Hengo</persName>) may be played by a boy. The young actors of <placeName ref="#Reading_School">Reading School</placeName> proved that Greek women may be fitly represented by English lads; but I have never yet seen any actress who satisfied me in boys' parts. They always exhibit a painful consciousness, never more unpleasantly visible than when disguised under the mask of levity, not to say <pb n="27"/> effrontery. Even <persName ref="#Kemble_MrsC">Mrs. Charles Kemble</persName>, whose pantomime in <title ref="#Aladdin_panto"><q>Aladdin</q></title> and in <title ref="#Deaf_Dumb_play"><q>Deaf and Dumb,</q></title> was so perfect, seemed always (I speak it in her honour) a woman in boy's clothes.</p>
            
            <p>So much for the Tragedies. There would have been many more such, but that the pressing necessity of earning money, and the uncertainties and delays of the drama at moments when delay or disappointment weighed upon me like a sin, made it a duty to turn away from the lofty steep of Tragic Poetry to the <choice><sic>every-day</sic><reg>everyday</reg></choice> path of Village Stories.</p>
            
            <p>The <bibl><title ref="#DramaticScenes">Dramatic Scenes</title></bibl> may almost be said to hold the middle road between these tracks so widely different. On their first appearance, they kept good company. Two or three of the earliest were inserted in <title ref="#LondonMag"><q>The London Magazine</q></title> at the same time with the <title ref="#Essays_of_Elia_nonfict"><q>Essays of Elia,</q></title> and the <title ref="#Confessions_OpiumEater_nonfict"><q>Confessions of an Opium-eater;</q></title><note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#Lamb_Chas">Charles Lamb began contributing to the magazine from its inception in <date when="1820">; <persName ref="#DeQuincey_Thos">De Quincey</persName></date>'s</persName>, in <date when="1821">.</date></note> the rest were written for various annuals in the palmy days of those pretty books;--by which I mean the days of <persName ref="#Hood_Thos">Thomas Hood</persName> and of <persName ref="#Praed_Winthrop">Winthrop Praed</persName>, of <persName ref="#Hemans_Felicia">Mrs. Hemans</persName> and of <persName ref="#Landon_LE">L.E.L.</persName>, when engravings were mingled with prose and verse, and neither verse nor prose was written to illustrate the pictures.</p>
            
            <p>In some of these scenes, the descriptions introduced are taken from real places, and are as like to those places as my poor gift of word-painting could make them; and in all, I may say, or nearly all, I have, I cannot tell why, put more of my own pecu<pb n="28"/>liar <reg resp="#lmw">peculiar</reg>thoughts and fancies than in any other of my writings, which may be, perhaps, the reason why those who have happened to like them have liked them better than they deserve.</p>
            
            <p>Before closing this Preface, I wish to caution the reader against attributing to me, personally, any participation in the sentiments respecting the Jews, expressed by the characters in <title ref="#Gaston_deBlondeville"><q>Gaston de Blondeville;</q></title> they are as purely dramatic as the belief in witchcraft, and intended, like that, to display the barbarism of a most barbarous age. <persName ref="#Pierce_G">Pierce</persName>, the jester, one of the few rational personages of the drama, says of them:--<quote>For these poor Jews they are but as fear and misery have made them.</quote><note resp="#lmw">A loose quotation. In the play, <persName ref="#Pierce_G">Pierce</persName> says, <quote>"They are as Fear and Misery have made them"</quote> (act one, scene one).</note> And there I might, perhaps, safely have left the question; but that, besides my general hatred of persecution and intolerance, and all prejudices against caste and creed; I happen to have myself the happiness of knowing some individuals of that gifted Hebrew people, and if I were to write according to my knowledge, might very probably be accused of cherishing prejudices the contrary way; since I have rarely met any persons so eminent for high qualities, moral and intellectual, especially for the rare quality called charity.</p>
            
            <p><note resp="#lmw">In printed text, a printer's ornament appears here between the main text and the later addition, which functions as a post-script.</note></p>
            
            <p>This Introduction was written <date when="1853">nearly a twelvemonth ago,</date> when although suffering from great infirmity, I <pb n="29"/> was still lifted down stairs, and sometimes drawn through our green lanes. Brief and imperfect as these few pages are, I could not now even have attempted the task, for which I once again request the indulgence I have so often experienced.<note resp="#lmw"><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> was suffering from the after-effects of a serious fall that injured her spine, as well as from rheumatism.</note></p>
            
            <p><emph rend="small caps"><placeName ref="#Swallowfield_village">SWALLOWFIELD</placeName>,</emph></p>
            
            <p><emph rend="small caps"><date when="1854-07">JULY, 1854</date></emph></p>
            <pb n="30"/>

         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div>
       <!--LMW: additional new prosopography added to si-Add-DRAMA-LMW file. 2016-09-11 -->
            
         <!--ebb: 6 July 2014: Prosopography  entered to site index.-->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
