<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <!--2017-01-10 ebb: Here is the source of our base text in Hathi Trust:
https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/ssd?id=mdp.39015008020441;seq=189;num=177
The nine missing sketches are Sections 16 to 23, the last nine sketches in OV.

Make a new file for each sketch. 
Follow the filenameing conventions that you see in Box. Each OV sketch begins with the letters OV, then the main title, and if a subtitle it goes in block caps at the end of the filename.xml
Please use the 1824 NCCO PDF (saved in OV folder in Box) to check and correct the text.

  -->

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
            <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>


            <editor>Samantha Webb</editor>
            <editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName>Jonathan M. Horanic</persName>
               <persName>Samantha Webb</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--2017-01-10 ebb: We need to change this sourceDesc to indicate we’re checking each text and altering it to represent the 1824 edition as published in NCCO. -->
            <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
            <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                  <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third
                     Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B.
                     Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
               </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first
               edition published in 1824. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="sketch">
            <pb n="213"/>
            <head>THE TALKING GENTLEMAN.
               <!--ebb: If there’s a subtitle use an <lb/> element to separate -->
            </head>
            <p>The lords of the creation, who are generally (to do them justice) tenacious enough of
               their distinctive and peculiar faculties and powers, have yet by common consent made
               over to the females the single gift of loquacity. Every man thinks and says that
               every woman talks more than he: it is the creed of the whole sex,—the debates and law
               reports notwithstanding. And every masculine eye that has scanned my title has
               already, I doubt not, looked to the errata, suspecting a mistake in the gender; but
               it is their misconception, not my mistake. I do not (Heaven forbid!) intend to impugn
               or abrogate our female privilege; I do not dispute that we do excel, generally
               speaking, in the use of the tongue; I only mean to assert that one gentleman does
               exist, (whom I have the pleasure of knowing intimately,) who stands pre-eminent and
               unrivalled in the art of talking,—unmatched and unapproached by man, woman, or child.
               Since the decease of my poor friend “the Talking Lady,” who dropped down speech<pb
                  n="214"/>less in the midst of a long story about nine weeks ago, and was
               immediately known to be dead by her silence, I should be at a loss where to seek a
               competitor to contend with him in a race of words, and I should be still more puzzled
               to find one that can match him in wit, pleasantry, or good-humour.</p>
            <p>My friend is usually called Harry L., for, though a man of substance, a lord of land,
               a magistrate, a field officer of militia, nobody ever dreamed of calling him Mister
               or major, or by any such derogatory title—he is and will be all his life plain Harry,
               the name of universal good-will. He is indeed the pleasantest fellow that lives. His
               talk (one can hardly call it conversation, as that would seem to imply another
               interlocutor, something like reciprocity) is an incessant flow of good things, like
               Congreve’s comedies without a replying speaker, or Joe Miller laid into one; and its
               perpetual stream is not lost and dispersed by diffusion, but runs in one constant
               channel, playing and sparkling like a fountain, the delight and ornament of our good
               town of B.</p>
            <p>Harry L. is a perfect example of provincial reputation, of local fame. There is not
               an urchin in the town that has not heard of him, nor an old woman that does not
               chuckle by anticipation at his approach. The citizens of B. are as proud of him as
               the citizens of Antwerp were of the Chapeau de Paille, and they have<pb n="215"/> the
               advantage of the luckless Flemings in the certainty that their boast is not to be
               purchased. Harry, like the Flemish Beauty, is native to the spot; for he was born at
               B., educated at B., married at B.—though, as his beautiful wife brought him a good
               estate in a distant part of the country, there seemed at that epoch of his history
               some danger of his being lost to our ancient borough; but he is a social and
               gregarious animal; so he leaves his pretty place in Devonshire to take care of
               itself, and lives here in the midst of a hive. His tastes are not at all rural. He is
               no sportsman, no farmer, no lover of strong exercise. When at B., his walks are quite
               regular; from his own house, on one side of the town, to a gossip-shop called
               “literary” on the other, where he talks and reads newspapers, and others read
               newspapers and listen: thence he proceeds to another house of news, similar in kind,
               though differing in name, in an opposite quarter, where he and his hearers undergo
               the same process, and then he returns home, forming a pretty exact triangle of about
               half a mile. This is his daily exercise, or rather his daily walk; of exercise he
               takes abundance, not only in talking, (though that is nearly as good to open the
               chest as the dumb-bells,) but in a general restlessness and fidgetiness of person,
               the result of his ardent and nervous temperament, which can hardly endure repose of
               mind or body. He neither gives rest nor takes it. His<pb n="216"/> company is,
               indeed, in one sense (only one) fatiguing. Listening to him tires you like a journey.
               You laugh till you are forced to lie down. The medical gentlemen of the place are
               aware of this, and are accustomed to exhort delicate patients to abstain from Harry’s
               society, just as they caution them against temptations in point of amusement or of
               diet—pleasant but dangerous. Choleric gentlemen should also avoid him, and such as
               love to have the last word; for, though never provoked himself, I cannot deny that he
               is occasionally tolerably provoking,—in politics especially—(and he is an
               ultra-liberal, quotes Cobbett, and goes rather too far)—in politics he loves to put
               his antagonist in a fume, and generally succeeds, though it is nearly the only
               subject on which he ever listens to an answer—chiefly I believe for the sake of a
               reply, which is commonly some trenchant repartee, that cuts off the poor answer’s
               head like a razor. Very determined speakers would also do well to eschew his
               company—though in general I never met with any talker to whom other talkers were so
               ready to give way; perhaps because he keeps them in such incessant laughter, that
               they are not conscious of their silence. To himself the number of his listeners is
               altogether unimportant. His speech flows not from vanity or lust of praise, but from
               sheer necessity ;—the reservoir is full, and runs over. When he has no one else to
               talk to, he can be content with his own company,<pb n="217"/> and talks to himself,
               being beyond a doubt greater in a soliloquy than any man off the stage. Where he is
               not known, this habit sometimes occasions considerable consternation, and very
               ridiculous mistakes. He has been taken alternately for an actor, a poet, a man in
               love, and a man beside himself. Once in particular, at Windsor, he greatly alarmed a
               philanthropic sentinel, by holding forth at his usual rate whilst pacing the terrace
               alone; and but for the opportune arrival of his party, and their assurances that it
               was only “the gentleman’s way,” there was some danger that the benevolent soldier
               might have been tempted to desert his post to take care of him. Even after this
               explanation, he looked with a doubtful eye at our friend, who was haranguing himself
               in great style, sighed and shook his head, and finally implored us to look well after
               him till he should be safe off the terrace.—“You see, Ma’am,” observed the
               philanthropist in scarlet, “it is an awkward place for any body troubled with
               vagaries. Suppose the poor soul should take a fancy to jump over the wall!”</p>
            <p>In his externals he is a well-looking gentleman of forty, or thereabout; rather thin
               and rather pale, but with no appearance of ill health, nor any other peculiarity,
               except the remarkable circumstance of the lashes of one eye being white, which gives
               a singular non-resemblance to his organs of vision. Every one perceives<pb n="218"/>
               the want of uniformity, and few detect the cause. Some suspect him of what farriers
               call a wall-eye; some think he squints. He himself talks familiarly of his two eyes,
               the black and the white, and used to liken them to those of our fine Persian cat,
               (now, alas! no more,) who had, in common with his feline countrymen, one eye blue as
               a sapphire, the other yellow as a topaz. The dissimilarity certainly rather spoils
               his beauty, but greatly improves his wit,—I mean the sense of his wit in others. It
               arrests attention, and predisposes to laughter; is an outward and visible sign of the
               comical. No common man has two such eyes. They are made for fun.</p>
            <p>In his occupations and pleasures Harry is pretty much like other provincial
               gentlemen: loves a rubber, and jests all through at aces, kings, queens, and knaves,
               bad cards and good, at winning and losing, scolding and praise;—loves a play, at
               which he out-talks the actors whilst on the stage,—to say nothing of the advantage he
               has over them in the intervals between the acts;—loves music, as a good accompaniment
               to his grand solo;—loves a contested election above all. That is his real
               element,—that din and uproar and riot and confusion! To ride that whirlwind and
               direct that storm is his triumph of triumphs! He would make a great sensation in
               parliament himself, and a pleasant one. (By the way, he was once in danger of
                  being<pb n="219"/> turned out of the gallery for setting all around him in a
               roar.) Think what a fine thing it would be for the members to have mirth introduced
               into the body of the house! to be sure of an honest, hearty, good-humoured laugh
               every night during the session! Besides, Harry is an admirable speaker, in every
               sense of the word. Jesting is indeed his forte, because he wills it so to be; and
               therefore, because he chooses to play jigs and country dances on a noble organ, even
               some of his stanchest admirers think he can play nothing else. There is no quality of
               which men so much grudge the reputation as versatility of talent. Because he is so
               humourous, they will hardly allow him to be eloquent; and, because he is so very
               witty, find it difficult to account him wise. But let him go where he has not that
               mischievous fame, or let him bridle his jests and rein in his humour only for one
               short hour, and he will pass for a most reverend orator,—logical, pathetic, and
               vigorous above all.—But how can I wish him to cease jesting even for an hour? Who
               would exchange the genial fame of good-humoured wit for the stern reputation of
               wisdom? Who would choose to be Socrates, if with a wish he could be Harry L.?</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
