<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <!--2017-01-10 ebb: Here is the source of our base text in Hathi Trust:
https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/ssd?id=mdp.39015008020441;seq=189;num=177
The nine missing sketches are Sections 16 to 23, the last nine sketches in OV.

Make a new file for each sketch. 
Follow the filenameing conventions that you see in Box. Each OV sketch begins with the letters OV, then the main title, and if a subtitle it goes in block caps at the end of the filename.xml
Please use the 1824 NCCO PDF (saved in OV folder in Box) to check and correct the text.

  -->

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
            <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>


            <editor>Samantha Webb</editor>
            <editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName>Jonathan M. Horanic</persName>
               <persName>Samantha Webb</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--2017-01-10 ebb: We need to change this sourceDesc to indicate we’re checking each text and altering it to represent the 1824 edition as published in NCCO. -->
            <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
            <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                  <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third
                     Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B.
                     Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
               </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first
               edition published in 1824. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="sketch">
            <pb n="255"/>
            <head>WALKS IN THE COUNTRY.<lb/>THE VISIT.
               <!--ebb: If there’s a subtitle use an <lb/> element to separate -->
            </head>
            <p>October 27th.—A lovely autumnal day; the air soft, balmy, genial; the sky of that
               softened and delicate blue upon which the eye loves to rest,—the blue which gives
               such relief to the rich beauty of the earth, all around glowing in the ripe and
               mellow tints of the most gorgeous of the seasons. Really such an autumn may well
               compensate our English climate for the fine spring of the south, that spring of which
               the poets talk, but which we so seldom enjoy. Such an autumn glows upon us like a
               splendid evening; it is the very sunset of the year; and I have been tempted forth
               into a wider range of enjoyment than usual. This walk (if I may use the Irish figure
               of speech called a bull) will be a ride. A very dear friend has beguiled me into
               accompanying her in her pretty equipage to her beautiful home, four miles off; and
               having sent forward in the<pb n="256"/> style of a running footman the servant who
               had driven her, she assumes the reins, and off we set.</p>
            <p>My fair companion is a person whom nature and fortune would have spoiled if they
               could. She is one of those striking women whom a stranger cannot pass without turning
               to look again; tall and finely proportioned, with a bold Roman contour of figure and
               feature, a delicate English complexion, and an air of distinction altogether her own.
               Her beauty is duchess-like. She seems born to wear feathers and diamonds, and to form
               the grace and ornament of a court; and the noble frankness and simplicity of her
               countenance and manner confirm the impression. Destiny has, however, dealt more
               kindly by her. She is the wife of a rich country gentleman of high descent and higher
               attainments, to whom she is most devotedly attached,—the mother of a little girl as
               lovely as herself, and the delight of all who have the happiness of her acquaintance,
               to whom she is endeared not merely by her remarkable sweetness of temper and kindness
               of heart, but by the singular ingenuousness and openness of character which
               communicate an indescribable charm to her conversation. She is as transparent as
               water. You may see every colour, every shade of a mind as lofty and beautiful as her
               person. Talking with her is like being in the Palace of Truth described by Madame de
                  Genlis;<pb n="257"/> and yet so kindly are her feelings, so great her indulgence
               to the little failings and foibles of our common nature, so intense her sympathy with
               the wants, the wishes, the sorrows, and the happiness of her fellow-creatures, that,
               with all her frank-speaking, I never knew her make an enemy or lose a friend.</p>
            <p>But we must get on. What would she say if she knew I was putting her into print? We
               must get on up the hill. Ah! that is precisely what we are not likely to do! This
               horse, this beautiful and high-bred horse, well fed, and fat and glossy, who stood
               prancing at our gate like an Arabian, has suddenly turned sulky. He does not indeed
               stand quite still, but his way of moving is little better—the slowest and most sullen
               of all walks. Even they who ply the hearse at funerals, sad-looking beasts who totter
               under black feathers, go faster. It is of no use to admonish him by whip or rein, or
               word. The rogue has found out, that it is a weak and tender hand that guides him now.
               Oh for one pull, one stroke of his old driver the groom! How he would fly! But there
               is the groom half-a-mile before us, out of ear-shot, clearing the ground at a capital
               rate, beating us hollow. He has just turned the top of the hill;—and in a moment—aye,
               now he is out of sight, and will undoubtedly so continue till he meets us at the lawn
               gate. Well! there is no great harm. It is only prolonging the pleasure of enjoying
               together this<pb n="258"/> charming scenery in this fine weather. If once we make up
               our minds not to care how slowly our steed goes, not to fret ourselves by vain
               exertions, it is no matter what his pace may be. There is little doubt of his getting
               home by sunset, and that will content us. He is, after all, a fine noble animal; and
               perhaps when he finds that we are determined to give him his way, he may relent, and
               give us ours. All his sex are sticklers for dominion, though, when it is undisputed,
               some of them are generous enough to abandon it. Two or three of the most discreet
               wives of my acquaintance contrive to manage their husbands sufficiently with no
               better secret than this seeming submission; and in our case the example has the more
               weight since we have no possible way of helping ourselves.</p>
            <p>Thus philosophising, we reached the top of the hill, and viewed with “reverted eyes”
               the beautiful prospect that lay bathed in golden sunshine behind us. Cowper says,
               with that boldness of expressing in poetry the commonest and simplest feelings, which
               is perhaps one great secret of his originality,<q>“<l>Scenes must be beautiful,
                     which, daily seen,</l><l>Please daily, and whose novelty survives</l><l>Long
                     knowledge and the scrutiny of years.</l>”</q> Every day I walk up this
               hill—every day I pause at the top to admire the broad winding road with the green<pb
                  n="259"/> waste on each side, uniting it with the thickly timbered hedgerows; the
               two pretty cottages at unequal distances, placed so as to mark the bends; the village
               beyond, with its mass of roofs and clustered chimneys peeping through the trees; and
               the rich distance, where cottages, mansions, churches, towns, seem embowered in some
               wide forest, and shut in by blue shadowy hills. Every day I admire this most
               beautiful landscape; yet never did it seem to me so fine or so glowing as now. All
               the tints of the glorious autumn, orange, tawny, yellow, red, are poured in profusion
               amongst the bright greens of the meadows and turnip fields, till the eyes is satiated
               with colour; and then before us we have the common with its picturesque roughness of
               surface, tufted with cottages, dappled with water, edging off on one side into fields
               and farms and orchards, and terminated on the other by the princely oak avenue. What
               a richness and variety the wild broken ground gives to the luxuriant cultivation of
               the rest of the landscape! Cowper has described it for me. How perpetually, as we
               walk in the country, his vivid pictures recur to the memory! Here is his common, and
               mine!</p>
            <q>“<l>The common overgrown with fern, and rough</l><l>With prickly gorse, that,
                  shapeless and deform’d</l><l>And dangerous to the touch, has yet its
                  bloom,</l><l>And decks itself with ornaments of gold;—</l><pb n="260"/><l>there
                  the turf</l><l>Smells fresh, and, rich in odoriferous herbs</l><l>And fungous
                  fruits nf earth, regales the sense</l><l>With luxury of unexpected
               sweets.</l>”</q>
            <p>The description is exact. There, too, to the left is my cricket-ground; (Cowper’s
               common wanted that finishing grace;) and there stands one solitary urchin, as if in
               contemplation of its past and future glories; for, alas! cricket is over for the
               season. Ah! it is Ben Kirby, next brother to Joe, king of the youngsters, and
               probably his successor—for this Michaelmas has cost us Joe! He is promoted from the
               farm to the mansion-house, two miles off; there he cleans shoes, rubs knives, and
               runs upon errands, and is, as his mother expresses it, “a sort of ‘prentice to the
               footman.” I should not wonder if Joe, some day or other, should overtop the footman,
               and rise to be butler; and his splendid prospects must be our consolation for the
               loss of this great favourite. In the mean time we have Ben.</p>
            <p>Ben Kirby is a year younger than Joe, and the schoolfellow and rival of Jem Eusden.
               To be sure his abilities lie in rather a different line: Jem is a scholar, Ben is a
               wag: Jem is great in figures and writing, Ben in faces and mischief. His master says
               of him, that, if there were two such in the school, he must resign his<pb n="261"/>
               office; and, as far as my observation goes, the worthy pedagogue is right. Ben is, it
               must be confessed, a great corrupter of gravity. He hath an exceeding aversion to
               authority and decorum, and a wonderful boldness and dexterity in overthrowing the one
               and puzzling the other. His contortions of visage are astounding. His “power over his
               own muscles and those of other people” is almost equal to that of Liston; and indeed
               the original face, flat and square and Chinese in its shape, of a fine tan
               complexion, with a snub nose, and a slit for a mouth, is nearly as comical as that
               matchless performer’s. When aided by Ben’s singular mobility of feature, his knowing
               winks and grins and shrugs and nods, together with a certain dry shrewdness, a habit
               of saying sharp things, and a marvellous gift of impudence, it forms as fine a
               specimen as possible of a humorous country boy, an oddity in embryo. Every body likes
               Ben, except his butts; (which may perhaps comprise half his acquaintance;) and of
               them no one so thoroughly hates and dreads him as our parish school- master, a most
               worthy King Log, whom Ben dumbfounds twenty times a day. He is a great ornament of
               the cricket-ground, has a real genius for the game, and displays it after a very
               original manner, under the disguise of awkwardness—as the clown shows off his agility
               in a pantomime. Nothing comes amiss to him. By the bye, he would have been the very
               lad for us in<pb n="262"/> our present dilemma; not a horse in England could master
               Ben Kirby. But we are too far from him now—and perhaps it is as well that we are so.
               I believe the rogue has a kindness for me, in remembrance of certain apples and nuts,
               which my usual companion, who delights in his wit, is accustomed to dole out to him.
               But it is a Robin Goodfellow nevertheless, a perfect Puck, that loves nothing on
               earth so well as mischief. Perhaps the horse may be the safer conductor of the
               two.</p>
            <p>The avenue is quite alive to-day. Old women are picking up twigs and acorns, and pigs
               of all sizes doing their utmost to spare them the latter part of the trouble; boys
               and girls groping for beech-nuts under yonder clump; and a group of younger elves
               collecting as many dead leaves as they can find to feed the bonfire which is smoking
               away so briskly amongst the trees,—a sort of rehearsal of the grand bonfire nine days
               hence; of the loyal conflagration of the arch traitor Guy Vaux, which is annually
               solemnized in the avenue, accompanied with as much of squibbery and crackery as our
               boys can beg or borrow—not to say steal. Ben Kirby is a great man on the fifth of
               November. All the savings of a month, the hoarded half-pence, the new farthings, the
               very luck-penny, go off in fumo on that night. For my part, I like this day-light
               mockery better. There is no gunpowder—odious<pb n="263"/> gunpowder! no noise but the
               merry shouts of the small fry, so shrill and happy, and the cawing of the rooks, who
               are wheeling in large circles overhead, and wondering what is going forward in their
               territory—seeming in their loud clamour to ask what that light smoke may mean that
               curls so prettily amongst their old oaks, towering as if to meet the clouds. There is
               something very intelligent in the ways of that black people the rooks, particularly
               in their wonder. I suppose it results from their numbers and their unity of purpose,
               a sort of collective and corporate wisdom. Yet geese congregate also; and geese never
               by any chance look wise. But then geese are a domestic fowl; we have spoiled them;
               and rooks are free commoners of nature, who use the habitations we provide for them,
               tenant our groves and our avenues, and never dream of becoming our subjects.</p>
            <p>What a labyrinth of a road this is! I do think there are four turnings in the short
               half-mile between the avenue and the mill. And what a pity, as my companion
               observes—not that our good and jolly miller, the very representative of the old
               English yeomanry, should be so rich, but that one consequence of his riches should be
               the pulling-down of the prettiest old mill that ever looked at itself in the Loddon,
               with the picturesque low-browed irregular cottage, which stood with its light-pointed
               roof, its clustered chim<pb n="264"/>neys, and its ever-open door, looking like the
               real abode of comfort and hospitality, to build this huge, staring, frightful,
               red-brick mill, as ugly as a manufactory, and this great square house, ugly and red
               to match, just behind. The old buildings always used to remind me of Wollett’s
               beautiful engraving of a scene in the Maid of the Mill. It will be long before any
               artist will make a drawing of this. Only think of this redness in a picture! this
               boiled lobster of a house! Falstaff’s description of Bardolph’s nose would look pale
               in the comparison.</p>
            <p>Here is that monstrous machine of a tilted waggon, with its load of flour, and its
               four fat horses. I wonder whether our horse will have the decency to get out of the
               way. If he does not, I am sure we cannot make him; and that enormous ship upon
               wheels, that ark on dry land, would roll over us like the car of Jaggernaut.
               Really—Oh no! there is no danger now. I should have remembered that it is my friend
               Samuel Long who drives the mill-team. He will take care of us. “Thank you, Samuel!”
               And Samuel has put us on our way, steered us safely past his waggon, escorted us over
               the bridge; and now, having seen us through our immediate difficulties, has parted
               from us with a very civil bow and good-humoured smile, as one who is always civil and
               good-humoured, but with a certain triumphant masterful look in his eyes, which I
                  have<pb n="265"/> noted in men, even the best of them, when a woman gets into
               straits by attempting manly employments. He has done us great good though, and may be
               allowed his little feeling of superiority. The parting salute he bestowed on our
               steed, in the shape of an astounding crack of his huge whip, has put that refractory
               animal on his mettle. On we go fast! past the glazier’s pretty house, with its porch
               and its filberd walk; along the narrow lane bordered with elms, whose fallen leaves
               have made the road one yellow; past that little farm-house with the horse-chesnut
               trees before, glowing like oranges; past the white-washed school on the other side,
               gay with October roses; past the park, and the lodge, and the mansion, where once
               dwelt the great earl of Clarendon;—and now the rascal has begun to discover that
               Samuel Long and his whip are a mile off, and that his mistress is driving him, and he
               slackens his pace accordingly. Perhaps he feels the beauty of the road just here, and
               goes slowly to enjoy it. Very beautiful it certainly is. The park paling forms the
               boundary on one side, with fine clumps of oak, and deer in all attitudes; the water,
               tufted with alders, flowing along on the other. Another turn, and the water winds
               away, succeeded by a low hedge, and a sweep of green meadows; whilst the park and its
               paling are replaced by a steep bank, on which stands a small, quiet, village
               ale-house; and<pb n="266"/> higher up, embosomed in wood, is the little country
               church, with its sloping church-yard and its low white steeple, peeping out from
               amongst magnificent yew-trees:</p>
            <cit>
               <quote>“<l>Huge trunks! and each particular trunk a growth</l>
                  <l>Of intertwisted fibres serpentine</l>
                  <l>Up-coiling, and invet’rately convolved.</l>”</quote>
               <bibl><author>Wordsworth</author>.</bibl>
            </cit>
            <p>No village-church was ever more happily placed. It is the very image of the peace and
               humbleness inculcated within its walls.</p>
            <p>Ah! here is a higher hill rising before us, almost like a mountain. How grandly the
               view opens as we ascend over that wild bank, overgrown with fern, and heath, and
               gorse, and between those tall hollies, glowing with their coral berries! What an
               expanse! But we have little time to gaze at present; for that piece of perversity,
               our horse, who has walked over so much level ground, has now, inspired, I presume, by
               a desire to revisit his stable, taken it into that unaccountable noddle of his to
               trot up this, the very steepest hill in the county. Here we are on the top; and in
               five minutes we have reached the lawn gate, and are in the very midst of that
               beautiful piece of art or nature (I do not know to which class it belongs), the
               pleasure-ground of F. Hill. Never was the “prophetic eye of<pb n="267"/> taste”
               exerted with more magical skill than in these plantations. Thirty years ago this
               place had no existence; it was a mere undistinguished tract of field and meadow and
               common land; now it is a mimic forest, delighting the eye with the finest
               combinations of trees and shrubs, the rarest effects of form and foliage, and
               bewildering the mind with its green glades, and impervious recesses, and apparently
               interminable extent. It is the triumph of landscape gardening, and never more
               beautiful than in this autumn sunset, lighting up the ruddy beech and the spotted
               sycamore, and gilding the shining fir-cones that hang so thickly amongst the dark
               pines. The robins are singing around us, as if they too felt the magic of the hour.
               How gracefully the road winds through the leafy labyrinth, leading imperceptibly to
               the more ornamented sweep. Here we are at the door amidst geraniums, and carnations,
               and jasmines, still in flower. Ah! here is a flower sweeter than all, a bird gayer
               than the robin, the little bird that chirps to the tune of “mamma! mamma!” the
               bright-faced fairy, whose tiny feet come pattering along, making a merry music,
               mamma’s own Frances! And following her guidance, here we are in the dear round room
               time enough to catch the last rays of the sun, as they light the noble landscape
               which lies like a panorama around us, lin<pb n="268"/>gering longest on that long
               island of old thorns and stunted oaks, the oasis of B. Heath, and then vanishing in a
               succession of gorgeous clouds.</p>
            <p>October 28.—Another soft and brilliant morning. But the pleasures of to-day must be
               written in short-hand. I have left myself no room for notes of admiration.</p>
            <p>First we drove about the coppice; an extensive wood of oak, and elm, and beech,
               chiefly the former, which adjoins the park paling of F. Hill, of which demesne,
               indeed, it forms one of the most delightful parts. The roads through the coppice are
               studiously wild, so that they have the appearance of mere carttracts: and the manner
               in which the ground is tumbled about, the steep declivities, the sunny slopes, the
               sudden swells and falls, now a close narrow valley, then a sharp ascent to an
               eminence, commanding an immense extent of prospect, have a striking air of natural
               beauty, developed and heightened by the perfection of art. All this, indeed, was
               familiar to me; the colouring only was new. I had been there in early spring, when
               the fragrant palms were on the willow, and the yellow tassels on the hazel, and every
               twig was swelling with renewed life; and I had been there again and again in the
               green leanness of midsummer; but never as now, when the dark verdure of the
                  fir-plantations,<pb n="269"/> hanging over the picturesque and unequal paling,
               partly covered with moss and ivy, contrasts so remarkably with the shining
               orange-leaves of the beech, already half fallen, the pale yellow of the scattering
               elm, the deeper and richer tints of the oak, and the glossy stems of the “lady of the
               woods,” the delicate weeping birch. The underwood is no less picturesque. The
               red-spotted leaves, and redder berries of the old thorns, the scarlet festoons of the
               bramble, the tall fern of every hue, seem to vie with the brilliant mosaic of the
               ground, now covered with dead leaves, and strewn with fircones, now, where a little
               glade intervenes, gay with various mosses and splendid fungi. How beautiful is this
               coppice to-day! especially where the little spring, as clear as crystal, comes
               bubbling out from the “old fantastic” beech root, and trickles over the grass, bright
               and silent as the dew in a May morning. The wood pigeons (who are just returned from
               their summer migration, and are cropping the ivy berries) add their low cooings, the
               very note of love, to the slight fluttering of the fallen leaves in the quiet air,
               giving a voice to the sunshine and the beauty. This coppice is a place to live and
               die in. But we must go. And how fine is the ascent which leads us again into the
               world, past those cottages hidden as in a pit, and by that hanging orchard and that
                  rough<pb n="270"/> heathy bank! The scenery in this one spot has a wildness, an
               abruptness of rise and fall, rare in any part of England, rare above all in this rich
               and lovely but monotonous county. It is Switzerland in miniature.</p>
            <p>And now we cross the hill to pay a morning visit to the family at the great
               house,—another fine place, commanding another fine sweep of country. The park,
               studded with old trees, and sinking gently into a valley, rich in wood and water, is
               in the best style of ornamental landscape, though more according to the common
               routine of gentlemen’s seats than the singularly original place which we have just
               left. There is, how- ever, one distinctive beauty in the grounds of the great
               house;—the magnificent firs which shade the terraces and surround the sweep, giving
               out in summer odours really Sabæan, and now in this low autumn sun producing an
               effect almost magical, as the huge red trunks, garlanded with ivy, stand out from the
               deep shadows like an army of giants. In-doors—Oh I must not take my readers in-doors,
               or we shall never getaway!—In-doors the sunshine is brighter still; for there, in a
               lofty lightsome room, sits a damsel fair and arch and piquante, one whom Titian or
               Velasquez should be born again to paint, leaning over an instrument *<note
                  type="author" anchored="true">* The dital harp.</note> as<pb n="271"/> sparkling
               and fanciful as herself, singing pretty French romances, and Scottish Jacobite songs,
               and all sorts of graceful and airy drolleries picked up I know not where—an English
               improvvisatrice! a gayer Annot Lyle! whilst her sister, of a higher order of beauty,
               and with an earnest kindness in her smile that deepens its power, lends to the piano,
               as her father to the violin, an expression, a sensibility, a spirit, an eloquence,
               almost human—almost divine! Oh to hear these two instruments accompanying my dear
               companion (I forgot to say that she is a singer worthy to be so accompanied) in
               Haydn’s exquisite canzonet, “She never told her love,”—to hear her voice, with all
               its power, its sweetness, its gush of sound, so sus- tained and assisted by
               modulations that rivalled its in- tensity of expression; to hear at once such poetry,
               such music, such execution, is a pleasure never to be forgotten, or mixed with meaner
               things. I seem to hear it still.</p>
            <q><l>As in the bursting spring time o’er the eye</l>
               <l>Of one who haunts the fields fair visions creep</l>
               <l>Beneath the closed lids (afore dull sleep</l>
               <l>Dims the quick fancy) of sweet flowers that lie</l>
               <l>On grassy banks, oxlip of orient dye,</l>
               <l>And palest primrose and blue violet,</l>
               <l>All in their fresh and dewy beauty set,</l>
               <l>Pictur’d within the sense, and will not fly:</l><pb n="272"/>
               <l>So in mine ear resounds and lives again</l>
               <l>One mingled melody,—a voice, a pair</l>
               <l>Of instruments most voice-like! Of the air</l>
               <l>Rather than of the earth seems that high strain,</l>
               <l>A spirit’s song, and worthy of the train</l>
               <l>That sooth’d old Prospero with music rare.</l></q>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
