<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <!--2017-01-10 ebb: Here is the source of our base text in Hathi Trust:
https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/ssd?id=mdp.39015008020441;seq=189;num=177
The nine missing sketches are Sections 16 to 23, the last nine sketches in OV.

Make a new file for each sketch. 
Follow the filenameing conventions that you see in Box. Each OV sketch begins with the letters OV, then the main title, and if a subtitle it goes in block caps at the end of the filename.xml
Please use the 1824 NCCO PDF (saved in OV folder in Box) to check and correct the text.

  -->

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
            <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>


            <editor>Samantha Webb</editor>
            <editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName>Jonathan M. Horanic</persName>
               <persName>Samantha Webb</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--2017-01-10 ebb: We need to change this sourceDesc to indicate we’re checking each text and altering it to represent the 1824 edition as published in NCCO. -->
            <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
            <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                  <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third
                     Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B.
                     Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
               </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first
               edition published in 1824. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="sketch">
            <pb n="199"/>
            <head>WALKS IN THE COUNTRY.<lb/>THE HARD SUMMER.
               <!--ebb: If there’s a subtitle use an <lb/> element to separate -->
            </head>
            <p>August 15th.—Cold, cloudy, windy, wet. Here we are, in the midst of the dog-days,
               clustering merrily round the warm hearth, like so many crickets, instead of
               chirruping in the green fields like that other merry insect the grasshopper;
               shivering under the influence of the Jupiter Pluvius of England, the watery St.
               Swithin; peering at that scarce personage the sun, when he happens to make his
               appearance, as intently as astronomers look after a comet, or the common people stare
               at a balloon; exclaiming against the cold weather, just as we used to exclaim against
               the warm. “What a change from last year!” is the first sentence you hear, go where
               you may. Every body remarks it, and every body complains of it; and yet in my mind it
               has its advantages, or at least its compensations, as every thing in nature has, if
               we would only take the trouble to seek for them.</p>
            <pb n="200"/>
            <p>Last year, in spite of the love which we are now pleased to profess towards that
               ardent luminary, not one of the sun’s numerous admirers had courage to look him in
               the face: there was no bearing the world till he had said “Good-night” to it. Then we
               might stir; then we began to wake and to live. All day long we languished under his
               influence in a strange dreaminess, too hot to work, too hot to read, too hot to
               write, too hot even to talk; sitting hour after hour in a green arbour, embowered in
               leafiness, letting thought and fancy float as they would. Those day-dreams were
               pretty things in their way; there is no denying that. But then, if one half of the
               world were to dream through a whole summer, like the Sleeping Beauty in the Wood,
               what would become of the other?</p>
            <p>The only office requiring the slightest exertion, which I performed in that warm
               weather, was watering my flowers. Common sympathy called for that labour. The poor
               things withered, and faded, and pined away; they almost, so to say, panted for
               drought. Moreover, if I had not watered them myself, I suspect that no one else
               would; for water last year was nearly as precious hereabout as wine. Our land-springs
               were dried up; our wells were exhausted; our deep ponds were dwindling into mud; and
               geese, and ducks, and pigs, and laundresses, used to look with a jealous and
               suspicious eye on the few and<pb n="201"/> scanty half-buckets of that impure
               element, which my trusty lacquey was fain to filch for my poor geraniums and
               campanulas and tuberoses. We were forced to smuggle them in through my faithful
               adherent’s territories, the stable, to avoid lectures within doors; and at last even
               that resource failed; my garden, my blooming garden, the joy of my eyes, was forced
               to go waterless like its neighbours, and became shrivelled, scorched, and sunburnt,
               like them. It really went to my heart to look at it.</p>
            <p>On the other side of the house matters were still worse. What a dusty world it was
               when about sunset we became cool enough to creep into it! Flowers in the court
               looking fit for a hortus siccus; mummies of plants, dried as in an oven; hollyhocks,
               once pink, turned into Quakers; cloves smelling of dust. Oh dusty world! May herself
               looked of that complexion; so did Lizzy; so did all the houses, windows, chickens,
               children, trees, and pigs in the village; so above all did the shoes. No foot could
               make three plunges into that abyss of pulverised gravel, which had the impudence to
               call itself a hard road, without being clothed with a coat a quarter of an inch
               thick. Woe to white gowns! woe to black! Drab was your only wear.</p>
            <p>Then, when we were out of the street, what a toil it was to mount the hill, climbing
               with weary steps and<pb n="202"/> slow upon the brown turf by the way-side, slippery,
               hot, and hard as a rock! And then if we happened to meet a carriage coming along the
               middle of the road,—the bottomless middle,—what a sandy whirl-wind it was! What
               choking! what suffocation! No state could be more pitiable, except indeed that of the
               travellers who carried this misery about with them. I shall never forget the plight
               in which we met the coach one evening in last August, full an hour after its time,
               steeds and driver, carriage and passengers, all one dust. The outsides and the horses
               and the coachman, seemed reduced to a torpid quietness, the resignation of despair.
               They had left off trying to better their condition, and taken refuge in a wise and
               patient hopelessness, bent to endure in silence the extremity of ill. The six
               insides, on the contrary, were still fighting against their fate, vainly struggling
               to ameliorate their hapless destiny. They were visibly grumbling at the weather,
               scolding the dust, and heating themselves like a furnace, by striving against the
               heat. How well I remember the fat gentleman without his coat, who was wiping his
               forehead, heaving up his wig, and certainly uttering that English ejaculation, which,
               to our national reproach, is the phrase of our language best known on the continent.
               And that poor boy, red-hot, all in a flame, whose mamma, having divested her own
               person of all superfluous apparel, was trying<pb n="203"/> to relieve his sufferings
               by the removal of his neck-kerchief—an operation which he resisted with all his
               might. How perfectly I remember him, as well as the pale girl who sate opposite,
               fanning herself with her bonnet into an absolute fever! They vanished after a while
               in their own dust; but I have them all before my eyes at this moment, a
               companion-picture to Hogarth’s Afternoon, a standing lesson to the grumblers at cold
               summers.</p>
            <p>For my part, I really like this wet season. It keeps us within, to be sure, rather
               more than is quite agreeable; but then we are at least awake and alive there, and the
               world out of doors is so much the pleasanter when we can get abroad. Every thing does
               well, except those fastidious bipeds, men and women; corn ripens, grass grows, fruit
               is plentiful; there is no lack of birds to eat it, and there has not been such a
               wasp-season these dozen years. My garden wants no watering, and is more beautiful
               than ever, beating my old rival in that primitive art, the pretty wife of the little
               mason, out and out. Measured with mine, her flowers are nought. Look at those
               hollyhocks, like pyramids of roses; those garlands of the convolvulus major of all
               colours, hanging around that tall pole, like the wreathy hop-bine; those magnificent
               dusky cloves, breathing of the Spice Islands; those flaunting double dahlias; those
                  splen<pb n="204"/>did scarlet geraniums, and those fierce and warlike flowers the
               tiger-lilies. Oh how beautiful they are! Besides, the weather clears sometimes—it has
               cleared this evening; and here are we, after a merry walk up the hill, almost as
               quick as in the winter, bounding lightly along the bright green turf of the pleasant
               common, enticed by the gay shouts of a dozen clear young voices, to linger awhile,
               and see the boys play at cricket.</p>
            <p>I plead guilty to a strong partiality towards that unpopular class of beings,
               country-boys: I have a large acquaintance amongst them, and I can almost say, that I
               know good of many and harm of none. In general they are an open, spirited,
               good-humoured race, with a proneness to embrace the pleasures and eschew the evils of
               their condition, a capacity for happiness, quite unmatched in man, or woman, or girl.
               They are patient, too, and bear their fate as scapegoats (for all sins whatsoever are
               laid as matters of course to their door, whether at home or abroad,) with amazing
               resignation; and, considering the many lies of which they are the objects, they tell
               wonderfully few in return. The worst that can be said of them is, that they seldom,
               when grown to man’s estate, keep the promise of their boyhood; but that is a fault to
               come—a fault that may not come, and ought not to be anticipated. It is astonishing
               how sensible they are to<pb n="205"/> notice from their betters, or those whom they
               think such. I do not speak of money, or gifts, or praise, or the more coarse and
               common briberies—they are more delicate courtiers; a word, a nod, a smile, or the
               mere calling of them by their names, is enough to insure their hearts and their
               services. Half-a-dozen of them, poor urchins, have run away now to bring us chairs
               from their several homes. “Thank you, Joe Kirby!—you are always first—yes, that is
               just the place.—I shall see every thing there. Have you been in yet, Joe?”—”No,
               ma’am! I go in next.”—” Ah, I am glad of that—and now’s the time. Really that was a
               pretty ball of Jem Eusden’s!—I was sure it would go to the wicket. Run, Joe! They are
               waiting for you.” There was small need to bid Joe Kirby make haste; I think he is,
               next to a race-horse, or a greyhound, or a deer, the fastest creature that runs—the
               most completely alert and active. Joe is mine especial friend, and leader of the
               “tender juveniles,” as Joel Brent is of the adults. In both instances this post of
               honour was gained by merit, even more remarkably so in Joe’s case than in Joel’s; for
               Joe is a less boy than many of his companions, (some of whom are fifteeners and
               sixteeners, quite as tall and nearly as old as Tom Coper) and a poorer than all, as
               may be conjectured from the lamentable state of that patched round frock, and the
               ragged condition of<pb n="206"/> those unpatched shoes, which would encumber, if any
               thing could, the light feet that wear them. But why should I lament the poverty that
               never troubles him? Joe is the merriest and happiest creature that ever lived twelve
               years in this wicked world. Care cannot come near him. He hath a perpetual smile on
               his round ruddy face, and a laugh in his hazel-eye, that drives the witch away. He
               works at yonder farm on the top of the hill, where he is in such repute for
               intelligence and good-humour, that he has the honour of performing all the errands of
               the house, of helping the maid, and the mistress, and the master, in addition to his
               own stated office of carter’s boy. There he works hard from five till seven, and then
               he comes here to work still harder under the name of play— batting, bowling, and
               fielding, as if for life, filling the place of four boys; being, at a pinch, a whole
               eleven. The late Mr. Knyvett, the king’s organist, who used in his own person to sing
               twenty parts at once of the hallelujah chorus, so that you would have thought he had
               a nest of nightingales in his throat, was but a type of Joe Kirby. There is a sort of
               ubiquity about him; he thinks nothing of being in two places at once, and for
               pitching a ball William Grey himself is nothing to him. It goes straight to the mark
               like a bullet. He is king of the cricketers from eight to sixteen, both inclusive,
               and an excellent ruler he makes. Never<pb n="207"/>theless, in the best-ordered
               states there will be grumblers, and we have an opposition here in the shape of Jem
               Eusden.</p>
            <p>Jem Eusden is a stunted lad of thirteen, or there-about, lean, small, and short, yet
               strong and active. His face is of an extraordinary ugliness, colourless, withered,
               haggard, with a look of extreme age, much increased by hair so light that it might
               rather pass for white than flaxen. He is constantly arrayed in the blue cap and
               old-fashioned coat, the costume of an endowed school to which he belongs; where he
               sits still all day, and rushes into the field at night, fresh, untired, and ripe for
               action, to scold, and brawl, and storm, and bluster. He hates Joe Kirby, whose
               immoveable good-humour, broad smiles, and knowing nods, must certainly be very
               provoking to so fierce and turbulent a spirit; and he has himself (being, except by
               rare accident, no great player) the preposterous ambition of wishing to be manager of
               the sports. In short, he is a demagogue in embryo, with every quality necessary to a
               splendid success in that vocation,—a strong voice, a fluent utterance, an incessant
               iteration, and a frontless impudence. He is a great “scholar,” too, to use the
               country phrase; his “piece,” as our village-schoolmaster terms a fine sheet of
               flourishing writing, something between a valentine and a sampler, enclosed within a
               border of little<pb n="208"/> coloured prints—his last, I remember, was encircled by
               an engraved history of Moses, beginning at the finding in the bulrushes, with
               Pharaoh’s daughter, dressed in a rose-coloured gown and blue feathers—his piece is
               not only the admiration of the school but of the parish, and is sent triumphantly
               around from house to house at Christmas, to extort halfpence and sixpences from all
               encouragers of learning—Montem in miniature. The Mosaic history was so successful,
               that the produce enabled Jem to purchase a bat and ball, which, besides adding to his
               natural arrogance (for the little pedant actually began to mutter against being
               eclipsed by a dunce, and went so far as to challenge Joe Kirby to a trial in
               Practice, or the Rule of Three), gave him, when compared with the general poverty, a
               most unnatural preponderance in the cricket state. He had the ways and means in his
               hands—(for, alas! the hard winter had made sad havoc among the bats, and the best
               ball was a bad one)—he had the ways and means, could withhold the supplies, and his
               party was beginning to wax strong, when Joe received a present of two bats and a ball
               for the youngsters in general, and himself in particular—and Jem’s adherents left him
               on the spot—they ratted, to a man, that very evening. Notwithstanding this desertion,
               their forsaken leader has in nothing relaxed from his pretensions, or his ill-humour.
               He still quarrels and<pb n="209"/> brawls as if he had a faction to back him, and
               thinks nothing of contending with both sides, the ins and the outs, secure of
               out-talking the whole field. He has been squabbling these ten minutes, and is just
               marching off now with his own bat (he has never deigned to use one of Joe’s) in his
               hand. What an ill-conditioned hobgoblin it is! And yet there is something bold and
               sturdy about him too. I should miss Jem Eusden.</p>
            <p>Ah, there is another deserter from the party! my friend the little hussar—I do not
               know his name, and call him after his cap and jacket. He is a very remarkable person,
               about the age of eight years, the youngest piece of gravity and dignity I ever
               encountered; short, and square, and upright, and slow, with a fine bronzed flat
               visage, resembling those convertible signs the Broad-Face and the Saracen’s Head,
               which, happening to be next-door neighbours in the town of B., I never know apart,
               resembling, indeed, any face that is open- eyed and immoveable, the very sign of a
               boy! He stalks about with his hands in his breeches pocket, like a piece of
               machinery; sits leisurely down when he ought to field, and never gets farther in
               batting than to stop the ball. His is the only voice never heard in the mélée; I
               doubt, indeed, if he have one, which may be partly the reason of a circumstance that
               I record to his honour, his fidelity to Jem Eusden, to whom he has adhered through
               every change of fortune with a tena<pb n="210"/>city proceeding perhaps from an
               instinctive conscious- ness that that loquacious leader talks enough for two. He is
               the only thing resembling a follower that our demagogue possesses, and is cherished
               by him accordingly. Jem quarrels for him, scolds for him, pushes for him; and but for
               Joe Kirby’s invincible good humour, and a just discrimination of the innocent from
               the guilty, the activity of Jem’s friendship would get the poor hussar ten drubbings
               a day.</p>
            <p>But it is growing late. The sun has set a long time. Only see what a gorgeous
               colouring has spread itself over those parting masses of clouds in the west,—what a
               train of rosy light! We shall have a fine sunshiny day to-morrow,—a blessing not to
               be undervalued, in spite of my late vituperation of heat. Shall we go home now? And
               shall we take the longest but prettiest road, that by the green lanes? This way, to
               the left, round the corner of the common, past Mrs. Welles’s cottage, and our path
               lies straight before us. How snug and comfortable that cottage looks! Its little yard
               all alive with the cow, and the mare, and the colt almost as large as the mare, and
               the young foal, and the great yard-dog, all so fat! Fenced in with hay-rick, and
               wheat-rick, and bean-stack, and backed by the long garden, the spacious
               drying-ground, the fine orchard, and that large field quartered into four different
               crops. How comfortable this cottage looks, and how well the<pb n="211"/> owners earn
               their comforts! They are the most prosperous pair in the parish—she a laundress with
               twenty times more work than she can do, unrivalled in flounces and shirt-frills, and
               such delicacies of the craft; he, partly a farmer, partly a farmer’s man, tilling his
               own ground, and then tilling other people’s;—affording a proof, even in this
               declining age, when the circumstances of so many worthy members of the community seem
               to have “an alacrity in sinking,” that it is possible to amend them by sheer
               industry. He, who was born in the workhouse, and bred up as a parish boy, has now, by
               mere manual labour, risen to the rank of a land-owner, pays rates and taxes, grumbles
               at the times, and is called Master Welles,—the title next to Mister—that by which
               Shakspeare was called:—what would man have more? His wife, besides being the best
               laundress in the county, is a comely woman still. There she stands at the spring,
               dipping up water for to-morrow,—the clear, deep, silent spring, which sleeps so
               peacefully under its high flowery bank, red with the tall spiral stalks of the
               foxglove and their rich pendent bells, blue with the beautiful forget-me-not, that
               gem-like blossom, which looks like a living jewel of turquoise and topaz. It is
               almost too late to see its beauty; and here is the pleasant shady lane, where the
               high elms will shut out the little twilight that re- mains. Ah, but we shall have the
               fairies’ lamps to<pb n="212"/> guide us, the stars of the earth, the glow-worms! Here
               they are, three almost together. Do you not see them? One seems tremulous, vibrating,
               as if on the extremity of a leaf of grass; the others are deeper in the hedge, in
               some green cell on which their light falls with an emerald lustre. I hope my friends
               the cricketers will not come this way home. I would not have the pretty creatures
               removed for more than I care to say, and in this matter I would hardly trust Joe
               Kirby—boys so love to stick them in their hats. But this lane is quite deserted. It
               is only a road from field to field. No one comes here at this hour. They are quite
               safe; and I shall walk here to-morrow and visit them again. And now, good night!
               beautiful insects, lamps of the fairies, good-night!</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
