<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="../SI_Ref_and_Resp.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to Sir William Elford, 24 August 1820</title><author>Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor>Rebecca Nesvet</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName>Rebecca Nesvet</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
               <!--ebb8: 29 May 2014: Transcription and header needs to be checked. Prosop is good. --></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and "should contain phrases describing the edition or version: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp><persName>Who?</persName></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><notesStmt><note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note><note>You can have multiple notes here.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository>Reading Central Library</repository><idno>MS number</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford <date when="1820-08-24">24 August 1820</date>.</head></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Describes our editorial practice.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><date when="1820-08-24">August 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>, 1820.</date><name type="place">Three Mile Cross</name></dateline><salute>To Sir William Elford</salute></opener><p>As Papa is going to this Club dinner which you my dear Friend wish so devoutly at the---<note resp="#rnes">Mitford anonymizes the place.</note> I take the opportunity of getting a frank to reply to your kind &amp; delightful &amp; most welcome letter.--What you say of Lady Madalina is charming--she must be a most fascinating woman--&amp; simething better than a fascinating woman to have excited such admiration in you. I hope I shall see her. I went into Reading yesterday to call on her if she were arrived--but she was not. I saw Mr. Palmer &amp; pleased him very much (for he is exceedingly fond &amp; proud of her) by telling him something of what you saw. He came hwever at night, I understand from some friends who have been here today--but today I myself was out <unclear>[illeg]</unclear>ing according to an engagement of a fortnight's stansing. Very likely she will call tomorrow, if not I will wait on her Lady<unclear>ship</unclear> you will comprehend, my dear Friend, that your opinion has excited this desire of an honour which to confess the truth I have hitherto rather shunned--I don't know why--but in spite of my age &amp; my rotundity &amp; rubincundity which seem to <del>[illeg]</del><add>take away my</add>right to such feelings, I am by fits &amp; starts desperately shy--I have a particular aversion to seeing people who desire to see one as they won't desire to see Punch, which I rather understood to be the case with the lady in question. Another thing was that her particular friend &amp; in this neighborhood is a person whom I do not like. A single woman of eighteen &amp; thirty with manners too light, too bold too young for eighteen--rouge on her sheeks and a leer in her eyes--a rattle without an idea--full of the outward and visible signs of cheerfulness, but with none of the inward and spiritual grace</p><p>--a person whose hoity-toityness is depressing beyond beyond conception--this was the favorite of the chosen, of one whose station &amp; talents gave her the power to chuse<!-- i.e., choose -->--And thus it was that gave me the impression which you must have seen &amp; which you have so completely counteracted. But I have not you yourself something judged of people by their aporiades? <!-- DEFINE APORIADES -->Don't you  like to meet with good company in the hearts of your friends, as well as at their tables? Now that we shall have you to talk about we shall get on excellently -- &amp; except that she will be furiously disappointed, &amp; that I shall be shy &amp; ashamed when even I think of my letters--those letters which are first like so many bottles of ginger beer, bouncing &amp; frothy &amp; flying in every body's face--with these trifling drawbacks we shall admire one another as much as is proper &amp; N. B. I hope &amp; trust my dear friend that friend that you will have the discretion to keep this paragraph to yourself--at least not to let any one see it <unclear>[illeg.]</unclear>through whom it can by any chance work round to her Ladyship's ears. [Illeg.] Reading--&amp; which is worse Three Mile Cross is Queen-land. -- Our opinins I believe are exactly alike--The letter was a firebrand tossed by a hand as reckless as it is mischievous, I have no patience with the meetings, &amp; Addresses &amp; the intolerable quantity of nonsense that is talked on the occasion. She may or she may not be guilty to the extent imputed--they may or they may not be able to prove the crime--but no one can think her innicent--It is impossible. No modesr woman could endure to hear that which she hears day by day--The courage she displays is the hard impudence of guilt--not the firmness of virtue.--Besides, my dear Sir William, women do not give up reputation except for the gratification of passion.--She cannot be innocent. I say this without having read a syllable of the trial--for having perfectly <add>made up my mind</add><del>[illeg.]</del>I do not wish to litter my brains with a quantity of trash just to settle whether an immodest woman be a little more or less bad than I had imagined. You will laugh at my earnestness, but really I am provoked at the quantity of <emph rend="underline">Queenery</emph> that is going on here <metamark rend="caret"/><add>not in this house for Papa and Mama are being moderate but <unclear>[illeg]</unclear> everyone else</add>is going on here--There has been a meeting at Reading, &amp; the address was signed by a thousand of the Inhabit<unclear>[illeg]</unclear>men &amp; men and boys--I am sorry to say by some soldiers quartered there. Is this wife?--The <unclear>[illeg]</unclear>she has of the soldiers' affections is really alarming--we hear of it on all sides. God grant the trial were safely over! If it do pass by tranuqilly, it will do some good by showing ministers that a standing army is a two edged sword.--You see I have not lost all my Whiggery--though I am no Queen's woman, I am indeed not a little disgusted at the part the opposition have taken in the question. Tell me what you think on the subject. For though I have said that our opinions were alike, I spoke only from preconceived ideas of your mode of thinking.--I can generally guess what you will say on most points. On Haydon's Picture for instance I foresaw that you did not like the disjointed Head. After all, I myself only like it conditionally--think it answers to the Artist's own design of perfect abstraction--thoughts <unclear>[illeg]</unclear>inward  &amp; upward--a mind absorbed in the contemplation of its own divine task of immeasurable love--loving the present in the glorious future--This was his intention &amp; this he has accomplished. But I do not think that this was the best expression he would have given--&amp; the disproportion was visible even to my unlearned eyes, though I could not have imagined it to be so monstrous. Moreover no authority can reconcile me to the glory--I do not believe that our Saviour was surrounded by any other light than the <del>et[ernal]</del>moral effulgence of his divine virtues, &amp; why should that which did not exist in nature be represented in an imitation of nature? Your <unclear>[illeg]</unclear>of the rest of the Picture is a most valuable anctin to my ardent admiration. I am afraid he will not dispose of it as he had hoped--the subscription with the limitation to 10 guineas has entirely failed &amp; he now means to throw it open without limitation--but as those who would have given their 50d have already given their 10£. I do not foresee much of an advantage from their change. His best chance is in its being purchased by some rich patron of Art--though the largeness of the piece &amp; of the picture are both against him. Nevertheless he is going on <unclear>sing song</unclear>with a picture quite as large--&amp; this intensity of purpose &amp; and of will--this absolute devotion to one great <unclear>god</unclear> is what I admire in him.--I like his simplicity too, his kindheartedness, his perfect singleness of mind. He is something of a "gunpowder Percy" <!--IDENTIFY--> to be sure, &amp; there is a stern brightness in his insufferable eyes which is exceedingly startling &amp; disagreeable--nevertheless little as I have seen of him--I do like him very much. Next to Napoleon &amp; Chantrey &amp; Wordsworth. I think him the greatest man of the Age--but Napoleon is <emph rend="underline">the</emph> man--there is no putting any body within a million of miles of the Exile of St. Helena. Miss James brought me a little bust of him from Birmingham which cost sixpence &amp; which is looking down upon me at this moment with the most gracious beningnity. My little dog is as dogs &amp; histories always are, a great physiognomist--moreover she is a very fastidious lady--won't go bear one person in a hundred--&amp; has generally speaking a singular aversion to busts &amp; pictures. Mama put Napoleon down to her expecting that she won't as <unclear>[illeg]</unclear> growl &amp; bark--when to our great astonishment she ran up to the last <!--END OF PAGE--></p></div></body><back>
        <!--ebb8: Prosopography all up to date with site index. --></back></text></TEI>