<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Headnote to <title ref="#CharlesI_MRMplay">The Tragedy of Charles the First</title></title><!--Include an xml:id for your text if we have it--><author ref="#rnes">Rebecca Nesvet</author><sponsor>University of Wisconsin, Green Bay</sponsor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Corrections and proofing by</resp><persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: June 1, 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a <orgName>Creative Commons</orgName> Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0
                  Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><notesStmt><note>[Anything we need to say about the preparation of this headnote beyond what we're covering in the rest of this header?]</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p>born digital</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>In October 2012, the modern British playwright <persName ref="#HowardBrenton">Howard Brenton
         </persName>’s drama <emph>55 Days</emph><cit><bibl corresp="#_55Days_play"><title>55 Days</title><author ref="#HowardBrenton">Howard Brenton</author></bibl></cit>
            
            
            
            opened at <placeName>London</placeName>’s <placeName ref="#HampstTh">Hampstead Theatre</placeName>. 
            A stridently pro-republican imagining of the birth of the short-lived English Commonwealth, 
            55 Days focuses on the 1649 struggle between the newly victorious parliamentary Lieutenant General <persName>Oliver Cromwell
            </persName> and the defeated King <persName>Charles I</persName>. The action builds to a wholly fictitious eleventh-hour 
            clandestine meeting between those two men. <persName ref="HowardBrenton">Brenton</persName>’s <persName>Cromwell</persName> has long desired this interview. <quote>“What kind of man is in there?”</quote><persName>Cromwell</persName> asks of<persName>Charles</persName>’s “royal shell” of “hard ceremony.” To solve this mystery, <persName ref="#HowardBrenton">Brenton’s</persName><persName>Cromwell </persName>seems to hound <persName>Charles</persName> to death, despite his own desire for a constitutional monarchy. </p><p>Anticipating <persName ref="#HowardBrenton">Brenton</persName>'s drama, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> speculates about the <quote>"man"</quote> inside <persName>Charles</persName>’s shell, and finds <persName>Charles</persName> the husband, father, and private individual essential to his political self-fashioning and his tragic flaws of intransigence and chivalry. But <persName>Mitford</persName>’s tragedy is more than a speculative character study. It also examines the nature and costs of political and domestic liberty, a theme with which many dramatists grappled in the turbulent, reform-minded 1820s. <persName>Mitford</persName>’s treatment of these themes resonates with unusual immediacy, as she eschews the Continental or exotic settings that dominated this dramatic tradition, instead dramatizing some of the most contentious events in British political history. </p><p>It may seem odd that the conservative <persName>Mitford</persName> should theatrically reanimate <persName>Cromwell</persName> and the <orgName>Regicides</orgName>, but the topic was not her idea. As she explains in her preface to the 1834 edition, the celebrated <placeName>Drury Lane</placeName> actor <persName>William Macready</persName> encouraged her to write a tragedy about <persName>Charles I</persName> because he wanted to play <persName>Cromwell</persName>, whom <persName>Mitford</persName> later called “one of the most remarkable characters that ever featured in the great Theatre of Life.” <persName>Macready</persName> may have been cut out for the role, as some of his most memorable roles were those of rebels, tyrants, or both. They included <persName>Richard III</persName>, the pseudohistorical Swiss revolutionary <persName>William Tell</persName>, <persName>Lord Byron</persName>’s doomed biblical despot <persName>Sardanapalus</persName>, and the <persName>Cardinal Richelieu</persName>, the posthumously infamous architect of <persName>Louis XIV</persName>’s <placeName>France</placeName>.</p><p>Initially, <persName>Macready</persName> believed that he would be allowed to stage <persName>Mitford</persName>’s <title>Charles the First</title> at <placeName>Drury Lane</placeName>. There was precedent for <persName>Cromwell</persName>’s theatrical representation. As <persName>Mitford</persName>’s Preface to <title>Charles I</title> explains, in 1747, <placeName>Drury Lane</placeName> had staged <persName>William Havard</persName>’s tragedy <title>Charles I</title> without incident. Later, <persName>Havard</persName>’s Charles played <placeName>Covent Garden</placeName>, and it was even reprinted in 1793, the year of the execution of <persName>Louis XVI</persName>. But <persName>Havard</persName>’s political context differed significantly from <persName>Mitford</persName>’s. In 1747, the Jacobite Wars had only just concluded with the defeat of <persName>Charles Edward Stuart</persName>, the great-grandson of <persName>Charles I</persName>, and in 1793, <persName>Havard</persName>’s plainly treacherous, sneering, over-the-top <persName>Cromwell</persName> would have seemed an anti-Jacobin cartoon villain. In 1825, however, <placeName>Britain</placeName> endured the deeply unpopular monarchy of <persName>George IV</persName>, whose nine-year Regency, occasioned by his father <persName>George III</persName>’s mental incapacity, demonstrated that not all kings are fit to rule. </p><p>Unsurprisingly, the Licenser <persName>(George Colman)</persName> and Lord Chamberlain (<persName>Lord Montrose</persName>)decreed that <title>Charles the First</title> could not be produced as written. But <persName>Mitford</persName> was not deterred. She revised the script, and nine years later, in 1834, it received its premiere and was published. In the preface to the first edition, <persName>Mitford</persName> subtly concedes the difficulty of staging her theme while <persName>George IV</persName> lived. Though she claims her work is not “revolutionary,” she also states that “against such a king as <persName>William IV</persName>,” brother and heir of <persName>George IV</persName>, a <persName>Cromwell</persName>-style rebel’s “shafts would fall harmless.” How they would have struck <persName>George IV</persName>, she refuses to speculate.</p><p>The Digital Mitford edition of <cit><bibl>Charles the First</bibl></cit> is transcribed from the 1834 first edition. Where this text varies from the 1825 text, variations have been coded. The 1825 licenser’s notes have been transcribed and coded as well. The Digital Mitford interface allows for parallel display of these three texts, enabling comparison. The play was reprinted in the 1841 edition of <persName>Mitford</persName> collected works. That text is not incorporated into the Digital Mitford edition.</p><p> With <persName>Mitford</persName> undergoing a critical renaissance, some scholars have analyzed the dramaturgy of <title>Charles I</title> and established its centrality to major tensions in early nineteenth-century theatre and society. <persName>Diego Saglia</persName>’s research situates <title>Charles the First</title>’s engagement with the theme of liberty in a topical tradition.<persName>Saglia</persName> finds that during the 1820s, the turbulent first decade of the Age of Reform, several  plays,  including <persName>Mitford's</persName><title>Julian</title> (YEAR) and <title>Rienzi</title> (written c. 1822-4, staged 1828), “intensely” explore the theme of liberty (<title>Saglia</title> 353). In this regard, <title> Rienzi</title> in particular anticipates <title>Charles the First</title>, as its historical hero, the Roman revolutionary <persName>Cola di Rienzo</persName>, seen as the “tribune of the people,” ultimately reveals himself a demagogue (Saglia 363). Likewise, <persName>Mitford</persName>’s <persName>Cromwell</persName> claims to represent the people of <placeName>England</placeName>, but nurses demagogical ambition. <persName>Mitford</persName> indicates this hypocrisy early in the drama, with a by giving <persName>Cromwell</persName> conspiratorial asides reminiscent of those of <persName>Shakespeare</persName>’s (and <persName>Macready</persName>’s) <persName>Richard III</persName>. For example, <persName>Mitford</persName>’s <persName>Cromwell</persName> allows his <orgName>New Model Army</orgName> comrades to brainstorm ways to deal with the defeated king, but when one, Major-General Sir <persName>Thomas Harrison</persName>, suggests exiling him, as the Biblical king <persName>Amaziah</persName> was exiled, <persName>Cromwell</persName> remarks “(Aside.) Ha! And they slew him [<placeName>Amaziah</placeName>]!” <persName>Cromwell</persName> diabolically deciphers <persName>Harrison</persName>’s unspoken wish, then engineers its dread fulfilment as a communal act.</p><p>Several modern critical studies examine <cit><bibl>Charles the First</bibl></cit> in comparison with other British Romantic dramas. Examining what <persName>Terence Allan Hoagwood</persName> terms the Romantic drama's "displacement of political themes," <persName>Joseph Nicholles</persName> argues that <persName>Colman</persName>'s suppression of <title>Charles the First</title><quote>"exhibits his own awareness that meanings"</quote> of publicly presented plays <quote>"are not under the control of authorial intention"</quote> (43). In the same critical anthology, <persName>Joseph Nicholes</persName> surveys the hermeneutics of historiography in Romantic dramatic representations of the English Civil War, which, he argues, tend to deflect association with the more recent revolution in France. <persName>Nicholes</persName> 
            observes that <persName>Mitford</persName>'s <persName>Cromwell</persName> drives the play's action, despite its 
            titular emphasis on <persName>Charles</persName> (Nicholes 144). <persName>Jacqueline Mulhallen</persName> compares 
            <title>Charles I</title> with the <persName>Percy Bysshe Shelley</persName>'s 1822 tragedy of the same title.
            <persName>Mulhallen</persName> claims that unlike <persName>Shelley</persName>'s play of ideas, <quote>“<persName>Mitford</persName>’s play is about a clash of personalities”</quote> 
            (Mulhallen 123), but <persName>Saglia</persName>’s context-reconstruction would seem to complicate this argument. </p><p>Scholars have also remembered <cit><bibl>Charles the First</bibl></cit> on account of its suppression. 
            <persName>John Russell Stephens</persName> clearly charts its censorship history (Stephens 41-4). 
            The play also merited an entry in <persName>Richard Findlater</persName>’s <title>Banned!: A Review of Theatrical Censorship in Britain</title>
       , published in the year that the British Parliament abolished the Lord Chamberlain’s theatre-censorship role.</p>
               
               <!--OUTLINE:<p>Notable plot points: Mitford’s dramatization of women’s history and centrality of women characters
                  -	Lady Fairfax and Henrietta put aside their differences
                  -	Formidable Lady Fairfax
                  -	Henrietta Maria tries to save her husband
                  
                  
                  -	This fictional episode echoes Lucy Hutchinson’s “treachery” against her husband, committed out of love and a prioritization of domestic life over political principle.
                  -	Hutchinson as a source, could have inspired made-up scene. Millington reference circumstantially suggests Hutchinson as a source, as Millington is not very significant outside Nottinghamshire and his quarrel with John Hutchinson
                  - Hutchinson was also a key source for Shelley’s <title>Charles I</title>. </p>
             
             
               
               <p>Conclusion
                  Allegedly, <persName>Shelley</persName> abandoned his work-in-progress because he disliked his sympathy with the tyrannical Charles. In an uncanny doubling of this authorial predicament, the Royalist <persName>Mitford</persName> seemed to the Licenser and Chamberlain to show inappropriate sympathy for <persName>Cromwell</persName>; to seek perhaps too enthusiastically the human being within the shell.</p>--></body><back>
              
<!--ebb: Rebecca: I've added all your entries to the Site Index, including the new bibls below, but I'm leaving your listBibl here because I'm asking you to add volume and page information to your citations. If you're going to add new bibl entries, please start them in a NEW listBibl beneath this one, OK? RN: 28 June 2014: OK, thanks--><div type="listBibl"><!--ebb: These bibls have been entered in the Site Index, but some could use more info. Signal me when you've added it.--><listBibl><bibl xml:id="HavardChasI_play"><title>The Tragedy of Charles I</title><author>William Havard</author><date when="1747">1747</date></bibl><bibl xml:id="CensorshipEnglDrama"><title>The Censorship of English Drama, 1824-1901</title><placeName>Cambridge: Cambridge University press</placeName><date when="2010">2010</date></bibl><bibl xml:id="_55Days_play"><title>55 Days</title><author>Howard Brenton</author><placeName>London: Nick Hern</placeName><date when="2012"/></bibl><bibl xml:id="RomDrama_Hoagwood"><title level="a">Romantic Drama and Historical Hermeneutics</title><title level="m">British Romantic Drama: Historical and Critical Essays</title><author>Terence Allan Hoagwood</author><editor>Terence Allan Hoagwood</editor><editor>Daniel Watkins</editor><pubPlace>Cranbury, NJ</pubPlace><publisher>Associated University Presses</publisher><date when="1998">1998</date><biblScope unit="page">22-55</biblScope></bibl><bibl xml:id="BannedThtr_Findlater"><title>Banned!: A Review of Theatrical Censorship in Britain</title><author>Richard Findlater</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Gibbon &amp; McKee</publisher><date when="1967">1967</date></bibl><bibl xml:id="Memoirs_Hutchinson"><title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title><author>Lucy Hutchinson</author><editor>Julius Hutchinson</editor><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Longman</publisher><date when="1806">1806</date></bibl><bibl xml:id="Trans_Nicholes"><title level="a">Transitory Actions and Men Betrayed: The French Revolution in the English Revolution in Romantic Drama</title><title level="m">British Romantic Drama: Historical and Critical Essays</title><author>Terence Allan Hoagwood</author><editor>Terence Allan Hoagwood</editor><editor>Daniel Watkins</editor><pubPlace>Cranbury, NJ</pubPlace><publisher>Associated University Presses</publisher><date when="1998">1998</date><biblScope unit="page">115-158</biblScope></bibl><bibl xml:id="ThtrShelley_Mulhallen"><title>Memoirs of the Life of Colonel Hutchinson</title><!--ebb: I have tried to follow examples when generating XML:IDs. I've read through the TEI-5 guidelines and the Digital Mitford Coding Guidelines and can't find an exact formula for text IDs. Where is it, please?--><author>Jacqueline Mulhallen</author><pubPlace>n.p.</pubPlace><publisher>OpenBook</publisher><date when="2010">2010</date></bibl></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI>