<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href='http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng' type='application/xml' schematypens='http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0'?><?xml-model href='http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng' type='application/xml'
	schematypens='http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron'?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Headnote to <title ref="#CharlesI_MRMplay">The Tragedy of Charles the First</title></title><!--Include an xml:id for your text if we have it--><author ref="#rnes">Rebecca Nesvet</author><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Corrections and proofing by</resp><persName ref="#rnes">Rebecca Nesvet</persName></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 14 June 2015. P5.</edition><respStmt><resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp><persName>Who?</persName></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a <orgName>Creative Commons</orgName> Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0
                  Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><notesStmt><note><!--[Anything we need to say about the preparation of this headnote beyond what we're covering in the rest of this header?]--></note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><p>born digital</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p><quote>In spite of the unfortunate event of my late effort <title level="m">Charles the First</title>, I still wish to make another attempt at Historical Tragedy,</quote> wrote <persName>Mary Russell Mitford</persName> on <date when="1825-12-01">1 December 1825</date>, to <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">George Colman</persName>, the London theatre playwright, manager, and advisor to the Licenser of Plays. <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> planned to dramatize the conflict between the medieval Archbishop <persName>Thomas à Becket</persName> and King <persName>Henry II</persName>, who apparently arranged <persName>Becket</persName>'s assassination. Before writing this work, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> wished to know if <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">Colman</persName> would approve of its presentation. <quote>Your opinion, or rather your advice, whether for or against the play is all I ask,</quote> she assured him; she would be equally grateful for his approval of the idea or his <quote>kind warning</quote> to desist<cit><bibl><!--ADD--></bibl></cit>.</p><p><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> had reason to worry that <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">Colman</persName> might find her <quote>attempt at Historical Tragedy</quote> objectionable, and even unproduceable, as a few weeks earlier, he had advised the Licenser, <persName ref="#Duke_Montrose">Lord Montrose</persName>, to reject <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>’s completed <title level="m" ref="#CharlesI_MRMplay">Tragedy of Charles the First</title>. On <date when="1825-09-29">29 September 1825</date>, <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">Colman</persName> informed <persName ref="#Duke_Montrose">Montrose</persName> that <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>'s title <quote>brings, instantly, to mind the violent commotions</quote> of the Caroline era, and, more dangerously <quote>exhibits the fanatical manners</quote> (mores) and <quote>puritanical cant</quote> of <persName ref="#Cromwell">Oliver Cromwell</persName> and his associates. Also, she <quote>blasphemously</quote> employs <quote>Scriptural allusions, &amp; quotations,</quote> and characters take the name of the Lord in vain <cit><bibl><!--ADD--></bibl></cit>. <persName ref="#Duke_Montrose">Montrose</persName> concluded that the play is <quote>certainly not proper for representation</quote> in a theatre.  On <date when="1825-10-10">10 October</date>, <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">Colman</persName> duly <quote>suspended</quote> the play's license on account of its <quote>peculiar title &amp; incidents</quote><cit><bibl><!--ADD--></bibl></cit>. In these two men's shared view, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>’s depiction of the events leading up to the Regicide could not be produced for public audiences.  </p><p>That <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> did not check with <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">Colman</persName> before writing this play reinforces the impression that <persName ref="#Duke_Montrose">Montrose</persName>’s decision blindsided her. In fact, the path to Regicide was not inherently unstageable territory in the London theatre of the long eighteenth century. True, the <date when="1660">1660</date> Act of Indemnity and Oblivion criminalized any discussion of the Regicide that might serve to “revive the memory of the late differences,” or to investigate any surviving Briton’s involvement in <persName ref="#ChasI">Charles</persName>’s deposition and death <cit><bibl><!--ADD David Norbrook, WRITING THE ENGLISH REPUBLIC: POETRY, RHETORIC, AND POLITICS, 1627-60 (cup, 1999), 1.--></bibl></cit>. This Act suppressed Commonwealth history well into the eighteenth century. For instance, the late-eighteenth-century descendants of one Regicide, Colonel <persName>John Hutchinson</persName>, embargoed his wife <persName>Lucy Hutchinson</persName>’s manuscript account of her husband’s exploits, her own political activity, and her hopes for a future in which their religious and political ideals would not be condemned. When the historian and <q>Republican Virago</q><persName>Catharine Macaulay</persName> (1731-91) implored the Hutchinson descendant <persName>Sir Thomas Hutchinson</persName> to publish the memoir, he refused. It first appeared, with a profusion of Whiggish apology from <persName>Sir Thomas</persName>'s nephew <persName>Julius Hutchinson</persName>, in <date when="1806">1806</date>.<cit><bibl><!--ADD--></bibl></cit></p><p>However, the Regicide could be staged during the eighteenth century, in certain rhetorical situations. As <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">Colman</persName> and <persName ref="#Duke_Montrose">Montrose</persName> knew, in <date when="1737">1737</date>, the playwright <persName ref="#Havard_Wm">William Havard</persName> had seen his <title ref="#HavardChasI_play">King Charles the First, An Historical Tragedy</title> produced at <placeName ref="#Drury_Lane_Theatre">Drury Lane</placeName>. Less than thirty years after the <date when="1715">1715</date> and <date when="1719">1719</date> defeats of Jacobite insurgents, and a few years before their final attempt (<date when="1745">1745</date>), <persName ref="#ChasI">Charles</persName> may have been associated less with British monarchic hegemony than with this deposed faction and its threats to the Hanoverian status quo. The <quote>decline of the Jacobite cause</quote>, observes critic <persName>Richard C. McCoy</persName>, made <persName ref="#Havard_Wm">Havard</persName>'s <persName ref="#ChasI">Charles</persName> a figure of pathos and pity <cit><bibl><!--ADD ALTERATIONS OF STATE: SACRED KINGSHIP IN THE ENGLISH REFORMATION (COLUMBIA UP, 2002), 135.--></bibl></cit>. Thus abjectly humanized, he did not invite parallel with <persName>George II</persName>. </p><p>In the Regency, the Regicide's image had again changed. The massive unpopularity of the <q>mad</q> king <persName ref="#GeoIII">George III (d. <date when="1820-01-29">1820</date>)</persName> and his successor <persName ref="#GeoIV">George IV</persName> invalidated <persName ref="#Havard_Wm">Havard</persName>'s safeguards. <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Sir Walter Scott</persName> had created a new narrative of the defunct Jacobite struggle, wherein <persName ref="#GeoIV">George IV</persName> inherited the Stuart claim to the British throne and even earned a Scottish cultural identity <cit><bibl><!--ADD Caroline McCracken-Flesher--></bibl></cit>. Meanwhile, voices of reform began to put the suppressed memory of the Regicides to new and radical use. In <date when="1819">1819</date>, <persName ref="#Shelley_PB">Percy Bysshe Shelley</persName> began writing another <title>Tragedy of Charles the First</title>. As <persName>Nora Crook</persName> demonstrates this radical political drama deprecates both <persName>Charles</persName> and <persName>Cromwell</persName>, and explores the utopian potential of the Commonwealth envisioned by the complicated rebel and republican martyr Sir <persName ref="#Vane_hist">Henry Vane</persName>. Why <persName ref="#Shelley_PB">Shelley</persName> abandoned this play is unclear, but he wrote in frustration of his sympathy for <persName ref="#ChasI">Charles</persName>, suggesting that his envisioned Regicidal drama was self-censored <!-- <cit><bibl> ADD CROOK </bibl></cit> -->.</p><p>While <persName ref="#Shelley_PB">Shelley</persName>’s <title>Charles the First</title> fulfilled a political exigency, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> was drawn by the subject’s potential as a vehicle for the actor-manager <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">William Macready</persName>. To Mitford, <persName ref="#Cromwell">Cromwell</persName> was <q>one of the most remarkable creatures that ever figured in the great Theatre of Life</q><cit><bibl><!--Mitford--></bibl></cit>. Modern historians agree: as <persName>Alan Marshall</persName> contends, <q>few men in the  past have attracted more enthusiasts and detractors.</q><cit><bibl><!--ADD Alan Marshall, CROMWELL: SOLDIER (LONDON: BRASSEY, 2004), 7.--></bibl></cit><persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Macready</persName> tended to play rebels, and despots, including <persName ref="#RichardIII">Richard III</persName>, the pseudohistorical Swiss revolutionary <persName>William Tell</persName>, <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName>'s doomed Oriental tyrant <persName>Sardanapalus</persName>, and the <persName>Cardinal Richelieu</persName>, the posthumously infamous architect of <persName>Louis XIV</persName>'s France, who is now perhaps best known as the enemy of the <orgName>Three Musketeers</orgName>.</p><p>At the same time, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>'s <title ref="#CharlesI_MRMplay">Charles the First</title> is not apolitical. <persName ref="#dsa">Diego Saglia</persName> has demonstrated that many plays produced in the <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> patent theatres during the 1820s opening of the Age of Reform investigate the concept of liberty, and <persName>Mitford</persName>’s are no exceptions. As <persName>Saglia</persName> points out, her <title ref="#Rienzi">Rienzi</title>, inspired by the medieval Italian rebel (or demagogue) <persName ref="#Rienzo_hist">Cola di Rienzo</persName>, fits this description. So does <title><emph>Charles the First</emph></title>, whose characters attempt to balance different sorts of liberties—domestic as well as political and spiritual <cit><bibl><!--ADD Saglia 363--></bibl></cit>.  In this play, <persName ref="#Cromwell">Cromwell</persName> claims to represent the people of <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>, but privately nurses tyrannic ambition. <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> indicates this hypocrisy early in the drama, by giving <persName>Cromwell</persName> conspiratorial asides reminiscent of those of <persName>Shakespeare</persName>'s (and <persName>Macready</persName>'s) <persName ref="#RichardIII">Richard III</persName>. For example, while <persName ref="#Cromwell">Cromwell</persName> allows his <orgName ref="#New_Model_Army">New Model Army</orgName> comrades to brainstorm ways to deal with the deposed king, and one, <persName ref="#Harrison_hist">Major-General Sir Thomas Harrison</persName> suggests exiling him like the Biblical king <persName ref="#Amaziah">Amaziah</persName>, <persName ref="#Cromwell">Cromwell</persName> remarks <quote><stage>(Aside)</stage> Ha! And they slew him [Amaziah]!</quote> This <persName ref="#Cromwell">Cromwell</persName> diabolically deciphers <persName ref="#Harrison_hist">Harrison</persName>'s unspoken wish, then engineers its dread fulfillment as a communal act. And yet, he also persuasively champions political liberty. He warns the would-be Regicides that should <persName>Charles</persName> survive, he will avenge himself. Then:</p><quote><l>[...] with us will die</l><l>The liberty for which the blood of saints</l><l>And martyrs hath been spilt, freedom of act,</l><l>Of speech, of will, of faith!</l></quote><p>Surely this is a paean to liberty, no matter its motivation.</p><p><persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>'s representation of <persName ref="#ChasI">Charles</persName> seems equally diplomatic. <persName ref="#ChasI">Charles</persName>’s complicating humanity apparently catalyzed <persName ref="#Shelley_PB">Shelley</persName>’s internal censor, but <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> embraces psychological and moral complexity, making <persName ref="#ChasI">Charles</persName> at once a loving father, an impassioned husband, and a disastrous king. <persName ref="#Queen_Ch1">Henrietta Maria</persName>, <persName ref="#ChasI">Charles</persName>'s French queen, displays similar depth--and frequently steals the scene. Anachronistically styling herself a Gothic heroine, <persName ref="#Queen_Ch1">Henrietta Maria</persName> stalks castle corridors in search of her imprisoned love, rails at his enemies, and, when she finds him, offers to trade her life for his via a ruse that strongly anticipates <persName>Sydney Carton</persName>’s redemptive self-sacrifice in <title><emph>A Tale of Two Cities</emph></title>, which <persName>Charles Dickens</persName> would not write until four years after <persName>Mitford</persName>’s death. </p><p>When this rich dramatic tapestry failed to impress <persName ref="#Colman_the_Younger">Colman</persName> and <persName ref="#Duke_Montrose">Montrose</persName>, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> revised it, and it was finally staged and published in 1834. By then, the climate had become more favorable. In a new preface, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> claims that although her work was never <q>revolutionary, [...] against such a king as <persName ref="#WilliamIV">William IV</persName>,</q> rebellion's <q>shafts would fall harmless.</q><!--citation--> (How they might have struck <persName ref="#GeoIV">George IV</persName> in 1825, she does not speculate.)</p><p>Still, the <q>unfortunate event</q> that linked <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>' with English Republican transgression may have kept haunting her. In <date when="1840">1840</date>, the struggle for various kinds of reform, including working-class male suffrage, had culminated with the composition of the <title>People’s Charter</title> and its presentation to <orgName ref="#Parliament_UK">Parliament</orgName>. Its suspected primary author, <persName>William Lovett</persName>, was serving a three-year sentence at <placeName>Wandsworth Gaol</placeName> for having allegedly incited <orgName>Chartist demonstrators</orgName> at <placeName>Birmingham</placeName>’s <placeName>Bull Ring</placeName> to violence. <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> was writing on commission again, this time for the ornate illustrated compendium <title>Finden’s Tableaux</title>. <title level="a">The Roundhead’s Daughter</title> makes it clear where her sympathies lie with regards to the English Civil War, the Commonwealth, and the Regicide. In this story, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>’s <orgName>Parliamentarians</orgName> are ‘<orgName>Puritans</orgName>’, and are stereotypically ‘Puritanical’. The heroine, <persName>Mabel Goodwin</persName>, wears ‘the pinched coif and demure kerchief of the Puritans’, squandering her beauty (36). Also squandered by the <orgName>Commonwealth-men</orgName> are <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>’s land and cultural heritage. In 1658, the <placeName>English countryside</placeName> is characterized by ‘neglected desolation’, and the heroine’s suitor’s father, the disenfranchised Cavalier <persName>Lord Philip Montresor</persName>, has seen his ‘magnificent mansion’, where ‘the <persName ref="#ElizI">Virgin Queen</persName>’ once danced with his ancestor, stolen by the ‘<orgName>Committee of Sequestration</orgName>’ and bestowed upon <persName>Mabel</persName>’s father, <persName>Colonel Goodwin</persName>, ‘a plain soldier and zealous Roundhead’ (36). Luckily, <persName>Mabel</persName> defies her father and <persName ref="#Cromwell">Cromwell</persName>’s regime to marry her nobleman, and, after the Restoration, <persName>Lord Philip</persName> magnanimously saves the <persName>Colonel</persName> and facilitates the ‘reconciliation’ in ‘tranquillity’ of the formerly warring factions<cit><bibl><!--ADD FINDEN--></bibl></cit>. Like the ending of <title level="m">Waverley</title>, that of <title level="a">The Roundhead’s Daughter</title> preaches reconciliation in a context favorable to the Hanoverian victors. Also uniting morality (‘Good win[s]’) with wealth (<persName>Montresor</persName> means ‘my treasure’), <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> lets her audience know that in the Victorian era, the dissensions of the Civil War have been completely healed.</p><p>At this time, The Digital Mitford provides the two major variants of <title level="m" ref="#CharlesI_MRMplay">Charles the First</title>: the manuscript that <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> submitted in <date when="1825">1825</date> to the Licenser’s office, with <persName ref="#Duke_Montrose">Montrose</persName>’s annotations, and the substantially revised print edition (London: <!--PUBLISHER, 1834)-->. The play was printed once more in <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>’s era, in her collected <bibl corresp="#Dramatic_Works_of_MRM"><title level="m">Dramatic Works</title> (<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>, <date when="1854">1854</date>)</bibl>. This copy is apparently identical in substance to <bibl>the <date when="1834">1834</date> version</bibl>. A few typos have been corrected since <date when="1834">1834</date>, and there are some formatting differences, but the script was not changed. Nor was the <title level="a">Preface</title>, which discusses the events of <date when="1834">1834</date> in the same words as that edition's preface, making the early years of the Age of Reform seem eerily current. This <bibl><date when="1854">1854</date> volume’s new <title level="a">General Introduction</title> is included in the Digital Mitford, edited by <editor ref="#lmw">Lisa Wilson</editor></bibl>. </p><p>Even in the twentieth century, simulating the Regicide remains taboo. In the <date when="2012">2012</date><placeName>Hampstead Theatre</placeName>, <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> premiere of <bibl corresp="#_55Days_play"><author>Howard Brenton</author>’s play <title level="m">55 Days</title></bibl>, the executioner lifts his ax above the deposed king, but before the blade can fall, the curtain does. The continuing controversiality of this execution as stage drama compels us to reread <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>'s take--and perhaps to revive it.</p></body></text></TEI>