<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Benjamin Robert Haydon 18 April 1821.</title>
            <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>

            <editor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by </resp>
               <persName ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</persName>

            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp> Date last checked: <date when="2014-06-03">2014-06-03</date>. Proofing and
                  corrections by: </resp>
               <persName ref="#ad">Alexandra Drayton</persName>

               <!--ebb: 28 May 2014: Need to update header and review comments. Prosopography refs are now current. Need to check transcription, etc., and some possible new prosop entries in unclear words/names. --><!-- ad: 04 May 2014: I think this is now all up to date -->
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition> This is optional, used to describe this edition, and "should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>



         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Reading Central Library</repository>
                  <idno>MS number</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to B. R. Haydon, <date>18 April
                  1821</date>.</head>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. A different
               from Mitford's, that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines
               across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across
               Mitford's writing. This hand has drawn a diagonal line in red pencil down page 3 of
               the manuscript of this letter. </handNote>
            <handNote xml:id="black_ink" medium="black_ink"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford,
               perhaps cataloging letters and describing them. Page 2 of this letter manuscript
               bears horizontal cross-outs at lines 1 and 24 of paragraph 2, and a vertical line
               running down the center of the page. The hand has cross-written above the vertical
               line: <quote>"Omit all this it is told in the next letter."</quote> Page 3 of the
               manuscript bears horiontal cross-outs at lines 10 and 26, and a vertical line runs
               down the center of the page. The hand has cross-written above the vertical
                  line:<quote>"Omit all this it is in the next
               letter."</quote>
            </handNote>
         </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date when="1821-04-18">April 18<hi rend="superscript" rendition="superscript"/>
                     1821.</date>
                  <name type="place">Three Mile Cross</name>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I have been waiting till <date>Easter</date> should bring some Parliament men into
               the Country to thank you for your delightful account of
               your <placeName>Glasgow</placeName> excursion--Oh what an honour &amp; a pleasure it
               is to be selected as a friend to whom you like <q>“to unburthen your
                  thoughts”</q>--&amp; how heartily I sympathised with all your feelings whether
               stern or relenting--I had been waiting for a frank to tell you this--but I suppose
               indignation is a stonger impulse than pleasure for since I received the
                  <title resp="#Examiner">Examiner</title> this morning I can no longer refrain from writing. I had read the Article in the magazine <!--identify article and author--> wondering who could be meant--thinking
               how likely it was to be misrepresented but never for an instant dreaming that it
               could be aimed at you--of all impossible slanders that seemed the most
               impossible--&amp; I am even now lost in astonishment at such a malicious <del rend="squiggles" quantity="1" unit="word"><gap reason="illegible"/></del><add
                  place="above">falsehood's</add> finding a place
               in so respectable a publication. I suppose that as there is now no regular Editor
               <!--was not Leigh Hunt the editor at this time? substantiate this.#ad Leigh Hunt was editor of the Examiner from 1808-1821-->
               the venom slid in undetected. I am almost glad that it did since it has afforded you
               an opportunity of making a defence &amp; dignified &amp; so spirited--What a
               necessary thing it is that a great painter should be a good writer! And really in
               these days when the appetite for anecdote as it is called (that is for scandal) is so
                     <unclear><supplied>craving</supplied></unclear> &amp; the gossip of a set of
                     unidea'd women over a country tea table
               yields in malice to the slander of literary chit chat, every man should be brought to
               wield the pen as a weapon of defence against his enemies his rivals &amp; his
               friends. Do you know to which class the present writer belongs?--I will not talk of
               him any more for it really gives me unwomanly feelings--to use a womanly
               phrase <q>it puts me in a passion.</q>----<note resp="#ebb">Here Mitford's long dash signals a change of topic, effectively a paragraph break.</note></p><p>What became of your poor
                  <placeName ref="#Glasgow">Glasgow</placeName> culprit<!--identify this Glasgow culprit-->? Did he 
               come back to London according to your behest? And is he likely to<pb n="2"/> turn honest &amp;
               make his way in the world? I think if any thing <del rend="squiggles"/> could reform
               a man your severity of words &amp; kindness of action would do so.</p>
                  <handShift/><add hand="#black_ink">Omit all this it is in the next
                     letter.</add><note resp="#ebb">This is written vertically from bottom center to nearly top center of this second leaf of the letter, and is accompanied by a long vertical line to the right of the inscription, meeting to horizontal lines at either end. The top line crosses out nearly all of the first full line of Mitford's next paragraph: the words: "I think you know my friend Mrs. Hofland--I have", and the bottom line crosses out the fifth line from the bottom of the leaf, the line reading, "in her most pathetic manner.'----Having begun storytelling".</note>
            <p><handShift/><del rend="strikethrough" hand="#black_ink"><handShift/>I think you know my friend <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs Hofland</persName> I have</del>
               just had a letter from <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> containing so
               remarkable an anecdote respecting her that I am tempted to transcribe it--To
               understand it I must tell you that <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Mrs Hofland</persName>
               has been for several years involved in a Chancery suit on the success of which they
               had placed great reliance. (Ah I could have told them what a miserable thing is a
               successful Chancery suit!)<!--identify the Chancery suit that Barbara Hofland was involved in--> Now for <rs type="letter"><persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James's</persName> letter</rs>. <quote cit="#James_Miss">"The Hofland suit is decided in their favour--but all the costs
                  being to be paid out of the property not a sixpence <persName ref="#Hofland_B"
                     >Mrs. <abbr>Hof.</abbr></persName> says will come to them. <!--ebb: Proofread to here, 4 July 2014-->Their lawyer had
                  neglected to write &amp; the news of the decision was brought by a neighbour who
                  told her only that it was decided in their favour--she went to town to enquire
                     <sic>was</sic><!--this is noted as sic because the word "and" appears to have been skipped in the ms-->
                  quite overcome by the information she received--I
                  <!-- I believe this I refers not to Mitford but Hofland or Mitford's correspondent-->
                  was about to mount the outside of the <placeName>Twickenham</placeName> coach to
                  return all <unclear>illegible<supplied>around</supplied></unclear> as you may
                  suppose when recollecting she should save sixpence in going by the
                     <placeName>Richmond</placeName> Stage &amp; such an one being on hand, she
                  withdrew her <unclear>illegible <supplied resp="#ad">boot</supplied></unclear> although a
                  most respectable woman with her husband at her side affected to make room for
                  her--Home she came by the Richmond coach &amp; saved her sixpence &amp; her life.
                  The <placeName>Twickenham</placeName> coach was overturned an hour after &amp;
                  that decent woman in whose place she would have sat killed on the spot. The
                  husband had his collar bone &amp; a rib broken. This most striking event gave a
                  new &amp; <unclear><supplied>just</supplied></unclear> turn to her thoughts--I am
                  sure you will feel as thankful as I did at the detail which she gave
                  <!-- is it worth annotating for this coach accident?--> in her most pathetic
                  manner."</quote> _____
               <!--a cross-out line is drawn over the foregoing text in a different hand--> Having
               begun storytelling I must tell
               you <del rend="strikethrough">another</del> <add place="above">a story</add>
               <!--this last phrase is written above the deleted word--> which comes from Germany.
               The King of <placeName>Naples</placeName> having arrived at
                        <placeName>Laybach</placeName> before the other sovereigns <del rend="squiggles"><unclear><supplied>of</supplied></unclear></del>was
               desirous to have the amusement of bear hunting which of course was to be provided for
               him but there being no bears resident in the neighbourhood one
               was purchased of a <unclear><supplied>
               Savoyard</supplied></unclear><!--tag Savoyard as nationality?--> <!-- #ad I think Savoyard is a very good reading of this word--> &amp; placed a few
               miles out of town in a thicket. The King
                    attended as the story went by a train of
                  <unclear>illegible <supplied>cars &amp;</supplied></unclear> courtiers arrived near the place &amp; the bear
               finding himself in the neighbourhood of the <unclear>illegible</unclear> good company
               fancied he was to perform as usual came out on his hind legs in a most graceful
               attitude--which alas! had an effect on the hard heart of his Neopolitan majesty who
               discharged his piece &amp; shot him dead. This story is none of my radical
               inventions--it came from <persName>Lord <unclear>illegible</unclear></persName> to
               Mr. <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm"><abbr>W.</abbr>Elford</persName> &amp; from him to
               me. ____
               <!--an underline is drawn by Mitford which I take to indicate a paragraph break-->
            </p>
            <p>I have a great grievance just now which I have nothing <damage rend="smudge" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied>to</supplied></unclear>
                     
               <!--a cross-out line is drawn on the foregoing lines of text likely in a different hand-->
               do with--but which I cannot help thinking a grievance nevertheless. The <persName
                  ref="#Wellington_Duke">Duke of Wellington</persName>'s sons are at home for the
               <orgName>Eton</orgName> &amp; they come every day to a little alehouse next
               door to learn French of a Jew who is lodging there for the purpose of teaching them.
                  <quote>The poor little lads <persName ref="#MRM"> Ma'am </persName></quote>, says my friend
               the landlord, <quote>are kept very strict. They never look up but their tutor
               corrects them, &amp; there they sit in my parlour from eleven to half past
                  four &amp; never have a glass of anything.</quote> Without sympathising very
               deeply in the misfortune which my friend the <!-- link to <person xml:id="RoseInnLandlord"> who was the fictional landlord in Our Village --> <roleName>alehouse keeper</roleName> with a true
                  tap-room feeling considers as
                     worst of all, I am quite indignant at
               the poor little boys being cheated of their holidays. Is it not abominable? A worse
               iniquity than <del rend="squiggle" unit="word" quantity="1"> </del> beating <persName ref="#Napoleon"
               >Napoleon</persName><!--note Battle of Waterloo-->. When they ought to be playing
               cricket or stealing birdsnests or doing mischief or doing nothing.
      <name type="event" ref="#Waterloo">The Battle of Waterloo </name> was 
               <del rend="squiggles"/><add place="above"> a <unclear>illegible</unclear> to this wickedness.</add> The only
               thing that even looks like the holidays is
               their mode of conveyance which is generally <unclear><supplied resp="#ad">five</supplied></unclear> in a gig
               rain or shine.
               <!--the cross-out line in another hand falls over "in a gig rain or shine."--></p>
            <p>Pray did you get a little letter which I sent to you at
                  <placeName>Glasgow</placeName><sic>.<!-- #ad It looks like an underscore to me, not a full stop? --></sic> It is not worth asking for.--My
                  <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">father</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Russell_M"
                  >mother</persName> join in kindest remembrances &amp; I am ever<lb/> My dear
                  <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. Haydon</persName><lb/>
               <lb/>Most sincerely and affectionately yours <lb/><persName ref="#MRM"/>MM Mitford
               <!--I tried to tag this as <signed> but program turned angry red, not sure how to handle that. Also, section would not accept <closer> apparently; it would signal any use of <closer> as disruptive to the <div>.-->
               Were you not very affected at the death of poor <persName ref="#Keats">John
                        <unclear><supplied>Keats?</supplied></unclear></persName> There is another
               proof of the terrible personality of the age. If he had lived I think his name would
               have been second only to <persName ref="#Wordsworth_Wm">Wordsworth's</persName><!-- #ad the possesive 's at the end of Wordsworth is an educated guess rather than what is actually readable on the document (the photo cuts the page off). -->
               amongst the Poets of the day--Indeed even now there are parts of
                  <title ref="#Endymion">Endymion</title> which surely no other man could have
               written.</p>
            <space/>
            <space/>
            <space/>
            <p/>
            <!--Address and postmarks written vertically-->
            <p>B.R. Haydon, Esqre <lb/> St. John's Place <lb/> Lisson Grove North <lb/> Regent's
               Park <lb/>
               <emph>London</emph><lb/></p>
            <!--end of vertical text-->
            <space/>
            <space/>
            <space/>
            <p><lb/>I am happy to tell you that after a great deal of enquiry &amp; some threats we
               have succeeded in regaining your greyhound puppy &amp; have
               placed him in very good summer quarters. He is the largest young dog I ever saw in my
               life &amp; gives promise of great strength--Once more farewell.</p>

         </div>
      </body>





      <back>
         <!--ebb:28 May 2014: Prosop Data Collected and Current -->
         <!-- #ad: 04 June 2014: Tagged the Battle of Waterloo but as this already has an xml:id I haven't signalled this change anywhere else -->
         <listEvent>
            <event type="battle" xml:id="Waterloo" when="1815-06-18">
               <label>Battle of Waterloo</label>
            </event>
            
         </listEvent>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
