<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter from Lord Montrose to George Colman, 20 October 1825.</title><author> </author><editor>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName/></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 August 2013. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><notesStmt><note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note><note>You can have multiple notes here.</note></notesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository>British Library</repository><idno>Add MS 42873, folio page 412</idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Lord Montrose to George Colman <date when="1825-10-20">20 October, 1825</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p><material>Paper</material>One quarto-sized sheet sheet folded once vertically and twice horizontally. No address leaf or envelope.</p></support><condition>Letter complete on the front and back of the first vertical fold of the sheet only. (Second leaf is blank.)</condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Missing address leaf or envelope and seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote><!--None--></handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>The letter writer's spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where the spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice,” “sic,” and “reg” to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><placeName>Buchanan</placeName><date when="1825-10-20">20<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Octr<lb/>18<hi rend="underline">25</hi></date></dateline><salute>Sir</salute></opener><p>I return the Licenses signed. King Charles is certainly not proper for representation in my opinion, &amp; if the Legislature will place the responsibility in such men as myself, I disdain to avoid the responsibility--<pb/>Your letters to the Manager are very proper &amp; I remain Sir</p><closer>
               yours &amp;c
               <signed>Montrose</signed><address><addrLine>George Colman Esq</addrLine><addrLine>&amp;c &amp;c &amp;c</addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div type="context"/></back></text></TEI>