<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    
    <fileDesc><titleStmt>
<title xml:id="MRM2021">Letter to <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary Webb</persName>, <date when="1819-05-16">May 16, 1819</date></title>
        <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>
        <editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor>
        <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor>
        <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
        <respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName> <persName ref="#slc">Sara Cantwell</persName>
        </respStmt><respStmt><resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp><persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName><!-- LMW: Coding completed and backlist pulled to central list, ai-add-LMW-new 2016-09-19-->
        </respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2015-09-25">25 September 2015</date>. P5.</edition>
            <respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt><respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp>photo files: <idno>DSCF8936.jpg, DSCF8939.jpg, DSCF8940.jpg, DSCF8941.jpg, DSCF8942.jpg, DSCF8943.jpg, DSCF8944.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt>
        </editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2013</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p>
            <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                        License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository><collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection>
                                <idno><!--LMW: spreadsheet lists no shelfmark/idno for this RCL letter.--></idno>
</msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Mary Webb, <date when="1819-05-16">1819 May 16<!-- LMW:  Date authority: Needham note attached to letter and verified with Mitford 1819 journal events. Mitford dined in Wokingham on this date, a Sunday, and mentions having seen Mr. Palmer and Miss Anstruther the previous day.--></date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc>
<support><p>One sheet of <material>paper</material>, four surfaces photographed. Folded in half and then again in thirds; the fourth leaf is blank.</p>
    
<p>Address leaf blank, bearing no addressee, address, or postmark.</p></support><condition><p>All leaves show considerable foxing and discoloration.</p></condition></supportDesc>
</objectDesc><sealDesc><p>No wax seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="letter"> <!--LMW: No address, date, or salutation given at the top of this letter. At the end is written "Wokingham  Sunday." "From the context, letter may have been posted enclosed in one of Aunt Mary's.-->
                <p>I have stolen half of dear <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_elder">Aunt Mary</persName>'s paper my own dear <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_younger">Mary</persName> to tell you what I presume you already know that I am not on my road to <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> though <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> very graciously very kindly permitted me to go &amp; my dear <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> wished to have me--but in the first place <foreign xml:lang="fr">le jeu le ne vaut pas la chandelle</foreign><note resp="slc">French, loosely translates as "the game isn't worth the candle."</note> to go to <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> for four days is condemning oneself to four days with too much to do in every one of them--in the second we are expecting a friend out of <placeName ref="#Hampshire_county">Hampshire</placeName>, &amp; <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir. W. Elford</persName> is coming on <date when="1819-05-21">Friday</date>. So at home I am (here) &amp; at home (there) I shall remain<note resp="#lmw">"Here" refers to <placeName ref="#Wokingham_city">Wokingham</placeName>; she is writing this letter from <orgName ref="#Webbs">the Webb's</orgName> house. "There" refers to <placeName ref="#Bertram_house">Bertram House</placeName>.</note>--I came over today to console myself &amp; was indeed consoled by seeing your dear <persName ref="#Webb_James">Father</persName> looking much better than I expected &amp; in very good spirits--<persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. Palmer</persName>'s beautiful phiz <choice><sic>to</sic><reg>too</reg></choice> was here--by the way there is a <title>print of the <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> procession</title>--executed by an <rs type="person">Artist</rs><note resp="#lmw">Editors have been unable, at yet, to locate this print or identify the artist. More research needed.</note> who must be very clever since he has performed <pb n="1"/>what I should have considered as an impossibility on the first blush of the business--made <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. Palmer</persName> 50 times uglier than he is--&amp; moreover given to <persName>Miss Anstruther</persName> &amp; the <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Right <choice><sic>Honble</sic><reg>Honorable</reg></choice> Lady</persName> the air of having the rouge washed off their faces by the rain--so that they look like weather-beaten dolls. I saw this fine picture in <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> yesterday which I entered for the first time after my long quarantine--You need not send me a word about the fashions, my dear, <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> has been a complete <title ref="#Ladys_Mag">Lady's Magazine</title> &amp; <title ref="#La_Belle_Assemblee">La Belle Assemblée</title>--you would have died laughing if you had heard him describe the way of trimming a lady's bonnet--at his total want of words &amp; the bon <choice><sic>hommie</sic><reg>homie</reg></choice> with which he adopted any ridiculous one's which I put into his mouth--closing every remark with an <q>“I assure you <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName>'s bonnet was just so”</q>--now <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Miss Eliza</persName> you must take this for a full answer to the letter which you have not written yet--And not have the assurance to expect me who am forced to spin all my cobwebs out<pb n="2"/> of my own brain--to <metamark rend="caret" place="below" function="insertion"/><add place="above">write again to</add> you who live in the land of sights &amp; <choice><sic>shews</sic><reg>shows</reg></choice>--</p>
                <p>I am very glad that you are going to <placeName ref="#Richmond">Richmond</placeName>--I wish with all my heart I were going there too--but I do not suppose I shall be able to get there for a month or two. If you happen to see my dear <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName>, tell her that <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> behaved with perfect good faith in the invitation <persName>Mrs. Clarke</persName> was so kind as to send &amp; very much wished me to put off our intended visitor and go--</p>
                <p>--Dearest of the dear--it is post time--I have been talking to <persName ref="#Webb_Mary_elder">Aunt Mary</persName> &amp; hindering myself and her from writing--you know what <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> says of my <choice><sic>gossipping</sic><reg>gossiping</reg></choice>--</p>
                    <p>Good bye--God bless you--How many lovers have you got? How many has <persName ref="#Webb_Eliza">Eliza</persName>? Ever <choice><sic>your's</sic><reg>yours</reg></choice></p><closer><lb/><signed><persName ref="#MRM">M. R. Mitford</persName></signed>
                        <lb/><address><addrLine><placeName ref="#Wokingham_city">Wokingham</placeName> <date when="1819-05-16">Sunday</date></addrLine></address></closer>
            </div>
        </body>
        
        <back>
        </back></text></TEI>
