<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng"
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng" 
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:id="MRM1766">Letter to <persName ref="#Haydon">B. R. Haydon</persName>, <date when="1820-09-14">September 14, 1820</date></title>
            <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>
            <editor ref="#msm">M. Stephanie Murray</editor>
            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <sponsor>Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#msm">M. Stephanie Murray</persName>
               <persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
               <persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName> 
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2013-06-04">4 June 2013</date>. P5.</edition>
               <respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt>
               <respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>14Sept1820BRHaydon1.jpg, 14Sept1820BRHaydon2.jpg, 14Sept1820BRHaydon3.jpg, 14Sept1820BRHaydon4.jpg</idno></resp></respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title> Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive </title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository>
                  <collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection>
                  <idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 Horizon No.: 1361550 ff. 415</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Benjamin Robert Haydon, <date when="1820-09-14">1820 September 14</date>.</head>
               
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support><p> One sheet of <material>paper</material>, two surfaces photographed.</p> 
                           <p>No address leaf.</p>
                        </support>
                        <condition>
                        </condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <sealDesc>
                     <p>No seal.</p> 
                  </sealDesc> 
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes><handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. A red line is drawn from top left to bottom right on leaves two, three, and four. On leaf four, a red line is drawn from top left to bottom right across each of the two text blocks. Lines of text are crossed out on leaves three and four. On leaf three, "All in a letter to Sir William Elford" is written perpendicularly to the Mitford text. There is no red crayon on leaf one.</handNote>
            
            <handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "7" in the top left of the first leaf.</handNote>
            
            <handNote xml:id="penAnnot_RCL">Someone, apparently other than <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName>, who occasionally left notes in a spidery thin hand to explain or document details in Mitford's letters in the margins of her pages, noted in the manuscripts held at <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>. This annotator may be <persName ref="#Harness_Wm">William Harness</persName> or <persName ref="#Lestrange">A. G. L'Estrange</persName>. The annotator has written <persName ref="#Haydon">B. R. Haydon <choice><sic>Eq</sic><reg>Esq.</reg></choice></persName><lb/><emph rend="underline">fragment</emph> at the top of leaf one. <!--LMW: do we want to assume that these notes at the top are also penAnnot_RCL? Are we putting this here in the headnote, or below in the body?-->
            </handNote>
         </handNotes>
      </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
         <p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2019-07-15" who="#ebb">Added note to end about fragmentary state of this letter.</change>
         <change when="2016-09-19" who="#lmw">Updated header and added back list.</change>
         <change when="2016-09-16" who="#lmw">Proofed against ms.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <placeName ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</placeName>
                  <date when="1820-09-14">Sept. 14<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1820.</date>
              </dateline>
               <salute>My dear <rs type="person" ref="#Haydon">Sir</rs></salute>
            </opener>
            <p>My <rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</rs> has begun a <choice><sic>negociation</sic><reg resp="#lmw">negotiation</reg></choice> respecting the greyhounds the issue of which I shall know before I finish this letter &amp; will then tell you the particulars--I am so sorry that they should inconvenience you--So sorry that we should not ourselves have room for them--So sorry that just now when you have so well earned every sort of pleasure, one so simple &amp; so pure should be taken from you. These regrets are very useless--but one cannot help feeling them.--<!--LMW: Long dash; does this function like jerks; ie, is there paragraph break here functionally?--></p><p>Do not commit such a mistake as to fancy your hand writing illegible--I can read it as well as print--The Characters are peculiar but the moment one knows them by heart one reads them as easily as a scholar reads Greek. Oh my dear <persName ref="#Haydon">Mr. Haydon</persName> if only you were but to see some of the young-lady Correspondences which <pb n="2"/>befall one sometimes--a full sheet of foolscap twice crossed in a hand all Ms &amp; Ns--a series of ups &amp; downs which defy guessing--I was forced to turn off a cousin of my own a delightful woman whose letters had but one fault that of being wholly unintelligible from beginning to end--nothing could be prettier looking than her hand only it was utterly unreadable. Never think of calling that writing of yours which <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del><choice><sic><add>shews</add></sic><reg>shows</reg></choice> so plainly the rapidity &amp; energy of your spirit, a scrawl--with what a delightful hieroglyphic you eked it out in your stage <persName ref="#Iago_O">Iago</persName>! I have seen <persName ref="#Kean_Edmund">Kean</persName> both in <persName ref="#Othello_O">Othello</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Iago_O">Iago</persName>, &amp; I felt like you his terrible power in the former. To see <persName ref="#Kean_Edmund">Kean</persName> in <persName ref="#Othello_O">Othello</persName> is a very painful pleasure. If I may say it without danger of being suspected of affectation I must confess that I do not much like acted plays. <persName ref="#Kean_Edmund">Kean</persName> is disappointing &amp; unequal--&amp; <persName ref="#Kemble_JP">Kemble</persName> was cold--&amp; one loses all the sweetness &amp; poetry of those delicious plays in these great theatres where nothing but the coarser strokes tell--In short it is altogether owing to my intense love &amp; admiration <del rend="squiggles">of</del> for <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> &amp; the old Dramatists that <pb n="3"/>I never desire to see a favorite play acted. Did you ever read two plays by <persName type="hist">Thomas May</persName> the Historian of the Long Parliament which I wonder <persName ref="#Hazlitt_Wm">Mr.Hazlitt</persName> did not mention --<title>The Heir</title> &amp; <title>The Old Couple</title>? They are as sweet &amp; beautiful as a May morning.--Do you read the Scotch Novels? Have you read <title ref="#Abbot_WS">the Abbot</title>? Do you like it? I was disappointed beccause every alternate work has been excellent, &amp; as <title ref="#Monastery">the Monastery</title> was bad I expected this to be very good--<del rend="hatch"><gap quantity="1" unit="letter"/><supplied resp="#lmw">&amp;</supplied></del> after all it is ungrateful to impute as a fault the failure of one's own too high expectations--It is very pleasant reading though not a work that would have made a reputation like <title ref="#Waverley">Waverley</title> or <title ref="#Old_Mortality">Old Mortality</title>. The real fault lies in the subject. <persName ref="#MaryQoS">Mary Queen of Scots</persName> is a person of whom in spite of her sins we have dreamt all our life long. There is not a man of any imagination who has not made her romance in his own mind long before now--<orgName ref="#OxfordBodleian">The Bodleian</orgName> <persName ref="#MaryQoS">Mary</persName> full of beauty &amp; grace--the love of men the envy of women--She who makes possible all that has been feigned of nymph of Goddess there<pb n="4"/> is no writing up to what one fancies of her.--<persName ref="#Schiller_F">Schiller</persName> has tried &amp; <persName ref="#Alfieri_Vittorio">Alfieri</persName> &amp; both have failed--but I think <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Sir Walter Scott's</persName> failure the most egregious of any--He takes the <persName ref="#Venus">Venus</persName> down from her pedestal &amp; makes her scold--he disenchants the <persName ref="#Dulcinea_DQ">Lady Dulcinea</persName>--he lets the glaring daylight into the magic lantern &amp; puts out the dreamy pictures--Now this is not a friends office--nor a Poets--This is another fault too--All the plot that is not of <persName ref="#MaryQoS">Queen Mary</persName> is filled by a twin brother &amp; sister confusion, like that of <persName ref="#Viola_TN">Viola</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Sebastian_TN">Sebastian</persName> in <title ref="#TwelfthNight_Shkspr">Twelfth Night</title>--&amp; let the <title ref="#EdinburghRev_per">Edinburgh Review</title>ers say what they will<persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName> at the side of <persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName> cuts no better a figure than <persName ref="#Reynolds_Josh">Reynolds</persName> by the side of <persName ref="#Vandyke">Vandyke</persName>. Nevertheless the book is pleasant and free from his peculiar faults as from his striking beauties--only one old hag--no fortune scene--no prophecy &amp; no ghost. How sorry I am to hear so bad an account of <persName ref="#Keats">Mr. Keats</persName>!--When I write to <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> I will mention your kind permission to send me his book. I am delighted that you were pleased with her letter--she is a sweet &amp;<note resp="ebb">The rest of this letter is missing.</note></p></div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div>
            <!--EBB:  L'Estrange includes some of p3 in a letter dated 9 September 1820 -->
      
                  
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
