<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, April 25, 1823.</title>
           <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>
           <editor ref="#err">Elizabeth Raisanen</editor>
           <sponsor>
              <orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName>
           </sponsor>
           <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
           <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
              <persName ref="#err">Elizabeth Raisanen</persName>
           </respStmt>
           <respStmt>
              <resp>Date last checked: <date when="2016-07-04"/>. Proofing and corrections by: Elisa Beshero-Bondar</resp>
              <!--2016-07-04 ebb: TRANSCRIPTION INCOMPLETE. I have updated the header so it doesn't erroneously point to another letter, and I documented the address leaf.-->
              <persName/>
           </respStmt>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
           <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 11 August 2014. P5.</edition>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
           <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
           <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
           <date>2014</date>
           <availability>
              <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>The Reading Central
                 Library</placeName>.</p>
              <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                 License</licence>
           </availability>
        </publicationStmt>
        <seriesStmt>
           <title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
        </seriesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
           <msDesc>
              <msIdentifier>
                 <repository ref="#ReadingCL">The Reading Central Library</repository>
                 <collection><!-- err: Need to find which collection these letters are from! -->
                 </collection>
                 <idno><!-- err: mansucript/collection numbers still needed. --></idno>
              </msIdentifier>
              <head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1823-04-25">April 25, 1823</date>.</head>
              <physDesc>
                 <objectDesc>
                    <supportDesc>
                       <support>
                          <p>One quarto sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form
                             two octavo pages, which comprise pages 1-4 of the letter. The fifth
                             page bears the end of the letter one side, and (after being folded
                             into four panels) exposes the address on the other side.</p>
                          <p>Address leaf lacking postmarks, bears the date "April twenty six 1823" in Mitford's hand, with "J. B. Monck Plymouth" at the bottom indicating that Monck franked this letter on Mitford's behalf.
                             </p>
                       </support>
                       <condition> </condition>
                    </supportDesc>
                 </objectDesc>
                 <sealDesc>
                    <p>The last sheet of the letter is torn suggesting a missing round seal.</p>
                 </sealDesc>
              </physDesc>
           </msDesc>
        </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
           <handNote xml:id="pencil" medium="pencil">Someone, apparently other than Mitford
              (perhaps cataloging the letters and describing them, or marking them up while
              creating an earlier edition of Mtiford's letters), left grey pencil marks and
              numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. The date
              "April 26th 1823" is written in this hand on the top left of the last leaf of the letter.</handNote>
           <handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon">Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a
              different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing
              diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing wo rds overtop and perpendicularly
              across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red diagonal line is drawn from the top
              left to the bottom right of pages 2, 3, and 4 of the manuscript.</handNote>
        </handNotes>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
           <p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
              end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
              spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
              searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
              Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
              following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
              ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
        </editorialDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline>April 23rd, 1823</dateline>
               <salute>My Dear Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I am but just returned from Town, whither I have been led by one of the evil consequences of dramatic Authorship--that is to say a false report--&amp; lose not a moment in writing to you to thank you for your zealous kindness, &amp;to say how heartily we sympathise in all your feelings. I have no time to tell you the story of the strange mistake which led me to <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>--no heart to talk to you of plays &amp; theatres--for my very soul is sick of them all--they mean to be kind I believe all of them--but between the lies &amp; the quarrels &amp; <pb n="2"/> and the envy that attends merely I have fairly <!-- xx --> a thousand times that the play had failed. Do we tell this--that really my soul <!-- xx --> within me when I think of the turmoil of tumult which i have undergone--I am to undergo--for <persName ref="#Kemble_C">Charles Kemble</persName> will not infer the <!-- xx --> to withdraw my tragedy of the <!-- xx -->, and threaten him with a lawsuit if I do. In the meantime, I am <!-- xx --> about between him I <!-- xx --> like a wicked bale, <!-- xx --> both <!-- xx -->, and <!-- xx --> by both <!-- xx  xx--> not come to a deadly <!-- xx --> with <!-- xx --> are imagine what a <!-- xx --> this is for one who valued and quietly beyond every other <!-- xx --> of life!--In the meantime they have put <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian</title>at the end of the eighth night though it was <pb n="3"/> going brilliantly to brilliant houses--&amp; (but this is quite between ourselves) not paid me for the third and sixth nights--To be sure I have <persName ref="#Kemble_C">Charles Kemble</persName>'s personal words--&amp; I believe him to be an honest man--but to undergo all this misery &amp; not get my money would be terrible indeed! To <!-- xx --> all the <!-- xx --> Hamilton from <!-- xx --> had affronted above forty <!-- xx --> in my debt--oh who would be an <!-- xx -->! The only confront is that the <!-- xx --> can't go on without me, and that the very job they make is <!-- xx --> over <!-- xx --> at the theatre moved my <!-- xx --> there--to that if I <!-- xx --> there <!-- xx  xx-->, I had in their <!-- xx --> something floor <!-- xx xx xx-->. <pb n="4"/> Children then wonder these <!-- xx --> does and interminable <!-- xx --> and this unwomanly publicity <!-- xx xx xx--></p>
            <p>Well I write <!-- xx --> of this <!-- xx --> I have nothing <!-- xx --> to death of <!-- xx --> for though I have been in town <!-- xx --> I have been to Englifrew Jabroubee by their distracting commons? That I have lost all conviction of anything <!-- xx --> better <!-- xx --> How have something to send you in a month or two for I have been sitting for my portrait to be engraved at the desire of my Mother. I hope <!-- xx --> that you are all as well <!-- xx --> as you can be <!-- xx --> for everything to yourself and your brother and his <!-- xx --> all who are to good to know your family the may convey <!-- xx most?--> of gratitude toward Kathy and the good wishes I hope for continuing a while continue better <!-- xx --> has been my dear friend <!-- xx --> Ever your faithfully yours, </p>
            <p><pb n="5"/>It is very strange that <!-- xx --> about to request you to <!-- xx --> your letter to the who is <!-- xx --> friend as to give the <!-- xx --> his <!-- xx --> is <!-- xx xx xx--> May forgive this lad no letter! Alas the free and happy <!-- xx --> when <!-- xx --> lead <!-- xx --> this. <!-- xx --> prattle for you are for away! Oh write they ever <!-- xx -->! I <!-- xx --> here chained to a desk, 10, 12 hours a day <!-- xx --> at <!-- xx --> of writing for <!-- xx --> money <!-- xx --> correspondence on how <!-- xx --> on pity the <!-- xx -->! Pity <!-- xx --> very kind is under the fatigue and the anxiety <!-- xx --> God help you my dear friend. <!-- xx --> Forgive this <!-- xx --></p>
            <closer>
               <lb/>Faithfully your's<lb/>
               <signed>MR. Mitford.</signed><lb/>
               <address><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Edford</persName></address>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
