<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication information</p>        
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p> <!--LMW: ff. 379 MRM1746-->
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <p>My own dear darling Mossy's hair cut off after he was dead by dear Drum. August 22nd 1819.--He was the greatest darling that ever lived--son of Maira &amp; Mr. Walter <!--Fullterton?--> (a famous dog given him by Lord Rivers) &amp; was when he died about seven or eight years old. He was a large black dog of the largest &amp; strongest kind of greyhounds--very fast &amp; honest &amp; resolute past example--an excellent killer of hares &amp; a most magnificent &amp; noble looking creature--his coat was of the finest &amp; most glossy black with no white except a very little under his feet (pretty white shoe linings I used to call them) a little beautiful white spot quite small in the very middle of his neck between his chin &amp; his breast &amp; a white mark on his dear bosom. His face was singularly beautiful the finest black eyes--very bright &amp; yet sweet &amp; fond &amp; tender--eyes that seemed to speak--a beautiful complacent mouth which used sometimes to show one of the long white teeth at the side--a jet black <!--scribble--> nose--a brow which was bent &amp; flexible like Mr. <!--??'s--> &amp; gave great sweetness &amp; expression &amp; a look of thought to his dear face--there never was such a dog. His temper was beyond all comparison the sweetest ever known--Nobody ever saw him out of humour--&amp; his sagacity equal even to his temper--he understood every thing that was said, &amp; would quite talk &amp; answer &amp; hold a conversation in his pretty way.--his love for me was the strangest thing of all. Never was such fondness--Never. He came to me every morning in bed &amp; staid with me all day--never left me--(except to go coursing) for a single moment.--Never left the room but he got up to go--wherever I sat he sat wherever I went he went with me--even to wash my hands or to walk across the room. If in bad weather I paced backwards &amp; forwards in the room he used to walk backwards &amp; forwards too--so he did in the garden &amp; shrubberies--flowering &amp; all--he never left me a moment to go faster or slower--&amp; always lay close at my side.--He was brother to May Fly &amp; they were brought up together at Chilton till a twelvemonth old when he came back--lived with us at Bertram House all the rest of his life. He was always my dog &amp; my pet I loved him better than any thing in the world &amp; I hope made him happy. About 4 months before his death he had a sad fall reaching up at some horse flesh against the lower stable since which time he has been exceedingly poorly &amp; languid--but on the day before his death he was remarkably well &amp; fond--walked &amp; played with me &amp; was more amiable than ever sweet darling--indeed he never was so ill as not to walk &amp; go every where with me &amp; never lost for a moment his sweet complacency--but this evening he was enchanting &amp; I petted him all down the lane to Major Stuart's &amp; back again. The next morning he fell again when let out in trying to jump over the yard gate--but recovered enough to eat an excellent breakfast &amp; I went off to Reading believing him pretty well.--at half past ten he was in the Kitchen--in good spirits--&amp; at eleven George found him dead in the yard as composed &amp; sweet looking dear Angel as if he was asleep. Thank God he went off without suffering he must have died in a moment. I thought I should have broke my heart when I came home &amp; found what had happened--I shall miss him every moment of my life--I have missed him every instant today so have Drum &amp; Granny. He was laid out last night in the Cowhouse &amp; this morning we buried him in the middle plantation, on the house side of the ditch in the flowery corner between the ditch &amp; Lord Shrewbury's fields--that flowery corner which is so richly covered with blue bells orchises &amp; pansies <!--*  -->where we mean to plant primroses &amp; cowslips--under a fir tree marked with his initial he lies--we covered his dear body with flowers, every flower in the garden--cloves, carnations, jasmine, honeysuckle, sweet William, <!--???--> by Virgins bower, roses &amp; some shrubbery flowers--as well as some fine geraniums which as well as the rose tree we mean to take away for his dear sake.--George &amp; Frank Alloway buried him--dear Saint--&amp; Granny Drum &amp; I <!--Marry?? sp? Mary?--> Mozes Whim &amp; Shelly--Whim &amp; Molly in mourning--&amp; every body so sorry! No human being ever was so faithful so gentle so generous &amp; so fond. I shall never love any thing half so well. My dear beloved Mossy Heaven bless you.<pb n="2"/>
            Farewell my own best beloved! I forgot to say that he was born here at Bertram House &amp; that when a little puppy of a month old, he became so fond of me that he would leave his Mother Maria to climb into my lap. He always loved me better than all the world my own dear Mossy &amp; so did I him. God bless you my own pet.--It will always be pleasant to me to remember that I never teased him by petting other things &amp; that every thing I had he shared--he always eat half my breakfast &amp; the very day before he died I fed him all the morning with filberds (of which together with most kinds of <!--?? nuts?  --> he was very fond) &amp; gave him almost all my plum pudding at dinner--God bless him my Mossy--His delight at seeing me when I had been <!--insertion--> out was inexpressible--he knew the <!--?? sound?--> of the wheels &amp; used to gallop to meet me talking his own pretty talk--he met me <!--?? that?--> way at the white gate on the Thursday as he died on the Saturday.--Whilst I had him I was always sure of having one who would love me alike in riches or in poverty <!--?? He? --> always looked at me with looks of the fondest love--always faithful &amp; always kind. To think of him was a talisman against vexing thoughts. A thousand times I have said "I want my Mossy" when that Dear Mossy was close by I would put his dear black nose <!--?? in?--> my hand on leaving his house.--God bless you my Mossy I cried when you died &amp; I can hardly help crying whenever I think of you--all who loved me loved Mossy. God bless him my beloved <!--?? pet?--> my own dear Mossy God bless him!--Though one of his greatest distinctions <!--?? was?--> a sweet mildness &amp; complacency both of temper &amp; of look yet he was most courageous &amp; spirited &amp; lion-like if any improper person came about the place he always sent them away &amp; once drove off a man from the white gate whom he thought likely to attack me. Nobody would have ventured to insult me whilst I had him, dear dear darling.--He was very kind to all our other creatures--particularly <!--??--> of whom he was very fond--Selim the white cat, &amp; little Molly &amp; old <!--Whim?-->. All the servants loved poor dear Mossy especially <!--Sure.??--> Drum was very fond of him--so was Granny--fonder than of any other dog.--We have no child of his which is a great grief--Mr. <!--Body?--> has a black greyhound very like him whom we <!--?? think?--> to be his &amp; Farmer Dave's little cream coloured bitch which they say was got by him &amp; I believe was, but not at all like him. The brother of that little bitch was his very image with his own pretty white spots but that one died. He had Fly for a wife this Spring but she had no family. I would give the world for a puppy out of him--The nearest relation of his that we have now is a half nephew very like him out of a daughter of Maria's belonging to Mr. Slade. Mr. Webb has two of his half sisters &amp; Mr. Wilson had May Fly his own full sister--&amp; I hope has her still though when we heard last he had lost her. <!--insertion: every thing related to him is dear to me-->--My own beloved Mossy--I loved your Mother poor old Mia but not half so well as I loved you. You were everything to me my Mossy my own love! And I was every thing to you--You understood all I said &amp; loved to hear my voice--but you understood all that every body said--Mama came in one day &amp; said "George wants to give your dog his dinner" &amp; Mossy got up &amp; went to the door immediately though she had not mentioned his name &amp; thought he never for an instant willingly left me.--God bless him my own dear Mossy I miss him more &amp; more Dearest Saint--my dear beloved Mossy--He had the most perfect confidence in me--always came to me for protection against any one who theatened him &amp; thank God always found it--dear love--I <!--?? love?--> all things that he has lately or ever touched--even the old quilt we used to spread on <!--scribble: his--> my bed for him to lie on &amp; which we called Mossy's quilt &amp; the <!--pan?--> out of which he drank in the parlour which was called Mossy's pan &amp; <!--dear? ???--><pb n="3"/></p>
      <p>X This Paper, with Lock of the Dog's hair, was found in an sealed envelope with blank, <!--cross out: in an--></p>
         <p>I forgot to say that his breath was always as sweet &amp; balmy as that of a cow--his coat always glossy like Satin--&amp; he have never had any humour or disease or any thing to make him d <!--torn amn?--> -able in his life. Many other things I have omitted--&amp; so I should if I were to write a whole Volume of his praise--for he was above all praise sweet Angel.--The enclosed verses were the one written when he was very young--the other two days after his death--they are an imperfect but most sincere tribute to his matchless goodness beloved angel.--I have enclosed some of the hair cut off my Papa after his death--&amp; some cut off before when we were thinking of leaving this house &amp; I thought possible we might be parted--&amp; some of the hay on w <!--torn which?--> was laid our dear Angel.--He died Satursday the 21<!--torn:  st?--> August 1819 at Bertram House--Heaven bless him beloved Angel!-- M.R.M.</p>
            <p>Bertram House</p>
            <p>August 23rd 1819.</p>
         <p>His real name was Moss Trooper only we always called him Mossy as more affectionate--I find he could not have been more than six years old as the enclosed poem was written in 1814. He was born in the barn at Bertram House--dear Angel--God bless him in August--Hail &amp; Farewell</p>
         <figure>
            <graphic url="http://www.tei-c.org/logos/TEI-glow.png"/>
         </figure>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
