<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>--><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Title</title></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Information about the source</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener>To S. Hamilton Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi><!--ga:There is a mark after the title, presumably added by a different hand than Mitford's. It is an x shaped mark, located above and to the right of Hamilton's title. It refers the reader to the bottom of the page, where it adds "Editor of the Lady's Magazine"--><dateline><date when="1823-04-09">April 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1823.</date><name type="place">Three Mile Cross</name></dateline><salute>My dear Sir</salute></opener><p>I avail myself of the return of one friend <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName> to send you another article for the magazine<!--ga:There is a mark here, presumably added by a different hand than Mitford's. It is an x shaped mark, located above and to the right of Hamilton's title. It refers the reader to the bottom of the page, where it adds "Editor of the Lady's Magazine"-->--I have one <add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>half written </add>, which you shall have by the middle of next week at latest--Much sooner if I can find an opportunity--on <note resp="#ga">There is a small tear in the paper here, above the dash and partially obscuring the first letter of on. Not enough is missing to make the word illegible.</note>the subject of the <q><unclear><supplied resp="#ga">mergings</supplied></unclear></q> which the country people hold in the North of <placeName>Hampshire</placeName>--I mention this to you because perhaps on account of the subject you might like to keep room for it this month--It will be rather longer than the enclosed but not much. </p><p>I find that my father explained to you the mistake respecting <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title>--Be assured that it was not intentional--I won't at all know what will be the event of that play--but as you say <gap reason="torn" unit="word" quantity="1"/> is no hurry. I should at all events wish <gap reason="torn" unit="word" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied resp="#ga">to</supplied></unclear><note resp="#ga">Here a tear in the paper obliterates the rest of the line which due to the size of the tear and the context appears to be "to".</note> keep open <gap reason="torn" unit="letter" quantity="3"/><unclear><supplied resp="ga">communication</supplied></unclear> with <persName ref="#Elliston_Robt">Mr. Elliston</persName> if not for <gap reason="torn" unit="word" quantity="1"/><note resp="#ga"> Here a tear in the paper obliterates the rest of the line</note> for other tragedies--if ever I get courage enough to write more for really I have been so attached as a woman (I do not mind fair criticism--or any criticism on the work) the Author has been so mixed up with her production, that it is like going into a field of battle to produce a successful play. This must account for &amp; excuse to you the feeling of very unusual irritation under which you saw me--Do not judge of me by the temper I showed then--for really I am a very peaceful quiet person except when so terribly excited--&amp; at present the nervousness having subsided I feel nothing but thankfulness--a deep &amp; abiding thankfulness to all concerned in <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian</title>--&amp; am very far indeed from entering into any cabal against the Manager-As far as <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Macready</persName> would be from wishing to engaging me in one.--At present the <title>Foscari</title> will remain in the theater--perahps they may return it--but if not it does not seem right to <persName>Mr. Talfourd</persName> or to me to withdraw it at present.<pb n="2"/> The last No. of the magazine is very good indeed--I have shown it to several persons in this neighborhood as well as distributed the extra copies &amp; have great hopes that it will be taken in by several families--I mean of course our magazine.--Can you at all tell who wrote the article on Julian in the <title ref="#LondonMag">London</title>? I exceedingly wish to know--you know I suppose that my reason for writing Foscari out of <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre">Covent garden</placeName> is that <persname>Mr. Macready</persname>(to whom I am under no great obligations) may not be called upon to play the stage--<persname ref="#Kemble_C">Mr. Kemble</persname>I know wishes it performed &amp; if they had <persname ref="#Young_CM">Mr. Young</persname>next season I should not object--only I do not wish to be so ungrateful as to impose a part he dislikes on <persname>Mr. Macready</persname>--Of course this is between ourselves.--My father begs his compliments <gap reason="torn" unit="word" quantity="1"/> dear sir</p><closer><lb/>Very truly your's<lb/><signed>MR Mitford</signed><lb/><address><addrLine><persName>S. Hamilton Esq<hi rend="superscript">re</hi></persName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName>30 Judd Street</placeName></addrLine><addrLine><placeName>Brunswick Square</placeName></addrLine></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>