<?xml version=”1.0” encoding=”UTF-8”?>
<?xml-model href=”http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng” type=”application/xml” schematypens=”http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0”?>
<?xml-model href=”http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng” type=”application/xml”
	schematypens=”http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron”?>
<TEI xmlns=”http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0”>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <!--2017-01-10 ebb: Here is the source of our base text in Hathi Trust:
https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/ssd?id=mdp.39015008020441;seq=189;num=177
The nine missing sketches are Sections 16 to 23, the last nine sketches in OV.

Make a new file for each sketch. 
Follow the filenameing conventions that you see in Box. Each OV sketch begins with the letters OV, then the main title, and if a subtitle it goes in block caps at the end of the filename.xml
Please use the 1824 NCCO PDF (saved in OV folder in Box) to check and correct the text.

  -->

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
            <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>


            <editor>Samantha Webb</editor>
            <editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName>Jonathan M. Horanic</persName>
               <persName>Samantha Webb</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--2017-01-10 ebb: We need to change this sourceDesc to indicate we’re checking each text and altering it to represent the 1824 edition as published in NCCO. -->
            <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
            <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                  <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third
                     Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B.
                     Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
               </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first
               edition published in 1824. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type=”sketch”>
            <pb n=”177”/>
            <head>AN OLD BACHELOR.
               <!--ebb: If there’s a subtitle use an <lb/> element to separate -->
            </head>
            <p>There is no effect of the subtle operation of the asso- ciation of ideas more
               universal and more curious than the manner in which the most trivial circumstances
               re- call particular persons to our memory. Sometimes these glances of recollection
               are purely pleasurable. Thus I have a double liking for May-day, as being the
               birth-day of a dear friend whose fair ideabursts upon me with the first sunbeam of
               that glad morning; and I can never hear certain airs of Mozart and Handel without
               seeming to catch an echo of that sweetest voice in which I first learnt to love them.
               Pretty often, however, the point of association is less elegant, and occasionally it
               is tolerably ludicrous. We happened to-day to have for dinner a couple of wild ducks,
               the first of the season; and as the master of the house, who is so little of an epi-
               cure that I am sure he would never while he lived, out of its feathers, know a
               wild-duck from a tame,—whilst he, with a little affectation of science, was squeezing
               the lemon and mixing Cayenne pepper with the gravy, two<pb n=”178”/> of us exclaimed
               in a breath, “Poor Mr. Sidney!”— “Aye,” rejoined the squeezer of lemons, “poor Sid-
               ney! I think he would have allowed that these ducks were done even to half a turn.”
               And then he told the story more elaborately to a young visitor, to whom Mr. Sidney
               was unknown;—how, after eating the best parts of a couple of wild-ducks, which all
               the company pronounced to be the finest and the best dressed wild- ducks ever brought
               to table, that judicious critic in the gastronomic art limited the too sweeping
               praise by gravely asserting, that the birds were certainly excel- lent, and that the
               cookery would have been excellent also, had they not been roasted half a turn too
               much. Mr. Sidney has been dead these fifteen years; but no wild ducks have ever
               appeared on our homely board without recalling that observation. It is his memorable
               saying; his one good thing.</p>
            <p> Mr. Sidney was, as might be conjectured, an epi- cure; he was also an old bachelor,
               a clergyman, and senior fellow of * * College, a post which he had long filled,
               being, although only a second son, so well provided for that he could afford to
               reject living after living in expectation of one favourite rectory, to which he had
               taken an early fancy from the pleasantness of the situation and the imputed salubrity
               of the air. Of the latter quality, indeed, he used to give an instance, which,
               however satisfactory as confirming his pre-<pb n=”179”/> possession, could hardly
               have been quite agreeable, as preventing him from gratifying it;—namely, the extra-
               ordinary and provoking longevity of the incumbent, who at upwards of ninety gave no
               sign of decay, and bade fair to emulate the age of old Parr.</p>
            <p>Whilst waiting for the expected living, Mr. Sidney, who disliked a college residence,
               built himself a very pretty house in our neighbourhood, which he called his home; and
               where he lived, as much as a love of Bath and Brighton and London and lords would let
               him. He counted many noble families amongst his near con- nections, and passed a good
               deal of his time at their country seats—a life for which he was by character and
               habit peculiarly fitted.</p>
            <p>In person he was a tall stout gentlemanly man, “about fifty, or by’r lady inclining
               to threescore,” with fine features, a composed gravity of countenance and demeanour,
               a bald head most accurately powdered, and a very graceful bow—quite the pattern of an
               elderly man of fashion. His conversation was in excellent keeping with the calm
               imperturbability of his counte- nance and the sedate gravity of his manner,—smooth,
               dull, commonplace, exceedingly safe, and somewhat imposing. He spoke so little, that
               people really fell into the mistake of imagining that he thought; and the tone of
               decision with which he would advance some se- cond-hand opinion, was well calculated
               to confirm the<pb n=”180”/> mistake. Gravity was certainly his chief characteristic,
               and yet it was not a clerical gravity either. He had none of the generic marks of his
               profession. Although perfectly decorous in life and word and thought, no stranger
               ever took Mr. Sidney for a clergyman. He never did any duty any where, that ever I
               heard of, except the agreeable duty of saying grace before din- ner; and even that
               was often performed by some lay host, in pure forgetfulness of his guest’s
               ordination. Indeed, but for the direction of his letters, and an eye to * * *
               Rectory, I am persuaded that the circumstance might have slipped out of his own
               recollection.</p>
            <p>His quality of old bachelor was more perceptible. There lurked under all his polish,
               well covered but not concealed, the quiet selfishness, the little whims, the precise
               habits, the primness and priggishness of that disconsolate condition. His man
               Andrews, for instance, valet, groom, and body-servant abroad; butler, cook, caterer,
               and major d’omo at home; tall, portly, pow- dered and black-coated as his master, and
               like him in all things but the knowing pig-tail which stuck out ho- rizontally above
               his shirt-collar, giving a ludicrous dignity to his appearance;—Andrews, who,
               constant as the dial pointed nine, carried up his chocolate and shaving water, and
               regular as “the chimes at mid- night,” prepared his white-wine whey: who never for-
               got his gouty shoe in travelling, (once for two days he<pb n=”181”/> had a slight
               touch of that gentlemanly disorder,) and never gave him the newspaper unaired;—to
               whom could this jewel of a valet, this matchless piece of clock-work belong, but an
               old bachelor? And his little dog Viper, unparagoned of terriers, black, sleek, sharp,
               and shrewish; who would beg and sneeze and fetch and carry like a Christian; eat
               olives and sweetmeats and mustard, drink coffee and wine and liqueurs;—who but an old
               bachelor could have taught Viper his multi- farious accomplishments?</p>
            <p>Little Viper was a most useful person in his way; for although Mr. Sidney was a very
               creditable ac- quaintance to meet on the King’s highway, (your dull man, if he rides
               well, should never think of dismount- ing,) or even on the level ground of a carpet
               in the crowd of a large party; yet when he happened to drop in to take a family
               dinner—a pretty frequent habit of his when in the country—then Viper’s talents were
               in- estimable in relieving the ennui occasioned by that grave piece of gentility his
               master, “not only dull in himself, but the cause of dullness in others.” Any thing to
               pass away the heavy hours, till whist or piquet re- lieved the female world from his
               intolerable silence.</p>
            <p>In other respects these visits were sufficiently per- plexing. Every housewife can
               tell what a formidable guest is an epicure who comes to take pot-luck—how sure it is
               to be bad luck, especially when the unfortu-<pb n=”182”/> nate hostess lives five
               miles from a market town. Mr. Sidney always came unseasonably, on washing-day, or
               Saturday, or the day before a great party. So sure as we had a scrap dinner, so sure
               came he. My dear mo- ther, who with true benevolence and hospitality cared much for
               her guest’s comfort and nothing for her own pride, used to grieve over his
               discomfiture, and try all that could be done by potted meats and/omelettes, and
               little things tossed up on a sudden to amend the bill of fare. But cookery is an
               obstinate art, and will have its time;—however you may force the component parts,
               there is no forcing a dinner. Mr. Sidney had the evil habit of arriving just as the
               last bell rang; and in spite of all the hurry scurry in the kitchen department, the
               new niceties and the old, homely dishes were sure to disagree. There was a total want
               of keeping. The kickshaws were half raw, the solids were mere rags; the vegetables
               were cold, the soup was scalding; no shallots to the rump-steaks; no mushrooms with
               the broiled chicken; no fish; no oysters; no ice; no pine- apple. Poor Mr. Sidney! He
               must have had a great regard for us to put up with our bad dinners.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the chance of a rubber had something to do with his visits to our house. If
               there be such a thing as a ruling passion, the love of whist was his. Cards were not
               merely the amusement, but the business of his life. I do not mean as a money-making
                  speculation;<pb n=”183”/> for although he belonged to a fashionable club in
               London, and to every card-meeting of decent gentility within reach of his country
               home, he never went beyond a regular moderate stake, and could not be induced to bet
               even by the rashest defyer of calculation, or the most provoking undervaluer of his
               play. It always seemed to me that he regarded whist as far too im- portant and
               scientific a pursuit to be degraded into an affair of gambling. It had in his eyes
               all the dignity of a study; an acquirement equally gentlemanly and cle- rical. It was
               undoubtedly his test of ability. He had the value of a man of family and a man of the
               world, for rank, and wealth, and station, and dignities of all sorts. No human being
               entertained a higher respect for a king, a prince, a prime minister, a duke, a
               bishop, or a lord. But these were conventional feelings. His genuine and unfeigned
               veneration was reserved for him who played a good rubber, a praise he did not easily
               give. He was a capital player himself, and held all his country competitors, except
               one, in supreme and un- disguised contempt, which they endured to admiration. I
               wonder they did not send him to Coventry. He was the most disagreeable partner in the
               world, and nearly as unpleasant an adversary; for he not only enforced the
               Pythagorean law of science, which makes one hate whist so, but used to distribute
               quite impartially to every one at table little disagreeable observations on<pb
                  n=”184”/> every card they played. It was not scolding, or grum- bling, or
               fretting; one has a sympathy with those ex- pressions of feeling, and at the worst
               can scold again; it was a smooth polite commentary on the errors of the party,
               delivered in the calm tone of undoubted supe- riority with which a great critic will
               sometimes take a small poet, or a batch of poets, to task in a review. How the people
               could bear it!—but the world is a good-natured world, and does not like a man the
               less for treating it scornfully.</p>
            <p>So passed six evenings out of the seven with Mr. Sidney, for it was pretty well known
               that, on the rare occurrence of his spending a day at home without com- pany, his
               fac-totum Andrews used to have the honour of being beaten by his master in a snug
               game at double dumby; but what he did with himself on Sunday oc- casioned me some
               speculation. Never in my life did I see him take up a book, although he sometimes
               talked of Shakspeare and Milton, and Johnson and Burke, in a manner which proved that
               he had heard of such things; and as to the newspaper, which he did read, that was
               generally conned over long before night; be- sides he never exhibited spectacles, and
               I have a notion that he could not read newspaper type at night without them. How he
               could possibly get through the after- coffee hours on a Sunday puzzled me long.
               Chance solved the problem. He came to call on us after<pb n=”185”/> church, and
               agreed to dine and sleep at our house. The moment tea was over, without the slightest
               apology or attempt at conversation, he drew his chair to the fire, set his feet on
               the fender, and fell fast asleep in the most comfortable and orderly manner possible.
               It was evidently a weekly habit. Every sense and limb seemed composed to it. Viper
               looked up in his face, curled himself round on the hearth rug, and went to sleep too;
               and Andrews,just as the clock struck twelve, came in to wake him, that he might go to
               bed. It was clearly an invariable custom; a settled thing.</p>
            <p>His house and grounds were kept in the neatest man- ner possible. There was something
               even disagreeable in the excessive nicety, the Dutch preciseness of the shining
               gravel walks, the smooth shaven turf of the lawn, and the fine-sifted mould of the
               shrubberies. A few dead leaves or scattered flowers, even a weed or two, any thing to
               take away from the artificial toy-like look of the place, would have been an
               improvement. Mr. Sidney, however, did not think so. He actually caused his gardener
               to remove those littering plants called roses and gum cistuses. Other flowers fared
               little better. No sooner were they in bloom, than he pulled them up for fear they
               should drop. In doors, matters were still worse. The rooms and furniture were very
               handsome, abounding in the luxurious Tur- key carpets, the sofas, easy chairs, and
                  ottomans,<pb n=”186”/> which his habits required; and yet I never in my life saw
               any house which looked less comfortable. Every thing was so constantly in its place,
               so provokingly in order, so full of naked nicety, so thoroughly old-bache- lorish. No
               work! no books! no music! no flowers! But for those two things of life, Viper and a
               sparkling fire, one might have thought the place uninhabited. Once a year, indeed, it
               gave signs of animation, in the shape of a Christmas party. That was Mr. Sidney’s
               shining time. Nothing could exceed the smiling hos- pitality of the host, or the
               lavish profusion of the en- tertainment. It breathed the very spirit of a welcome
               splendidly liberal; and little Viper frisked and bounded, and Andrews’s tail vibrated
               (I was going to say wagged) with cordiality and pleasure. Andrews, on these oc-
               casions, laid aside his “customary black” in favour of a blue coat and a white silk
               court waistcoat, with a light running pattern of embroidery and silver span- gles,
               assumed to do honour to his master and the com- pany. How much he enjoyed the
               applause which the wines and the cookery elicited from the gentlemen; and how
               anxiously he would direct the ladies’ attention to a MS. collection of riddles, the
               compilation of some deceased countess, laid on the drawing-room table for their
               amusement between dinner and tea. Once, I re- member, he carried his attention so far
               as to produce a gone-by toy, called a bandalore, for the recreation of<pb n=”187”/>
               myself and another little girl, admitted by virtue of the Christmas holidays to this
               annual festival. Poor An- drews! I am convinced that he considered the enter-
               tainment of the visitors quite as much his affair as his master’s; and certainly they
               both succeeded. Never did parties pass more pleasantly. On those evenings Mr. Sidney
               even forgot to find fault at whist.</p>
            <p>At last, towards the end of a severe winter, during which he had suffered much from
               repeated colds, the rectory of * * * became vacant, and our worthy neigh- bour
               hastened to take possession. The day before his journey he called on us in the
               highest spirits, antici- pating a renewal of health and youth in this favourite spot,
               and approaching nearer than I had ever heard him to a jest on the subject of looking
               out for a wife. Married or single, he made us promise to visit him during the ensuing
               summer. Alas! long before the summer arrived, our poor friend was dead. He had waited
               for this living thirty years; he did not enjoy it thirty days.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
