<?xml version=”1.0” encoding=”UTF-8”?>
<?xml-model href=”http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng” type=”application/xml” schematypens=”http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0”?>
<?xml-model href=”http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng” type=”application/xml”
	schematypens=”http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron”?>
<TEI xmlns=”http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0”>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <!--2017-01-10 ebb: Here is the source of our base text in Hathi Trust:
https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/ssd?id=mdp.39015008020441;seq=189;num=177
The nine missing sketches are Sections 16 to 23, the last nine sketches in OV.

Make a new file for each sketch. 
Follow the filenameing conventions that you see in Box. Each OV sketch begins with the letters OV, then the main title, and if a subtitle it goes in block caps at the end of the filename.xml
Please use the 1824 NCCO PDF (saved in OV folder in Box) to check and correct the text.

  -->

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
            <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>


            <editor>Samantha Webb</editor>
            <editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName>Jonathan M. Horanic</persName>
               <persName>Samantha Webb</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--2017-01-10 ebb: We need to change this sourceDesc to indicate we’re checking each text and altering it to represent the 1824 edition as published in NCCO. -->
            <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
            <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                  <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third
                     Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B.
                     Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
               </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first
               edition published in 1824. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type=”sketch”>
            <pb n=”273”/>
            <head>A PARTING GLANCE AT OUR
               VILLAGE.<!--ebb: If there’s a subtitle use an <lb/> element to separate -->
            </head>
            <p>It is now eighteen months since our village first sat for its picture, and I cannot
               say farewell to my courteous readers, without giving them some little intelligence of
               our goings on, a sort of parting glance at us and our condition. In outward
               appearance it hath, I suppose, undergone less alteration than any place of its inches
               in the kingdom. There it stands, the same long straggling street of pretty cottages,
               divided by pretty gardens, wholly unchanged in size or appearance, un- increased and
               undiminished by a single brick. To be sure, yesterday evening a slight misfortune
               happened to our goodly tenement, occasioned by the unlucky dili- gence mentioned in
               my first notice, which, under the conduct of a sleepy coachman, and a restive horse,
               con- trived to knock down and demolish the wall of our court, and fairly to drive
               through the front garden, thereby destroying sundry curious stocks, carnations, and
               geraniums. It is a mercy that the unruly steed<pb n=”274”/> was content with
               battering the wall; for the messuage itself would come about our ears at the touch of
               a finger, and really there is one little end-parlour, an after-thought of the
               original builder, which stands so temptingly in the way, that I wonder the sagacious
               quadruped missed it. There was quite din enough without that addition. The three
               insides (ladies) squalling from the interior of that commodious vehi- cle; the
               outsides (gentlemen) swearing on the roof; the coachman, still half asleep, but
               unconsciously blow- ing his horn; we in the house screaming and scolding; the
               passers-by shouting and hallooing; and May, who little brooked such an invasion of
               her territories, barking in her tremendous lion-note, and putting down the other
               noises like a clap of thunder. But passen- gers, coachman, horses, and spectators,
               all righted at last; and there is no harm done but to my flowers and to the wall.
               May, however, stands bewailing the ruins, for that low wall was her favourite haunt;
               she used to parade backwards and forwards on the top of it, as if to show herself,
               just after the manner of a peacock on the top of a house; and would sit or lie for
               hours on the corner next the gate, basking in the sunshine like a marble statue.
               Really she has quite the air of one who laments the destruction of personal property;
               but the wall is to be rebuilt to-morrow, with old weather-stained bricks—no
               patch-work! and<pb n=”275”/> exactly in the same form; May herself will not find the
               difference; so that in the way of alteration this little misfortune will pass for
               nothing. Neither have we any improvements worth calling such. Except that the
               wheeler’s green door hath been retouched, out of the same pot (as I judge from the
               tint) with which he furbished up our new-old pony-chaise; that the shop-window of our
               neighbour, the universal dealer, hath been beautified, and his name and calling
               splendidly set forth in yellow letters on a black ground; and that our landlord of
               the Rose hath hoisted a new sign of unparalleled splendour; one side consisting of a
               full-faced damask rose, of the size and hue of a piony, the other of a maiden blush
               in profile, which looks exactly like a carnation, so that both flowers are
               considerably indebted to the modesty of the “out-of-door artist,” who has warily
               written The Rose under each;—except these trifling ornaments, which nothing but the
               jealous eye of a lover could de- tect, the dear place is altogether unchanged.</p>
            <p>The only real improvement with which we have been visited for our sins—(I hate all
               innovation, whe- ther for better or worse, as if I was a furious Tory, or a woman of
               three-score and ten)—the only mis- fortune of that sort which has befallen us, is
               under foot. The road has been adjusted on the plan of Mr. Mac-Adam; and a tremendous
               operation it is. I do<pb n=”276”/> not know what good may ensue; but for the last six
               months, some part or other of the highway has been impassable for any feet, except
               such as are shod by the blacksmith; and even the four-footed people who wear iron
               shoes, make wry faces, poor things! at those stones, enemies to man and beast.
               However, the busi- ness is nearly done now; we are covered with sharp flints every
               inch of us, except a “bad step” up the hill, which, indeed, looks like a bit cut out
               of the deserts of Arabia, fitter for camels and caravans than for Christian horses
               and coaches; a point which in spite of my dislike of alteration I was forced to
               acknowledge to our surveyor, a portly gentleman, who, in a smart gig drawn by a
               prancing steed, was kicking up a pro- digious dust at that very moment. He and I
               ought to be great enemies; for, besides the Mac-Adamite enormity of the stony road,
               he hath actually been guilty of tree-murder, having been an accessory before the fact
               in the death of three limes along the rope-walk—dear sweet innocent limes, that did
               no harm on earth except shading the path! I never should have for- given that
               offence, had not their removal, by opening a beautiful view from the village up the
               hill, reconciled even my tree-loving eye to their abstraction. And, to say the truth,
               though we have had twenty little squabbles there is no bearing malice with our
               surveyor; he is so civil and good-humoured, has such a bustling and happy<pb n=”277”
               /> self-importance, such an honest earnestness in his vo- cation (which is gratuitous
               by the bye), and such an intense conviction that the state of the turnpike road
               between B. and K., is the principal affair of this life, that I would not undeceive
               him for the world. How often have I seen him on a cold winter morn- ing, with a face
               all frost and business, great-coated up to the eyes, driving from post to post, from
               one gang of labourers to another, praising, scolding, ordering, cheated, laughed at,
               and liked by them all! Well, when once the hill is finished, we shall have done with
               him for ever, as he used to tell me by way of conso- lation, when I shook my head at
               him, as he went jolt- ing along over his dear new roads, at the imminent risk of his
               springs and his bones; we shall see no more of him; for the Mac-Adam ways are
               warranted not to wear out. So be it; I never wish to see a road- mender again.</p>
            <p>But if the form of outward things be all unchanged around us, if the dwellings of man
               remain the same to the sight and the touch, the little world within hath undergone
               its usual mutations;—the hive is the same, but of the bees some are dead and some are
               flown away, and some that we left insects in the shell, are already putting forth
               their young wings. Children in our village really sprout up like mushrooms; the air
               is so promotive of growth, that the rogues spring<pb n=”278”/> into men and women, as
               if touched by Harlequin’s wand, and are quite offended if one happens to say or do
               any thing which has a reference to their pre- vious condition. My father grievously
               affronted Sally L., only yesterday, by bestowing upon her a great lump of
               gingerbread, with which he had stuffed his pockets at a fair. She immediately, as she
               said, gave it to the “children.” Now Sally cannot be above twelve to my certain
               knowledge, though taller than I am. Lizzy herself is growing womanly. I actually
               caught that little lady stuck on a chest of drawers, contemplating herself in the
               glass, and striv- ing with all her might to gather the rich curls that hang about her
               neck, and turn them under a comb. Well! If Sally and Lizzy live to be old maids, they
               may probably make the amende honorable to time, and wish to be thought young again.
               In the meanwhile, shall we walk up the street?</p>
            <p>The first cottage is that of Mr. H. the patriot, the illuminator, the independent and
               sturdy yet friendly member of our little state, who, stout and comely, with a
               handsome chaise-cart, a strong mare, and a neat garden, might have passed for a
               portrait of that en- viable class of Englishmen, who, after a youth of frugal
               industry, sit down in some retired place to “live upon their means.” He and his wife
               seemed the happiest couple on earth; except a little too mnch<pb n=”279”/> leisure, I
               never suspected that they had one trouble or one care. But Care, the witch, will come
               everywhere, even to that happiest station, and this prettiest place. She came in one
               of her most terrific forms—blindness—or (which is perhaps still more tremendous) the
               faint glimmering light and gradual darkness which precede the total eclipse. For a
               long time we had missed the pleasant bustling officiousness, the little services, the
               voluntary tasks, which our good neigh- bour loved so well. Fruit trees were blighted,
               and escaped his grand specific, fumigation; wasps multi- plied, and their nests
               remained untraced; theicheerful modest knock with which, just at the very hour when
               he knew it could be spared, he presented himself to ask for the newspaper, was heard
               no more; he no longer hung over his gate to way-lay passengers, and entice them into
               chat; at last he even left off driving his little chaise, and was only seen moping up
               and down the garden-walk, or stealing gropingly from the wood-pile to the house. He
               evidently shunned con- versation or questions, forbade his wife to tell what ailed
               him, and even when he put a green shade over his darkened eyes, fled from human
               sympathy with a stern pride that seemed almost ashamed of the hum- bling infirmity.
               That strange (but to a vigorous and healthy man perhaps natural) feeling soon
               softened. The disease increased hourly, and he became depen-<pb n=”280”/> dent on his
               excellent wife for every comfort and re- lief. She had many willing assistants in her
               labour of love; all his neighbours strove to return, according to their several
               means, the kindness which all had received from him in some shape or other. The
               country boys, to whose service he had devoted so much time, in shaping bats,
               constructing bows and arrows, and other quips and trickeries of the same nature, vied
               with each other in performing little offices about the yard and stable; and John
               Evans, the half-witted gardener, to whom he had been a constant friend, repaid his
               goodness by the most unwearied attention. Gratitude even seemed to sharpen poor
               John’s perception and faculties. There is an old man in our parish work-house, who
               occasionally walks through the street, led by a little boy holding the end of a long
               stick. The idea of this man, who had lived in utter blindness for thirty years, was
               always sin- gularly distressing to Mr. H. I shall never forget the address with which
               our simple gardener usedto try to divert his attention from this miserable fellow-
               sufferer. He would get between them to prevent the possibility of recognition by the
               dim and uncertain vision; would talk loudly to drown the peculiar noise, the sort of
               duet of feet, caused by the quick short steps of the child, and the slow irregular
               tread of the old man; and, if any one ventured to allude to<pb n=”281”/> blind
               Robert, he would turn the conversation with an adroitness and acuteness which might
               put to shame the proudest intellect. So passed many months. At last Mr. H. was
               persuaded to consult a celebrated oculist, and the result was most comforting. The
               disease was ascertained to be a cataract; and now with the increase of darkness came
               an increase of hope. The film spread, thickened, ripened, speedily and healthily; and
               to-day the requisite operation has been performed with equal skill and success. You
               may still see some of the country boys lingering round the gate with looks of strong
               and wondering interest; poor John is going to and fro, he knows not for what, unable
               to rest a mo- ment; Mrs. H., too, is walking in the garden, shedding tears of
               thankfulness; and he who came to support their spirit, the stout strong-hearted
               farmer A., seems trembling and overcome. The most tranquil person in the house is
               probably the patient: he bore the opera- tion with resolute firmness, and he has seen
               again. Think of the bliss bound up in those four words! He is in darkness now, and
               must remain so for some weeks; but he has seen, and he will see; and that humble
               cottage is again a happy dwelling.</p>
            <p>Next we come to the shoemaker’s abode. All is unchanged there, except that its master
               becomes more industrious and more pale-faced, and that his fair daughter is a notable
               exemplification of the develope-<pb n=”282”/> ment which I have already noticed
               amongst our young things. But she is in the real transition state, just emerging from
               the chrysalis, and the eighteen months, between fourteen and a half and sixteen,
               would meta- morphose a child into a woman all the world over. She is still pretty,
               but not so elegant as when she wore frocks and pin-a-fores, and, unconsciously
               classi- cal, parted her long brown locks in the middle of her forehead, and twisted
               them up in a knot behind, giv- ing to her finely-shaped head and throat the air of a
               Grecian statue. Then she was stirring all day in her small housewifery, or her busy
               idleness, delving and digging in her flower-border, tossing and dandling every infant
               that came within her reach, feeding pigs and poultry, playing with May, and prattling
               with an open-hearted frankness to the country lads, who as- semble at evening in the
               shop to enjoy a little gentle gossiping; for be it known to my London readers, that
               the shoemaker’s in a country village is now what (according to tradition, and the old
               novels) the bar- ber’s used to be, the resort of all the male newsmon- gers,
               especially the young. Then she talked to these visitors gaily and openly, sang and
               laughed and ran in and out, and took no more thought of a young man than of a
               gosling. Then she was only fourteen. Now she wears gowns and aprons,—puts her hair in
               paper, —has left off singing, talks,—has left off running,<pb n=”283”/> walks,—nurses
               the infants with a grave solemn grace,—has entirely cut her former playmate
               Mayflower, who tosses her pretty head as much as to say—who cares?—and has nearly
               renounced all acquaintance with the visitors of the shop, who are by no means
               disposed to take matters so quietly. There she stands on the threshold, shy and
               demure, just vouchsafing a formal nod or a faint smile as they pass, and, if she in
               her turn be compelled to pass the open door of their news-room (for the working
               apartment is separate from the house), edging along as slyly and mincingly as if
               there were no such beings as young men in the world. Exquisite coquette! I think (she
               is my opposite neighbour, and I have a right to watch her doings,—the right of
               retaliation), there is one youth particularly distinguished by her non-notice, one
               whom she never will see or speak to, who stands a very fair chance to carry her off.
               He is called Jem Tanner, and is a fine lad, with an open ruddy countenance, a clear
               blue eye, and curling hair of that tint which the poets are pleased to denominate
               golden. Though not one of our eleven, he was a promising cricketer. We have missed
               him lately on the green at the Sunday- evening game, and I find on enquiry that he
               now fre- quents a chapel about a mile off, where he is the best male singer, as our
               nymph of the shoe-shop is incom- parably the first female. I am not fond of
                  betting;<pb n=”284”/> but I would venture the lowest stake of gentility, a silver
               threepence, that, before the winter ends, a wed- ding will be the result of these
               weekly meetings at the chapel. In the long dark evenings, when the father has enough
               to do in piloting the mother with conjugal gallantry through the dirty lanes, think
               of the oppor- tunity that Jem will have to escort the daughter. A little difficulty
               he may have to encounter: the lass will be coy for a while; the mother will talk of
               their youth, the father of their finances; but the marriage, I doubt not, will
               ensue.</p>
            <p>Next in order, on the other side of the street, is the blacksmith’s house. Change has
               been busy here in a different and more awful form. Our sometime con- stable, the
               tipsiest of parish officers, of blacksmiths and of men, is dead. Returning from a
               revel with a com- panion as full of beer as himself, one or the other, or both,
               contrived to overset the cart in a ditch; (the living scapegrace is pleased to lay
               the blame of the mishap on the horse, but that is contrary to all proba- bility, this
               respectable quadruped being a water- drinker ;) and inward bruises, acting on
               inflamed blood and an impaired constitution, carried him off in a very short time,
               leaving an ailing wife and eight children, the eldest of whom is only fourteen years
               of age. This sounds like a very tragical story: yet, perhaps, be- cause the loss of a
               drunken husband is not quite so<pb n=”285”/> great a calamity as the loss of a sober
               one, the effect of this event is not altogether so melancholy as might be expected.
               The widow, when she was a wife, had a complaining broken-spirited air, a peevish
               manner, a whining voice, a dismal countenance, and a person so neglected and
               slovenly, that it was difficult to believe that she had once been remarkably
               handsome. She is now quite another woman. The very first Sunday she put on her weeds,
               we all observed how tidy and com- fortable she looked, how much her countenance, in
               spite of a decent show of tears, was improved, and how completely through all her
               sighings her tone had lost its peevishness. I have never seen her out of spirits or
               out of humour since. She talks and laughs and bustles about, managing her journeymen
               and scolding her children as notably as any dame in the parish. The very house looks
               more cheerful; she has cut down the old willow trees that stood in the court, and let
               in the light; and now the sun glances brightly from the case- ment windows, and plays
               amidst the vine-leaves and the clusters of grapes which cover the walls; the door is
               newly painted, and shines like the face of its mistress; even the forge has lost half
               its dinginess. Every thing smiles. She indeed talks by fits of “poor George,”
               especially when any allusion to her old enemy, mine host of the Rose, brings the
               deceased to her me- mory; then she bewails (as is proper) her dear husband<pb n=”286”
               /> and her desolate condition; calls herself a lone widow; sighs over her eight
               children; complains of the trou- bles of business, and tries to persuade herself and
               others that she is as wretched as a good wife ought to be. But this will not do. She
               is a happier woman than she has been any time these fifteen years, and she knows it.
               My dear village-husbands, if you have a mind that your wives should be really sorry
               when you die, whether by a fall from a cart or otherwise, keep from the alehouse!</p>
            <p>Next comes the tall thin red house, that ought to boast genteeler inmates than its
               short fat mistress, its children, its pigs, and its quantity of noise, happiness, and
               vulgarity. The din is greater than ever. The hus- band, a merry jolly tar, with a
               voice that sounds as if is- suing from a speaking trumpet, is returned from a voyage
               to India; and another little one, a chubby roaring boy, has added his lusty cries to
               the family concert.</p>
            <p>This door, blockaded by huge bales of goods, and half darkened by that moving
               mountain, the tilted waggon of the S. mill which stands before it, belongs to the
               village shop. Increase has been here too in every shape. Within fourteen months two
               little pretty quiet girls have come into the world. Before Fanny could well manage to
               totter across the road to her good friend the nymph of the shoe-shop, Margaret made
               her appearance; and poor Fanny, discarded at once from<pb n=”287”/> the maid’s arms
               and her mother’s knee, degraded from the rank and privileges of”the baby,” (for at
               that age precedence is strangely reversed,) would have had a premature foretaste of
               the instability of human felicity, had she not taken refuge with that best of nurses,
               a fond father. Every thing thrives about the shop, from the rosy children to the neat
               maid and the smart ap- prentice. No room now for lodgers, and no need! The young
               mantua-making school-mistresses, the old inmates, are gone; one of them not very far.
               She grew tired of scolding little boys and girls about their A, B, C, and of being
               scolded in her turn by their sis- ters and mothers about pelisses and gowns; so she
               gave up both trades almost a year ago, and has been ever since our pretty Harriet. I
               do not think she has ever repented of the exchange, though it might not perhaps have
               been made so soon, had not her elder sister, who had been long engaged to an
               attendant at one of the col- leges of Oxford, thought herself on the point of mar-
               riage just as our housemaid left us. Poor Betsy! She had shared the fate of many a
               prouder maiden, wearing out her youth in expectation of the promotion that was to
               authorise her union with the man of her heart. Many a year had she waited in smiling
               constancy, fond of William in no common measure, and proud of him, as well she might
               be; for, when the vacation so far les- sened his duties as to render a short absence
                  practica-<pb n=”288”/> ble, and he stole up here for a few days to enjoy her
               company, it was difficult to distinguish him in air and manner, as he sauntered about
               in elegant indolence with his fishing-rod and his flute, from the young Oxonians his
               masters. At last promotion came; and Betsy, apprised of it by an affectionate and
               congratu- latory letter from his sister, prepared her wedding- clothes, and looked
               hourly for the bridegroom. No bridegroom came. A second letter announced, with regret
               and indignation, that William had made another choice, and was to be married early in
               the ensuing month. Poor Betsy! We were alarmed for her health, almost for her life.
               She wept incessantly, took no food, wandered recklessly about from morning till
               night, lost her natural rest, her flesh, her colour; and in less than a week she was
               so altered, that no one would have known her. Consolation and remonstrance were alike
               rejected, till at last Harriet happened to strike the right chord by telling her that
               “she wondered at her want of spirit.” This was touching her on the point of ho- nour;
               she had always been remarkably high-spirited, and could as little brook the
               imputation as a soldier or a gentleman. This lucky suggestion gave an imme- diate
               turn to her feelings; anger and scorn succeeded to grief; she wiped her eyes, “hemmed
               away a sigh,” and began to scold most manfully. She did still better. She recalled an
               old admirer, who in spite of repeated<pb n=”289”/> rejections had remained constant
               in his attachment, and made such good speed, that she was actually married the day
               before her faithless lover, and is now the happy wife of a very respectable
               tradesman.</p>
            <p>Ah! the in-and-out cottage! the dear, dear home! No weddings there! No changes!
               except that the white kitten, who sits purring at the window under the great myrtle,
               has succeeded to his lamented grand- father, our beautiful Persian cat, I cannot find
               one al- teration to talk about. The wall of the court indeed—but that will be mended
               to-morrow.</p>
            <p>Here is the new sign, the well-frequented Rose inn! Plenty of changes there! Our
               landlord is always im- proving, if it be only a pig-sty or a watering-trough— plenty
               of changes and one splendid wedding. Miss Phoebe is married, not to her old lover the
               recruiting sergeant (for he had one wife already, probably more,) but to a
               patten-maker, as errant a dandy as ever wore mustachios. How Phoebe could “abase her
               eyes” from the stately sergeant to this youth, half a foot shorter than herself,
               whose “waist would go into any alder- man’s thumb-ring,” might, if the final choice
               of a co- quette had ever been matter of wonder, have occasioned some speculation. But
               our patten-maker is a man of spirit; and the wedding was of extraordinary splen-
               dour. Three gigs, each containing four persons, graced the procession, beside
               numerous carts and innumerable<pb n=”290”/> pedestrians. The bride was equipped in
               muslin and satin, and really looked very pretty with her black sparkling eyes, her
               clear brown complexion, her blushes and her smiles; the bride-maidens were only less
               smart than the bride; and the bridegroom was “point device in his accoutrements,” and
               as munificent as a nabob. Cake flew about the village; plum-puddings were abundant;
               and strong beer, aye, even mine host’s best double X, was profusely distributed.
               There was all manner of eating and drinking, with singing, fiddling, and dancing
               between; and in the evening, to crown all, there was Mr. Moon the conjuror. Think of
               that stroke of good fortune !—Mr. Moon, the very pearl of all conjurors, who had the
               honour of puzzling and de- lighting their late Majesties with his “wonderful and
               pleasing exhibition of Thaumaturgics, Tachygraphy, mathematical operations, and
               magical deceptions,” hap- pened to arrive about an hour before dinner, and com-
               menced his ingenious deceptions very unintentionally at our house. Calling to apply
               for permission to perform in the village, being equipped in a gay scarlet coat, and
               having something smart and sportsman-like in his ap- pearance, he was announced by
               Harriet as one of the gentlemen of the C. Hunt, and taken (mistaken I should have
               said) by the whole family for a certain captain newly arrived in the neighbourhood.
               That misunder- standing, which must, I think, have retaliated on Mr.<pb n=”291”/>
               Moon a little of the puzzlement that he inflicts on others, vanished of course at the
               production of his bill of fare; and the requested permission was instantly given.
               Never could he have arrived in a happier hour! Never were spectators more gratified
               or more scared. All the tricks prospered. The cock crew after his head was cut off;
               and half-crowns and sovereigns flew about as if winged; the very wedding-ring could
               not escape Mr. Moon’s incantations. We heard of nothing else for a week. From the
               bridegroom, un esprit fort, who de- fied all manner of conjuration and diablerie,
               down to my Lizzy, whose boundless faith swallows the Arabian Tales, all believed and
               trembled. So thoroughly were men, women, and children, impressed with the idea of the
               worthy conjuror’s dealings with the devil, that when he had occasion to go to B., not
               a soul would give him a cast, from pure awe; and if it had not been for our
               pony-chaise, poor Mr. Moon must have walked. I hope he is really a prophet; for he
               foretold all hap- piness to the new-married pair.</p>
            <p>So this pretty white house with the lime-trees before it, which has been under repair
               for these three years, is on the point of being finished. The vicar has taken it, as
               the vicarage-house is not yet fit for his reception. He has sent before him a neat
               modest maid-servant, whose respectable appearance gives a character to her master and
               mistress,—a hamper full of flower-roots, sun-<pb n=”292”/> dry boxes of books, a
               piano-forte, and some simple and useful furniture. Well, we shall certainly have
               neighbours, and I have a presentiment that we shall find friends.</p>
            <p> Lizzy, you may now come along with me round the corner and up the lane, just to the
               end of the wheeler’s shop, and then we shall go home; it is high time. What is this
               affiche in the parlour window ?” Apart- ments to let—inquire within.” These are
               certainly the curate’s lodgings—is he going away? Oh I suppose the new vicar will do
               his own duty—yet, however well he may do it, rich and poor will regret the departure
               of Mr. B. Well, I hope that he may soon get a good living. “Lodgings to let”—who ever
               thought of see- ing such a placard hereabout? The lodgings, indeed, are very
               convenient for “a single gentleman, a man and his wife, or two sisters,” as the
               newspapers say—comfortable apartments, neat and tasty withal, and the civilest of all
               civil treatment from the host and hostess. But who would ever have dreamt of such a
               notice? Lodgings to let in our village!</p>
            <note place=”bottom”>THE END.<lb/>AUG 2, 1925<lb/>LONDON:<lb/>PRINTED BY R. GILBERT, ST. JOHN’S
               SQUARE.</note>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
