<?xml version=”1.0” encoding=”UTF-8”?>
<?xml-model href=”http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng” type=”application/xml” schematypens=”http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0”?>
<?xml-model href=”http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng” type=”application/xml”
	schematypens=”http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron”?>
<TEI xmlns=”http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0”>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <!--2017-01-10 ebb: Here is the source of our base text in Hathi Trust:
https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/ssd?id=mdp.39015008020441;seq=189;num=177
The nine missing sketches are Sections 16 to 23, the last nine sketches in OV.

Make a new file for each sketch. 
Follow the filenameing conventions that you see in Box. Each OV sketch begins with the letters OV, then the main title, and if a subtitle it goes in block caps at the end of the filename.xml
Please use the 1824 NCCO PDF (saved in OV folder in Box) to check and correct the text.

  -->

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
            <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>


            <editor>Samantha Webb</editor>
            <editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName>Jonathan M. Horanic</persName>
               <persName>Samantha Webb</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--2017-01-10 ebb: We need to change this sourceDesc to indicate we’re checking each text and altering it to represent the 1824 edition as published in NCCO. -->
            <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
            <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                  <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third
                     Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B.
                     Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
               </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first
               edition published in 1824. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type=”sketch”>
            <pb n=”250”/>
            <head>AUNT MARTHA. <!--ebb: If there’s a subtitle use an <lb/> element to separate -->
            </head>
            <p>One of the pleasantest habitations I have ever known is an old white house, built at
               right angles, with the pointed roofs and clustered chimneys of Elizabeth’s day,
               covered with roses, vines, and passion-flowers, and parted by a green sloping meadow
               from a strag- gling picturesque village street. In this charming abode resides a more
               charming family: a gentleman, 
               <quote>
                  “<l>Polite as all his life in courts</l>
                  <l>had been, And good as he the world had never seen;</l>“
               </quote> 
               two daughters full of sweetness and talent; and aunt Martha—the most delightful of old maids!                  She has another appellation, I suppose,—she must have one;— but I scarcely know it: Aunt
               Martha is the name that belongs to her—the name of affection. Such is the universal
               feeling which she inspires, that all her friends, all her acquaintances, (in this
               case the terms are almost synonymous,) speak of her like her own family:—she<pb
                  n=”251”/> is every body’s Aunt Martha—and a very charming Aunt Martha she is.</p>
            <p>First of all, she is, as all women should be if they can, remarkably handsome. She
               may be—it is a de- licate matter to speak of a lady’s age!—she must be
               five-and-forty; but few beauties of twenty could stand a comparison with her
               loveliness. It is such a fulness of bloom, so luxuriant, so satiating; just tall
               enough to carry off the plumpness which at forty-five is so be- coming; a brilliant
               complexion; curled pouting lips! long, clear, bright grey eyes—the colour for expres-
               sion, that which unites the quickness of the black with the softness of the blue; a
               Roman regularity of fea- ture; and a profusion of rich brown hair.—Such is Aunt
               Martha. Add to this a very gentle and pleasant speech, always kind, and generally
               lively; the sweetest temper; the easiest manners; a singular rectitude and singleness
               of mind; a perfect open-heartedness; and a total unconsciousness of all these charms;
               and you will wonder a little that she is Aunt Martha still. I have heard hints of an
               early engagement broken by the fickleness of man;—and there is about her an aversion
               to love in one particular direction—the love matrimo- nial—and an overflowing of
               affection in all other chan- nels, that it seems as if the natural course of the
               stream had been violently dammed up. She has many lovers—admirers I should say,—for
               there is, amidst her<pb n=”252”/> good-humoured gaiety, a coyness that forbids their
               going farther; a modesty almost amounting to shy- ness, that checks even the laughing
               girls, who some- times accuse her of stealing away their beaux. I do not think any
               man on earth could tempt her into wed- lock; it would be a most unpardonable monopoly
               if any one should; an intolerable engrossing of a general blessing; a theft from the
               whole community.</p>
            <p>Her usual home is the white house covered with roses; and her station in the family
               is rather doubtful. She is not the mistress, for her charming nieces are old enough
               to take and to adorn the head of the table; nor the housekeeper, though, as she is
               the only lady of the establishment who wears pockets, those ensigns of au- thority,
               the keys will sometimes be found, with other strays, in that goodly receptacle: nor a
               guest; her spirit is too active for that lazy post; her real vocation there, and
               every where, seems to be comforting, cheer- ing, welcoming, and spoiling every thing
               that comes in her way; and, above all, nursing and taking care. Of all kind
               employments, these are her favourites. Oh the shawlings, the cloakings, the
               cloggings! the cau- tions against cold, or heat, or rain, or sun! the reme- dies for
               diseases not arrived! colds uncaught! incipient tooth-aches! rheumatisms to come! She
               loves nursing so well, that we used to accuse her of inventing mala- dies for other
               people, that she might have the pleasure<pb n=”253”/> of curing them; and when they
               really come—as come they will sometimes in spite of Aunt Martha—what a nurse she is!
               It is worth while to be a little sick to be so attended. All the cousins, and
               cousins’ cousins of her connection, as regularly send for her on the occa- sion of a
               lying-in, as for the midwife. I suppose she has undergone the ceremony of dandling
               the baby, sitting up with the new mamma, and dispensing the cau- dle, twenty times at
               least. She is equally important at weddings or funerals. Her humanity is
               inexhaustible. She has an intense feeling of fellowship with her kind, and grieves or
               rejoices in the sufferings or happiness of others with a reality as genuine as it is
               rare.</p>
            <p>Her accomplishments are exactly of this sympathetic order; all calculated to
               administer much to the pleasure of her companions, and nothing to her own importance
               or vanity. She leaves to the sirens, her nieces, the higher enchantments of the
               piano, the harp, and the guitar, and that noblest of instruments, the human voice;
               ambitious of no other musical fame than such as belongs to the playing of quadrilles
               and waltzes for their little dances, in which she is indefatigable: she neither
               caricatures the face of man nor of nature under pretence of drawing figures or
               landscapes; but she ornaments the reticules, bell-ropes, ottomans, and chair-covers
               of all her acquaintance, with flowers as rich and luxuriant as her own beauty. She
               draws patterns for the igno-<pb n=”254”/> rant, and works flounces, frills, and
               baby-linen, for the idle; she reads aloud to the sick, plays at cards with the old,
               and loses at chess to the unhappy. Her gift in gossiping, too, is extraordinary; she
               is a gentle newsmonger, and turns her scandal on the sunny side. But she is an old
               maid still; and certain small pecu- liarities hang about her. She is a thorough
               hoarder; whatever fashion comes up, she is sure to have some- thing of the sort by
               her—or, at least, something there- unto convertible. She is a little superstitious;
               sees strangers in her tea-cup, gifts in her finger-nails, let- ters and
               winding-sheets in the candle, and purses and coffins in the fire; would not spill the
               salt “for all the worlds that one ever has to give;” and looks with dis- may on a
               crossed knife and fork. Moreover, she is orderly to fidgetiness;—that is her greatest
               calamity! —for young ladies now-a-days are not quite so tidy as they should be,—and
               ladies’ maids are much worse; and drawers are tumbled, and drawing-rooms in a litter.
               Happy she to whom a disarranged drawer can be a misery! Dear and happy Aunt
               Martha!</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
