<?xml version=”1.0” encoding=”UTF-8”?>
<?xml-model href=”http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng” type=”application/xml” schematypens=”http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0”?>
<?xml-model href=”http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng” type=”application/xml”
	schematypens=”http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron”?>
<TEI xmlns=”http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0”>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <!--2017-01-10 ebb: Here is the source of our base text in Hathi Trust:
https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/ssd?id=mdp.39015008020441;seq=189;num=177
The nine missing sketches are Sections 16 to 23, the last nine sketches in OV.

Make a new file for each sketch. 
Follow the filenameing conventions that you see in Box. Each OV sketch begins with the letters OV, then the main title, and if a subtitle it goes in block caps at the end of the filename.xml
Please use the 1824 NCCO PDF (saved in OV folder in Box) to check and correct the text.

  -->

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
            <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>


            <editor>Samantha Webb</editor>
            <editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName>Jonathan M. Horanic</persName>
               <persName>Samantha Webb</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--2017-01-10 ebb: We need to change this sourceDesc to indicate we’re checking each text and altering it to represent the 1824 edition as published in NCCO. -->
            <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
            <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                  <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third
                     Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B.
                     Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
               </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first
               edition published in 1824. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type=”sketch”>
            <pb n=”241”/>
            <head>WALKS IN THE COUNTRY.<lb/>NUTTING.
               <!--ebb: If there’s a subtitle use an <lb/> element to separate -->
            </head>
            <p>September 26th.—One of those delicious autumnal days, when the air, the sky, and the
               earth, seem lulled into an universal calm, softer and milder even than May. We
               sallied forth for a walk, in a mood con- genial to the weather and the season,
               avoiding, by mutual consent, the bright and sunny common, and the gay high road, and
               stealing through shady unfre- quented lanes, where we were not likely to meet any
               one,—not even the pretty family procession which in other years we used to
               contemplate with so much in- terest—the father, mother, and children, returning from
               the wheat-field, the little ones laden with brist- ling close-tied bunches of
               wheat-ears, their own glean- ings, or a bottle and a basket which had contained their
               frugal dinner, whilst the mother would carry her babe hushing and lulling it, and the
               father and an elder child trudged after with the cradle, all seeming<pb n=”242”/>
               weary, and all happy. We shall not see such a pro- cession as this to-day; for the
               harvest is nearly over, the fields are deserted, the silence may almost be felt.
               Except the wintry notes of the red-breast, nature her- self is mute. But how
               beautiful, how gentle, how har- monious, how rich! The rain has preserved to the
               herbage all the freshness and verdure of spring, and the world of leaves has lost
               nothing of its midsummer brightness, and the hare-bell is on the banks and the
               woodbine in the hedges, and the low furze, which the lambs cropped in the spring, has
               burst again into its golden blossoms.</p>
            <p>All is beautiful that the eye can see; perhaps the more beautiful for being shut in
               with a forest-like closeness. We have no prospect in this labyrinth of lanes,
               cross-roads, mere cart-ways, leading to the innu- merable little farms into which
               this part of the parish is divided. Uphill or down, these quiet woody lanes scarcely
               give us a peep at the world, except when, leaning over a gate, we look into one of
               the small enclosures, hemmed in with hedgerows, so closely set with growing timber,
               that the meady opening looks almost like a glade in a wood, or when some cottage,
               planted at a corner of one of the little greens formed by the meeting of these
               cross-ways, almost startles us by the unexpected sight of the dwellings of men in
               such a solitude. But that we have more of hill and<pb n=”243”/> dale, and that our
               cross-roads are excellent in their kind, this side of our parish would resemble the
               de- scription given of La Vendee, in Madame Laroche- jacquelin’s most interesting
               book *. I am sure if wood can entitle a country to be called Le Bocage, none can have
               a better right to the name. Even this pretty snug farm-house on the hill side, with
               its front covered with the rich vine, which goes wreathing up to the very top of the
               clustered chimney, and its sloping orchard full of fruit—even this pretty quiet nest
               can hardly peep out of its leaves. Ah! they are gathering in the orchard harvest.
               Look at that young rogue in the old mossy apple-tree—that great tree, bending with
               the weight of its golden-rennets—see how he pelts his little sister beneath with
               apples as red and as round as her own cheeks, while she, with her outstretched frock,
               is trying to catch them, and laugh- ing and offering to pelt again as often as one
               bobs against her; and look at that still younger imp, who, as grave as a judge, is
               creeping on hands and knees under the tree, picking up the apples as they fall so
                  <note place=”bottom”>* An almost equally interesting account of that very peculiar
                  and interesting scenery, may be found in “ The Maid of La Vendue,” an English
                  novel, remarkable for its simplicity and truth of paint- ing, written by Mrs. Le
                  Noir, tbe daughter of Christopher Smart, and inheritrix of much of his talent. Her
                  works deserve to be better known.</note><pb n=”244”/> deedily *, and depositing
               them so honestly in the great basket on the grass, already fixed so firmly and opened
               so widely, and filled almost to overflowing by the brown rough fruitage of the
               golden-rennet’s next neighbour the russeting; and see that smallest urchin of all
               seated apart in infantine state on the turfy bank, with that toothsome piece of
               deformity a crumpling in each hand, now biting from one sweet hard juicy mor- sel,
               and now from another.—Is not that a pretty English picture? And then, farther up the
               orchard, that bold hardy lad, the eldest-born, who has scaled (Heaven knows how!) the
               tall straight upper branch of that great pear-tree, and is sitting there as securely
               and as fearlessly, in as much real safety and apparent danger, as a sailor on the
               top-mast. Now he shakes the tree with a mighty swing that brings down a pelting
               shower of stony bergamots, which the father gathers rapidly up, whilst the mother can
               hardly assist for her motherly fear,—a fear which only spurs the spirited boy to
               bolder ventures. Is not that a pretty picture? And they are such a handsome family,
               too, <note place=”bottom”>*” Deedily,”—I am not quite sore that this word is good
                  English; but it is genuine Hampshire, and is used by the most correct of female
                  writers, Miss Austen. It means (and it is no small merit that it has no exact
                  synonyme) any thing done with a profound and plodding attention, an action which
                  engrosses all the powers of mind and body.</note><pb n=”245”/> the Brookers. I do
               not know that there is any gipsey blood, but there is the true gipsey complexion,
               richly brown, with cheeks and lips so deeply red, black hair curling close to their
               heads in short crisp rings, white shining teeth—and such eyes !—That sort of beauty
               entirely eclipses your mere roses and lilies. Even Lizzy, the prettiest of fair
               children, would look poor and watery by the side of Willy Brooker, the sober little
               personage who is picking up the apples with his small chubby hands, and filling the
               basket so orderly, next to his father the most useful man in the field. “Willy!” He
               hears without seeing; for we are quite hidden by the high bank, and a spreading
               hawthorn- bush that overtops it, though between the lower branches and the grass we
               have found a convenient peep-hole. “Willy!” The voice sounds to him like some fairy
               dream, and the black eyes are raised from the ground with sudden wonder, the long
               silky eye-lashes thrown back till they rest on the delicate brow, and a deeper blush
               is burning in those dark cheeks, and a smile is dimpling about those scarlet lips.
               But the voice is silent now, and the little quiet boy, after a moment’s pause, is
               gone coolly to work again. He is indeed a most lovely child. I think some day or
               other he must marry Lizzy; I shall pro- pose the match to their respective mammas. At
               present the parties are rather too young for a weddingi-the<pb n=”246”/> intended
               bridegroom being, as I should judge, six, or thereabout, and the fair bride barely
               five,—but at least we might have a betrothment after the royal fashion,—there could
               be no harm in that. Miss Lizzy, I have no doubt, would be as demure and coquettish as
               if ten winters more had gone over her head, and poor Willy would open his innocent
               black eyes, and wonder what was going forward. They would be the very Oberon and
               Titania of the village, the fairy king and queen.</p>
            <p>Ah! here is the hedge along which the periwinkle wreathes and twines so profusely,
               with its ever-green leaves shining like the myrtle, and its starry blue flowers. It
               is seldom found wild in this part of En- gland; but, when we do meet with it, it is
               so abundant and so welcome,—the very robin-redbreast of flowers, a winter friend.
               Unless in those unfrequent frosts which destroy all vegetation, it blossoms from
               Septem- ber to June, surviving the last lingering crane’s-bill, forerunning the
               earliest primrose, hardier even than the mountain daisy,—peeping out from beneath the
               snow, looking at itself in the ice, smiling through the tem- pests of life,and yet
               welcoming and enjoying the sun- beams. Oh, to be like that flower!</p>
            <p>The little spring that has been bubbling under the hedge all along the hill-side,
               begins, now that we have mounted the eminence and are imperceptibly descend- ing, to
               deviate into a capricious variety of clear deep<pb n=”247”/> pools and channels, so
               narrow and so choked with weeds, that a child might overstep them. The hedge has also
               changed its character. It is no longer the close compact vegetable wall of hawthorn,
               and maple, and briar roses, intertwined with bramble and woodbine, and crowned with
               large elms or thickly set saplings. No! the pretty meadow which rises high above us,
               backed and almost surrounded by a tall coppice, needs no defence on our side but its
               own steep bank, gar- nished with tufts of broom, with pollard oaks wreathed with ivy,
               and here and there with long patches of hazel overhanging the water. “Ah there are
               still nuts on that bough!” and in an instant my dear companion, ac- tive and eager
               and delighted as a boy, has hooked down with his walking-stick one of the lissome
               hazel stalks, and cleared it of its tawny clusters, and in another mo- ment he has
               mounted the bank, and is in the midst of the nuttery, now transferring the spoil from
               the lower branches into that vast variety of pockets which gentle- men carry about
               them, now bending the tall tops into the lane, holding them down by main force, so
               that I might reach them and enjoy the pleasure of collecting some of the plunder
               myself. A very great pleasure he knew it would be. I doffed my shawl, tucked up my
               flounces, turned my straw bonnet into a basket, and began gathering and
               scrambling—for, manage it how you may, nutting is scrambling work,—those boughs,<pb
                  n=”248”/> however tightly you may grasp them by the young fragrant twigs and the
               bright green leaves, will recoil and burst away; but there is a pleasure even in
               that: so on we go, scrambling and gathering with all our might and all our glee. Oh
               what an enjoyment! All my life long I have had a passion for that sort of seek- ing
               which implies finding, (the secret, I believe, of the love of field-sports, which is
               in man’s mind a natural impulse,)—therefore I love violeting,—therefore, when we had
               a fine garden I used to love to gather strawberries, and cut asparagus, and, above
               all, to collect the filberts from the shrubberies: but this hedge-row nutting beats
               that sport all to nothing. That was a make-believe thing, compared with this; there
               was no surprise, no suspense, no unexpectedness—it was as inferior to this wild
               nutting, as the turning out of a bag- fox is to unearthing the fellow in the eyes of
               a stanch fox-hunter.</p>
            <p>Oh what an enjoyment this nut-gathering is! They are in such abundance, that it seems
               as if there were not a boy in the parish, nor a young man, nor a young woman,—for a
               basket of nuts is the universal tribute of country gallantry; our pretty damsel
               Harriet has had at least half a dozen this season; but no one has found out these.
               And they are so full too, we lose half of them from over-ripeness; they drop from the
               socket at the slightest motion. If we lose, there is one who<pb n=”248”/> finds. May
               is as fond of nuts as a squirrel, and cracks the shell and extracts the kernel with
               equal dexterity. Her white glossy head is upturned now to watch them as they fall.
               See how her neck is thrown back like that of a swan, and how beautifully her folded
               ears quiver with expectation, and how her quick eye follows the rustling noise, and
               her light feet dance and pat the ground, and leap up with eagerness, seeming almost
               sustained in the air, just as I have seen her when Brush is beating a hedgerow, and
               she knows from his questing that there is a hare afoot. See, she has caught that nut
               just before it touched the water; but the water would have been no defence,—she
               fishes them from the bottom, she delves after them amongst the matted grass—even my
               bonnet—how beggingly she looks at that!” Oh what a pleasure nutting is!—Is it not,
               May? But the pockets are almost full, and so is the basket-bonnet, and that bright
               watch the sun says it is late; and after all it is wrong to rob the poor boys—is it
               not, May 1”—May shakes her graceful head denyingly, as if she understood the
               question—” And we must go home now—must we not? But we will come nutting again some
               time or other—shall we not, my May?”</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
