<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>-->

<!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>-->

<!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
-->

<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng"
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng" 
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery: Preface</title>
                <author>Mary Russell Mitford</author>

                <editor>Alexandra Drayton</editor>
                <editor>Samantha Webb</editor>


                <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
                    Project</orgName></sponsor>
                <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
                <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                    <persName>Alexandra Drayton</persName>
                    <persName>Samantha Webb</persName>
                    <persName>Jordan Price</persName>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
                    <persName>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
                    <persName ref="#bas">Brooke A. Stewart</persName>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain
                    phrases describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date:
                    2 June 2013. P5.</edition>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
                    <persName>Who?</persName>
                </respStmt>

            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
                <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
                <date>2013</date>
                <availability>
                    <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0
                        Unported License</licence>
                </availability>

            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
            </seriesStmt>

            <notesStmt>
                <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
                <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
            </notesStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                        <title>Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and
                            Scenery</title><edition>Third Edition</edition> by <author>Mary Russell
                            Mitford</author><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Geo. B.
                            Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria
                            Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>. </bibl> This text appears to be
                    identical in pagination and content to the first edition published in 1824. </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <front>
            <titlePage>
                <pb n="ii"/>
                <docTitle>
                    <titlePart type="main">Our Village:</titlePart>
                    <titlePart type="subtitle">Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery.</titlePart>
                </docTitle>
                <byline>by <docAuthor>Mary Russell Mitford</docAuthor>, Author of <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian, A
                        Tragedy</title><lb/></byline>
                <docEdition>Third Edition.</docEdition>
                <docImprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><lb/><publisher>Geo. B.
                        Whittaker</publisher>,<lb/><placeName>Ave-Maria-Lane</placeName>.
                        <docDate>1825</docDate>.</docImprint>
            </titlePage>
            <pb n="iii"/>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="sketch">
                <head><title level="a" ref="#Country_Cricket_Match_OV"></title>A COUNTRY CRICKET-MATCH.</head>
                <p> <persName ref="#OVNarrator">I</persName> doubt if there be any scene in the world more animating or delightful than a cricket-match :—I do not mean a set match at <placeName ref="#Lords_Cricket_Ground">Lord's Ground</placeName> for money, hard money, between a certain number of <orgName ref="#CountryCM_cricketers_OV">gentleman and players</orgName>, as they are called—people who make a trade of that noble sport, and degrade it into an affair of bettings, and hedgings, and cheatings, it may be, like boxing or horse-racing: nor do I mean a pretty <foreign>fête</foreign> in a gentleman’s park, where <orgName ref="#CountryCM_cricket_dandies_OV">one club
                    of cricketing dandies</orgName> encounters another such club, and where they show off in
                    graceful costume to a gay marquee of <orgName ref="#CountryCM_belles_OV">admiring belles</orgName>, who condescend so to
                    purchase admiration, and while away a long summer morning in partaking cold
                    collations, conversing occasionally, and seeming to understand the game;—the
                    whole being conducted according to ball-room etiquette, so as to be exceedingly
                    elegant and exceedingly dull. No! the cricket that I mean is a real solid
                    old-fashioned match between neighbouring parishes, where each attacks the other
                    for ho-<pb n="147"/>nour and a supper, glory, and half a crown a man. If there be
                    any gentlemen amongst them, it is well—if not, it is so much the better. Your
                    gentleman is in general rather an anomalous character. Elderly
                    gentlemen are obviously good for nothing; and young beaux are, for the most
                    part, hampered and trammelled by dress and habit; the stiff cravat, the
                    pinched-in waist, the dandy walk—oh they will never do for cricket! Now, our
                    country lads, accustomed to the flail or the hammer (your blacksmiths are
                    capital hitters,) have the free use of their arms; they know how to move their
                    shoulders; and they can move their feet too—they can run; then they are so much
                    better made, so much more athletic, and yet so much lissomer—to use a <placeName ref="#Hampshire_county">Hampshire</placeName>
                    phrase, which deserves at least to be good English. Here and there, indeed, one
                    meets with an old Etonian, who retains his boyish love for that game which
                    formed so considerable a branch of his education; some even preserve their
                    boyish proficiency, but in general it wears away like the Greek, quite as
                    certainly, and almost as fast; a few years of <placeName ref="#Oxford_Univ">Oxford</placeName>, or <orgName ref="#Cambridge_Univ"></orgName>, or the
                    continent, are sufficient to annihilate both the power and the inclination. No!
                    a village match is the thing,—where our highest officer—our conductor (to borrow
                    a musical term) is but a little farmer’s second son; where a day-labourer is our
                    bowler, and a blacksmith our long-stop; where the<pb n="148"/> spectators
                    consist of the retired <orgName ref="#CountryCM_retired_cricketers_OV">cricketers</orgName>, the veterans of the green, the careful
                    <orgName ref="#CountryCM_mothers_OV">mothers</orgName>, <orgName ref="#CountryCM_girls_OV">the girls</orgName>, and all the <orgName ref="#CountryCM_boys_OV">boys of two parishes</orgName>, together with a few
                    <orgName ref="#CountryCM_amateurs_OV">amateurs</orgName> little above them in rank, and not at all in pretension; where laughing
                    and shouting, and the very ecstasy of merriment and good humour, prevail: such a
                    match, in short, as I attended yesterday, at the expense of getting twice wet
                    through, and as I would attend tomorrow, at the certainty of having that ducking
                    doubled.</p>
                <p>For the last three weeks <rs type="place" ref="#ThreeMileCross">our village</rs> has been in a state of great excitement,
                    occasioned by a challenge from our north-western neighbours, the <orgName ref="#CountryCM_men_of_B_OV">men of <placeName ref="#B_town_OV">B</placeName></orgName>, to
                    contend with us at cricket. Now we have not been much in the habit of playing
                    matches. Three or four years ago, indeed, we encountered the <orgName ref="#CountryCM_men_of_S_OV">men of <placeName ref="#S_town_OV">S</placeName></orgName><!--scw: probably Silchester-->, our
                    neighbours south-by-east, with a sort of doubtful success, beating them on our
                    own ground, whilst they in the second match returned the compliment on theirs.
                    This discouraged us. Then an unnatural coalition between a <persName ref="#CountryCM_highChurch_curate_OV">high-church curate</persName>
                    and an <persName ref="#CountryCM_evangelical_farmer_OV">evangelical gentleman-farmer</persName> drove <orgName ref="CountryCM_cricketers_OV">our lads</orgName> from the Sunday evening
                    practice, which, as it did not begin before both services were concluded, and as
                    it tended to keep the young men from the ale-house, our magistrates had winked
                    at, if not encouraged. The sport therefore had languished until the present
                    season, when under another change of circumstances the spirit began to
                        revive.<pb n="149"/> Half a dozen fine active lads, of influence amongst
                    their comrades, grew into men and yearned for cricket: an <persName ref="CountryCM_publican_OV">enterprising publican</persName>
                    gave a set of ribands; his rival, <persName ref="#RoseInnLandlord_OV">mine host of the Rose</persName>, an out-doer by
                        profession, gave two; and the <rs type="person" ref="#CountryCM_highChurch_curate_OV">clergyman</rs> and his <rs type="person" ref="#CountryCM_evangelical_farmer_OV">lay ally</rs>, both well-disposed and
                    good-natured men, gratified by the submission to their authority, and finding,
                    perhaps, that no great good resulted from the substitution of public houses
                    for-out-of door diversions, relaxed. In short the practice recommenced, and the
                    hill was again alive with men and boys, and innocent merriment; but farther than
                    the riband matches amongst ourselves nobody dreamed of going, till this
                    challenge—we were modest, and doubted our own strength. The <orgName ref="#CountryCM_Bpeople_OV"><placeName ref="#B_town_OV">B</placeName> people</orgName>, on the
                    other hand, must have been braggers born a whole parish of gasconaders. Never
                    was such boasting! such crowing! such ostentatious display of practice! such
                    mutual compliments from man to man—bowler to batter, batter to bowler! It was a
                    wonder they did not challenge all <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>. It must be confessed that we were a
                    little astounded; yet we firmly resolved not to decline the combat; and one of
                    the most spirited of the new growth, <persName ref="#Grey_William_OV">William Grey</persName> by name, took up the glove in
                    a style of manly courtesy, that would have done honour to a knight in the days
                    of chivalry.—<said who="#Grey_William_OV" direct="false" aloud="true">“We were not professed players,” he said, "being little better than
                    school-boys, and scarcely<pb n="150"/> older: but, since they had done us the
                    honour to challenge us, we would try our strength. It would be no discredit to
                    be beaten by such a field.”</said></p>
                <p>Having accepted the wager of battle, <rs type="person" ref="#Grey_William_OV">our champion</rs> began forthwith to collect his
                    forces. <persName ref="#Grey_William_OV">William Grey</persName> is himself one of the finest youths that one shall
                    see,—tall, active, slender and yet strong, with a piercing eye full of sagacity,
                    and a smile full of good humour,—a farmer’s son by station, and used to hard
                    work as farmers’ sons are now, liked by every body, and admitted to be an
                    excellent cricketer. He immediately set forth to muster his men, remembering
                    with great complacency that <persName ref="#Long_Samuel_OV">Samuel Long</persName>, a bowler <emph>comme il y en a
                        peu</emph>, the very man who had knocked down nine wickets, had beaten us,
                    bowled us out at the fatal return match some years ago at <placeName>S</placeName>., had luckily, in a
                    remove of a quarter of a mile last Lady-day, crossed the boundaries of his old
                    parish, and actually belonged to us. Here was a stroke of good fortune! Our
                    captain applied to him instantly; and he agreed at a word. Indeed <persName ref="#Long_Samuel_OV">Samuel Long</persName> is
                    a very civilised person. He is a middle-aged man who looks rather old amongst
                    our young lads, and whose thickness and breadth give no token of remarkable
                    activity; but he is very active, and so steady a player! so safe! We had half
                    gained the match when we had secured him. He is a man of substance, too, in
                    every way; owns one cow, two don-<pb n="151"/>keys, six pigs, and geese and ducks
                    beyond count; dresses like a farmer, and owes no man a shilling;— and all this
                    from pure industry, sheer day-labour. Note, that your good cricketer is commonly
                    the most industrious man in the parish; the habits that make him such are
                    precisely those which make a good workman—steadiness, sobriety, and
                    activity—<persName ref="#Long_Samuel_OV">Samuel Long</persName> might pass for the beau ideal of the two characters. Happy
                    were we to possess him! Then we had another piece of good luck. <persName ref="#Brown_James_OV">James Brown</persName>, a
                    journeyman blacksmith and a native, who, being of a rambling disposition, had
                    roamed from place to place for half a dozen years, had just returned to settle
                    with his brother at another corner of our village, bringing with him a
                    prodigious reputation in cricket and in gallantry—the gay Lothario of the
                    neighborhood. He is said to have made more conquests in love and in cricket than
                    any blacksmith in the county. To him also went the indefatigable <persName ref="#Grey_William_OV">William Grey</persName>,
                    and he also consented to play. No end to our good fortune! Another celebrated
                    batter, called <persName ref="#Hearne_Joseph_OV">Joseph Hearne</persName>, had likewise recently married into the parish. He
                    worked, it is true, at the A. mills, but slept at the house of his wife’s father
                    in our territories. He also was sought and found by our leader. But he was grand
                    and shy; made an immense favour of the thing; courted courting and then hung
                    back;—“Did not know that he could be spared; had partly resolved<pb n="152"/>
                    not to play again—at least not this season; thought it rash to accept the
                    challenge; thought they might do without him—”—“Truly I think so too,” said our
                    spirited champion; <said who="#Hearne_Joeseph_OV">“we will not trouble you, <persName ref="#Hearne_Joeseph_OV">Mr. Hearne</persName>.”</said></p>
                <p> Having thus secured two powerful auxiliaries, and rejected a third, we began to
                    reckon and select the regular native forces. Thus ran our list:—William Grey,
                    1.—<persName ref="#Long_Samuel_OV">Samuel Long</persName>, 2.—<persName ref="#Brown_James_OV">James Brown</persName>, 3.—<persName ref="#Simmons_George_OV">George</persName> and <persName ref="#Simmons_John_OV">John Simmons</persName>, one capital, the
                    other so, so,—an uncertain hitter, but a good fieldsman, 5.—<persName ref="#Brent_Joel">Joel Brent</persName>
                    excellent, 6.—<persName ref="#Appleton_Ben_OV">Ben Appleton</persName>—Here was a little pause—<persName ref="#Appleton_Ben_OV">Ben</persName>’s abilities at cricket
                    were not completely ascertained; but then he was so good a fellow, so full of
                    fun and waggery! no doing without <persName ref="#Appleton_Ben_OV">Ben</persName>. So he figured in the list, 7.—<persName ref="#Harris_George_OV">George Harris</persName>—a short halt there too! Slowish—slow but sure. I think the proverb
                    brought him in, 8.—<persName ref="#Coper_Tom_OV">Tom Coper</persName>—oh, beyond the world, Tom Coper! the red-headed
                    gardening lad, whose left-handed strokes send <emph>her</emph> (a cricket-ball,
                    like that other moving thing a ship, is always of the feminine gender,) send her
                    spinning a mile, 9.—<persName ref="#Willis_Robert_OV">Robert Willis</persName>, another blacksmith, 10.</p>
                <p>We had now ten of our eleven, but the choice of the last occasioned some demur.
                    Three young <orgName>Martins</orgName> , rich farmers of the neighbourhood, successively presented
                    themselves, and were all rejected by our inde-<pb n="153"/>pendent and impartial
                    general for want of merit—<emph>cricketal</emph> merit. “Not good enough,” was
                    his pithy answer. Then our worthy neighbour, the half-pay <persName ref="#Lieutenant_OV">lieutenant</persName>, offered
                    his services—he, too, though with some hesitation and modesty, was refused—”Not
                    quite young enough” was his sentence. <persName ref="#Strong_John_OV">John Strong</persName>, the exceedingly long son of
                    our dwarfish <persName ref="#mason_OV">mason</persName>, was the next candidate,—a nice youth—every body likes <persName ref="#Strong_John_OV">John Strong</persName>,—and a willing, but so tall and so limp, bent in the middle—a
                    thread-paper, six feet high! We were all afraid that, in spite of his name, his
                    strength would never hold out. <said who="#Grey_William_OV">"“Wait till next year, <persName ref="#Strong_John_OV">John</persName>,”</said> quoth <persName ref="#Grey_William_OV">William Grey</persName>,
                    with all the dignified seniority of twenty speaking to eighteen. <said who="#Strong_John_OV">“<persName ref="#Coper_Tom_OV">Coper</persName> a year
                        younger,”</said> said <persName ref="#Strong_John_OV">John</persName>. <said who="#Grey_William_OV">“<persName ref="#Coper_Tom_OV">Coper</persName>’s a foot shorter,”</said> replied William: so <persName ref="#Strong_John_OV">John</persName> retired;
                    and the eleventh man remained unchosen, almost till the eleventh hour. The eve
                    of the match arrived, and the post was still vacant, when a little boy of
                    fifteen, <persName ref="#Willis_David_OV">David Willis</persName>, brother to <persName ref="#Willis_Robert_OV">Robert</persName>, admitted by accident to the last
                    practice, saw eight of them out, and was voted in by acclamation.</p>
                <p>That Sunday evening’s practice (for Monday was the important day) was a period of
                    great anxiety, and, to say the truth, of great pleasure. There is something
                    strangely delightful in the innocent spirit of party. To be one of a numerous
                    body, to be authorised to say <emph>we</emph>, to have a rightful interest in
                    triumph or defeat, is gra-<pb n="154"/>tifying at once to social feeling and to
                    personal pride. There was not a ten-year old urchin, or a septuagenary woman in
                    the parish, who did not feel an additional importance, a reflected consequence,
                    in speaking of <quote>“our side.”</quote> An election interests in the same way; but that
                    feeling is less pure. Money is there, and hatred, and politics, and lies. Oh, to
                    be a voter, or a voter’s wife, comes nothing near the genuine and hearty
                    sympathy of belonging to a parish, breathing the same air, looking oTomn the same
                    trees, listening to the same nightingales! Talk of a patriotic elector!— Give me
                    a parochial patriot, a man who loves his parish! Even we, the female partisans,
                    may partake the common ardour. I am sure I did. I never, though tolerably eager
                    and enthusiastic at all times, remember being in a more delicious state of
                    excitation than on the eve of that battle. Our hopes waxed stronger and
                    stronger. Those of our players, who were present, were excellent. <persName ref="#Grey_William_OV">William Grey</persName>
                    got forty notches off his own bat; and that brilliant hitter <persName ref="#Coper_Tom_OV">Tom Coper</persName> gained
                    eight from two successive balls. As the evening advanced, too, we had
                    encouragement of another sort. A spy, who had been despatched to reconnoitre the
                    enemy’s quarters, returned from their practising ground, with a most consolatory
                    report. <said who="#Grover_Charles_OV">“Really,”</said> said <persName ref="#Grover_Charles_OV">Charles Grover</persName>, our intelligencer—a fine old steady
                    judge, one who had played well in his day—<said who="#Grover_Charles_OV">“they are no better<pb n="155"/> than
                    so many old women. Any five of ours would beat their eleven.”</said> This sent us to
                    bed in high spirits.</p>
                <p>Morning dawned less favourably. The sky promised a series of deluging showers,
                    and kept its word, as English skies are wont to do on such occasions; and a
                    lamentable message arrived at the head-quarters from our trusty comrade <persName ref="#Brent_Joel">Joel Brent</persName>. His master, a great farmer, had begun the hay-harvest that very morning,
                    and <persName ref="#Brent_Joel">Joel Brent</persName>, being as eminent in one field as in another, could not be spared.
                    Imagine <persName ref="#Brent_Joel">Joel Brent</persName>’s plight! the most ardent of all our eleven! a knight held back
                    from the tourney! a soldier from the battle! The poor swain was inconsolable. At
                    last, one who is always ready to do a good-natured action, great or little, set
                    forth to back his petition; and, by dint of appealing to the public spirit of
                    our worthy neighbour, and the state of the barometer, talking alternately of the
                    parish honour and thunder showers, of lost matches and sopped hay, he carried
                    his point, and returned triumphantly with the delighted <persName ref="#Brent_Joel">Joel Brent</persName>.</p>
                <p>In the meantime we became sensible of another defalcation. On calling over our
                    roll, <persName ref="#Brown_James_OV">Brown</persName> was missing; and the spy of the preceding night, <persName ref="#Grover_Charles_OV">Charles Grover</persName>,—the
                    universal scout and messenger of the village, a man who will run half-a-dozen
                    miles for a pint of beer, who does errands for the very love of the<pb n="156"/>
                    trade, who, if he had been a lord, would have been an ambassador—was instantly
                    despatched to summon the truant. His report spread general consternation. <persName ref="#Brown_James_OV">Brown</persName>
                    had set off at four o’clock in the morning to play in a cricket-match at M., a
                    little town twelve miles off, which had been his last residence. Here was
                    desertion! Here was treachery! Here was treason against that goodly state, our
                    parish! To send <persName ref="#Brown_James_OV">James Brown</persName> to <placeName ref="#Coventry_City">Coventry</placeName><!--SCW: "sent to Coventry" is an idiomatic expression meaning, roughly, to be sent to the doghouse. I'm going to check whether there's a way of indicating idiomatic expressions in the TEI--> was the immediate resolution; but even
                    that seemed too light a punishment for such delinquency. Then how we cried him
                    down! At ten, on Sunday-night, (for the rascal had actually practised with us,
                    and never said a word of his intended disloyalty,) he was our faithful mate, and
                    the best player (take him for all in all) of the eleven. At ten in the morning
                    he had run away, and we were well rid of him; he was no batter compared with
                    <persName ref="#Grey_William_OV">William Grey</persName> or <persName ref="#Coper_Tom_OV">Tom Coper</persName>; not fit to wipe the shoes of <persName ref="#Long_Samuel_OV">Samuel Long</persName>, as a
                    bowler; nothing of a scout to <persName ref="#Simmons_John_OV">John Simmons</persName>; the boy <persName ref="#Willis_David_OV">David Willis</persName> was worth fifty
                    of him— <quote>“<lg>
                            <l>I trust we have within our realm </l>
                            <l>Five hundred good as he.</l>
                    </lg>”</quote> was the universal sentiment. So we took tall <persName ref="#Strong_John_OV">John Strong</persName>,
                    who, with an incurable hankering after the honour of being admitted, had kept
                    constantly with<pb n="157"/> the players, to take the chance of some such
                    accident—we took <persName ref="#Strong_John_OV">John</persName> for our <emph>pis-aller</emph>. I never saw any one
                    prouder than the good-humoured lad was of this not very flattering piece of
                    preferment.</p>
                <p><persName ref="#Strong_John_OV">John Strong</persName> was elected, and <persName ref="#Brown_James_OV">Brown</persName> sent to <placeName ref="#Coventry_City">Coventry</placeName>; and, when I first heard of
                    his delinquency, I thought the punishment only too mild for the crime. But I
                    have since learned the secret history of the offence; (if we could know the
                    secret histories of all offences, how much better the world would seem than it
                    does now!) and really my wrath is much abated. It was a piece of gallantry, of
                    devotion to the sex, or rather a chivalrous obedience to one chosen fair. I must
                    tell my readers the story. <persName ref="#Allen_Mary_OV">Mary Allen</persName>, the prettiest girl of M., had it seems
                    revenged upon our blacksmith the numberless inconsistancies of which he stood
                    accused. He was in love over head and ears, but the nymph was cruel. She said
                    no, and no, and no, and poor <persName ref="#Brown_James_OV">Brown</persName>, three times rejected, at last resolved to
                    leave the place, partly in despair, and partly in that hope which often mingles
                    strangely with a lover’s despair, the hope that when he was gone he should be
                    missed. He came home to his brother’s accordingly; but for five weeks he heard
                    nothing from or of the inexorable Mary, and was glad to beguile his own “vexing
                    thoughts,” by endeavouring to create in his mind an artificial and factitious
                    interest in our<pb n="158"/> cricket-match—all unimportant as such a trifle must
                    have seemed to a man in love. Poor <persName ref="#Brown_James_OV">James</persName>, however, is a social and warm-hearted
                    person, not likely to resist a contagious sympathy. As the time for the play
                    advanced, the interest which he had at first affected became genuine and
                    sincere: and he was really, when he left the ground on Sunday-night, almost as
                    enthusiastically absorbed in the event of the next day as <persName ref="#Brent_Joel">Joel Brent</persName> himself. He
                    little foresaw the new and delightful interest which awaited him at home, where,
                    on the moment of his arrival, his sister-in-law and confidante, presented him
                    with a billet from the lady of his heart. It had, with the usual delay of
                    letters sent by private hands, in that rank of life, loitered on the road in a
                    degree inconceivable to those who are accustomed to the punctual speed of the
                    post, and had taken ten days for its twelve-miles’ journey. Have my readers any
                    wish to see this <emph>billet-doux</emph>? I can show them (but in strict
                    confidence) a literal copy. It was addressed,</p><!--2017-01-31 ebb: To get floatingText to work, we needed to artifically close the paragraph element here. Ideally we'll close this paragraph after the floatingText element, but for now this will hold us. Check for an oXygen update to the TEI: I think this was something we patched after the latest release of the TEI-All schema. (Same with the second floatingText element below.--><!--2017-02-06: Filed ticket at TEI Council Meeting about floatingText nesting problem. This is a known issue. --><floatingText><body><opener><address><addrLine>“For mistur jem browne</addrLine> <addrLine>“blaxmith by</addrLine> <addrLine>“S.”</addrLine></address></opener></body></floatingText> 
                <p>The inside ran thus:—</p><floatingText><body><p>“Mistur browne this is to Inform yew that oure parish playes
                    bramley men next monday is a week, i think we shall lose without yew. from your
                    humbell servant to command</p> <closer><signed>“<persName ref="#Allen_Mary_OV">Mary Allen</persName>.”</signed></closer></body></floatingText><pb n="159"/>
                <p>Was there ever a prettier relenting? a summons more flattering, more delicate,
                    more irresistible? The precious epistle was undated; but, having ascertained who
                    brought it, and found, by cross-examining the messenger, that the Monday in
                    question was the very next day, we were not surprised to find that <emph>Mistur
                        browne</emph> forgot his engagement to us, forgot all but Mary and Mary’s
                    letter, and set off at four o’clock the next morning to walk twelve miles, and
                    play for her parish and in her sight. Really we must not send James Browne to
                    <placeName ref="#Coventry_City">Coventry</placeName>—must we? Though if, as his sister-in-law tells our damsel Harriet he
                    hopes to do, he should bring the fair Mary home as his bride, he will not
                    greatly care how little we say to him. But he must not be sent to
                    <placeName ref="#Coventry_City">Coventry</placeName>—True-love forbid!</p>
                <p> At last we were all assembled, and marched down to H. common, the appointed
                    ground, which, though in our dominions according to the map, was the constant
                    practising place of our opponents, and <emph>terra incognita</emph> to us. We
                    found our adversaries on the ground as we expected, for our various delays had
                    hindered us from taking the field so early as we wished; and, as soon as we had
                    settled all preliminaries, the match began.</p>
                <p>But, alas! I have been so long settling my preliminaries that I have left myself
                    no room for the detail<pb n="160"/> of our victory, and must squeeze the account
                    of our grand achievements into as little compass as Cowley, when he crammed the
                    names of eleven of his mistresses into the narrow space of four eight-syllable
                    lines. <emph>They</emph> began the warfare—these boastful men of <placeName ref="#B_town_OV">B.</placeName> And what
                    think you, gentle reader, was the amount of their innings? These challengers—the
                    famous eleven—how many did they get? Think! imagine! guess!—You
                    cannot?—Well!—they got twenty-two, or rather they got twenty; for two of theirs
                    were short notches, and would never have been allowed, only that, seeing what
                    they were made of, we and our umpire were not particular.—They should have had
                    twenty more, if they had chosen to claim them. Oh, how well we fielded! and how
                    well we bowled! our good play had quite as much to do with their miserable
                    failure as their bad. <persName ref="#Long_Samuel_OV">Samuel Long</persName> is a slow bowler, <persName ref="#Simmons_George_OV">George Simmons</persName> a fast one,
                    and the change from <persName ref="#Long_Samuel_OV">Long</persName>’s lobbing to Simmons’s fast balls posed them
                    completely. Poor simpletons! they were always wrong, expecting the slow for the
                    quick, and the quick for the slow. Well, we went in. And what were our innings?
                    Guess again!—guess! A hundred and sixty-nine! in spite of soaking showers, and
                    wretched ground, where the ball would not run a yard, we headed them by a
                    hundred and forty-seven; and then they gave in, as well they might. William<pb
                        n="161"/> <persName ref="#Grey_William_OV">Grey</persName> pressed them much to try another innings. <said who="#Grey_William_OV">“There was so much
                    chance,”</said> as he courteously observed, <said who="#Grey_William_OV">“in cricket, that advantageous as our
                    position seemed, we might, very possibly, be overtaken. The B. men had better
                    try.”</said> But they were beaten sulky, and would not move—to my great disappointment;
                    I wanted to prolong the pleasure of success. What a glorious sensation it is to
                    be for five hours together winning—winning—winning! always feeling what a
                    whist-player feels when he takes up four honours, seven trumps! Who would think
                    that a little bit of leather, and two pieces of wood, had such a delightful and
                    delighting power? </p>
                <p>The only drawback on my enjoyment, was the failure of the pretty boy, <persName ref="#Willis_David_OV">David Willis</persName>, who injudiciously put in first, and playing for the first time in a
                    match amongst men and strangers, who talked to him, and stared at him, was
                    seized with such a fit of shamefaced shyness, that he could scarcely hold his
                    bat, and was bowled out, without a stroke, from actual nervousness. <said who="#Coper_Tom_OV">“He will
                    come of that,”</said> <persName ref="#Coper_Tom_OV">Tom Coper</persName> says.—I am afraid he will. I wonder whether <persName ref="#Coper_Tom_OV">Tom</persName> had
                    ever any modesty to lose. Our other modest lad, <persName ref="#Strong_John_OV">John Strong</persName>, did very well; his
                    length told in fielding, and he got good fame. <persName ref="#Brent_Joel_OV">Joel Brent</persName>, the rescued mower,
                    got into a scrape, and out of it again; his fortune for the day. He ran out his
                    mate, <persName ref="#Long_Samuel_OV">Samuel Long</persName>; who, I <pb n="162"/>do believe, but for the excess of <persName ref="#Brent_Joel">Joel Brent</persName>’s
                    eagerness, would have staid in till this time, by which exploit he got into sad
                    disgrace; and then he himself got thirty-seven runs, which redeemed his
                    reputation. <persName ref="#Grey_William_OV">William Grey</persName> made a hit which actually lost the cricket-ball. We
                    think she lodged in a hedge, a quarter of a mile off, but nobody could find her.
                    And <persName ref="#Simmons_George_OV">George Simmons</persName> had nearly lost his shoe, which he tossed away in a passion,
                    for having been caught out, owing to the ball glancing against it. These,
                    together with a very complete somerset of <persName ref="#Appleton_Ben_OV">Ben Appleton</persName>, our long-stop, who
                    floundered about in the mud, making faces and attitudes as laughable as
                    Grimaldi, none could tell whether by accident or design, were the chief
                    incidents of the scene of action. Amongst the spectators nothing remarkable
                    occurred, beyond the general calamity of two or three drenchings, except that a
                    form, placed by the side of a hedge, under a very insufficient shelter, was
                    knocked into the ditch, in a sudden rush of the cricketers to escape a pelting
                    shower, by which means all parties shared the fate of <persName ref="#Appleton_Ben_OV">Ben Appleton</persName>, some on land
                    and some by water; and that, amidst the scramble, a saucy gipsy of a girl
                    contrived to steal, from the knee of the demure and well-apparelled Samuel Long,
                    a smart handkerchief, which his careful dame had tied around it, to preserve his
                    new (what is the mincing feminine word?) his new—inexpressibles;<pb n="163"/>
                    thus reversing the story of Desdemona, and causing the new Othello to call aloud
                    for his handkerchief, to the great diversion of the company. And so we parted;
                    the players retired to their supper, and we to our homes; all wet through, all
                    good-humoured, and all happy—except the losers.</p>
                <p>To-day we are happy too. Hats, with ribands in them, go glancing up and down; and
                    <persName ref="#Grey_William_OV">William Grey</persName> says, with a proud humility, <said who="#Grey_William_OV">“We do not challenge any parish; but,
                    if we be challenged, we are ready.”</said> <pb n="164"/></p>
            </div>



        </body>
        <back>
  
        <div> 
            <listPerson>
                <!--scw 5/15/19: The names below should be cross-referenced with Needham notes or SI if already there.-->
                <person xml:id="Grey_William_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">No info found.</note>
                </person>
                
                <person xml:id="Long_Samuel_OV" sex="m">
                    <note>No information found on this man. The only information found is related to this sketch. He was a cricekter that was a good bowler.</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Brown_James_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">No notes on this man either. The information found is related to this sketch. He was a blacksmtih.</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Hearne_Joseph_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">Possibly a man born in Australia. Died in Windsor and married a woman named Mary Anne Stewart. This info needs verification.</note><!--Unless we can verify for certain that MRM is referring to a historical person, keep the note to the story. Mention the title of the sketch and volume of OV in which he appears, a brief account of what he does in it, as you do for other characters below-->
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Simmons_George_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">The brother of John Simmons. No other info found</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Simmons_John_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">The brother of George Simmons. No other info found.</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Appleton_Ben_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">Again, no information found. The only references to these men seem to be from this sketch itself.</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Harris_George_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">All other information found is about a different George Harris, also a cricket player. No information found about this man.</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Coper_Tom_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">Another cricket player with no information.</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Willis_Robert_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">Another cricketer and blacksmith.</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Strong_John_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">A friend of William Grey's.</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Willis_David_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">Robert Willis' brother.</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Grover_Charles_OV" sex="m">
                    <note resp="#jap">Charles Grover was a man of good judgment in Mitford's town.</note>
                </person>
                <person xml:id="Allen_Mary_OV" sex="f">
                    <note resp="#jap">A woman of M. Followed by James Brown but his advances were repeatedly turned down.</note>
                </person>
            </listPerson>
            
            <listPlace>
                
                <place xml:id="Lords_Cricket_Ground">
                    <placeName>Lord's Cricket Ground</placeName>
                    <location><geo>51.5298 0.1722 </geo></location>
                    <note>A Cricket venue in St. John's Wood, Founded by Thomas Lord.</note>
                </place>
                <place>
                    <place xml:id="Cambridge_Univ">
                        <placeName>Cambridge University</placeName>
                        <note>The University in Cambridge, England. The school was established in 1209.</note>
                    </place>
                </place>
                <place xml:id="Coventry_City">
                    <placeName>Coventry</placeName>
                    <location><geo>52°24'29.0"N 1°30'38.0"W</geo></location>
                    <note>The city in the West Midlands in England.</note>
                </place>
            </listPlace>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="proposed_new_ID4">
                    <title><!--Title--></title>
                    <author><!--Author--></author>
                    <editor><!--if indicated--></editor>
                    <pubPlace><!--where published--></pubPlace>
                    <publisher><!--publisher--></publisher>
                    <date><!--Date. The @when attribute can be yyyy, yyyy-mm, or yyyy-mm-dd.--></date>
                </bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
