<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Publication Information</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Information about the source</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>You will not expect us of course in this weather my dearest friend, but cannot suffer the servant to go into <placeName>Reading</placeName> without aprising you of our regret at being disappointed of our visit <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> particularly laments not being able to meet <persName>William Hayward</persName>, but the roads are in such plight &amp; our cavalry so exceedingly inefficient that to <!--beg>I cannot figure out the word, but she is talking about moving two large vehicles through the mire</--> the Gig &amp; great coach, through the mire would be impossible to say nothing of the live (or dead) weight which the aforesaid great coach would enclose. You must write to me Saturday my own dear <persName>Mary</persName>, &amp; give me the good news of the dear <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName>. I hope <persName>William</persName> will take great care of him at <placeName>Winchester</placeName>. I wish he was not going. You must likewise give me good tidings of poor <persName>Wilson</persName>-how sorry we all were for his accident-but dogs will fight-even my exemplary dog <persName ref="#Mossy">Mossy</persName> pretty nearly killed one of <persName>Mrs. Pile</persName>'s at <placeName>Overton</placeName>. When such a Sir Charles Grandison-<!--beg>Sir Charles Grandison refers to the History of Sir Charles Grandison by Samuel Robinson in 1753, February as found in Wikipediea</-->-sort of dog as <persName ref="#Mossy">Mossy</persName> does such things what can be expected of the less educated race! Bye the bye its great good luck that <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> did not harm him.</p><p>I have just heard from <persName ref="#James_Miss">Miss James</persName> who delivers her most particular love to you all, <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Papa</persName> &amp; Aunt <persName>Mary</persName> included. Some of this letter won't make you laugh. Do come &amp;see it, &amp;see me, &amp;the primroses. Do. Poor <persName ref="#Valpy_Richard">Dr. Valpy</persName>is very ill we are sending to enquire after him. Good bye, my dear loves. Ever yours </p></body></text></TEI>