<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Haydon">B.R. Haydon</persName>, 1823 August 24</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#rct">Rebecca Tang</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#rct">Rebecca Tang</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date/>. Proofing and corrections by: </resp><persName/></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 18 November 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>The Reading Central Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">The Reading Central Library</repository><collection><!-- rct: Need to find which collection these letters are from! --></collection><idno><!-- rct: mansucript/collection numbers still needed. --></idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to B.R. Haydon, <date when="1820-08-24">1820 August 24</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One quarto sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form two octavo pages, which comprise pages 1-4 of the letter.</p><p>Address leaf bearing the following postmarks:<!-- rct: These descriptions should be checked carefully for clarity/accuracy by whomever proofreads this letter. Thanks! -->
                              1) brown elliptical, single rim Receiving House stamp, reading "7 Night 7 August 28, 1823"<stamp/> 2) Sepia-colored T stamp, reading "T.P New<stamp><unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="unclear"/><lb/></stamp></p></support><condition> </condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="pencil" medium="pencil">Someone, apparently other than Mitford (perhaps cataloging the letters and describing them, or marking them up while creating an earlier edition of Mtiford's letters), left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "14" in the top left of the first leaf, underneath the opening line, "To B.R. Haydon Esqr." The fourth and final page of the letter contains the number "3" next to the right side of the mailing address, as well as in front of one of the stamps.</handNote><handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon">Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red diagonal line is drawn from the top left to the bottom right of pages 2 and 3 of the manuscript. On the last page of the letter, there are three red lines drawn from top left to bottom right in each section of the text.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener> To <persName ref="#Haydon">B.R. Haydon Esq<hi rend="superscript">r</hi></persName><add hand="#pencil">14</add><dateline><name type="place">Three Mile Cross</name><date when="1820-08-24">August 24<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>1823</date>. </dateline></opener><p>Yes, my dear Sir, I plead guilty--since I have been a professed Authoress (woe is me! a washerwoman in good practice hath the better trade) since that misfortune had befallen me I have become a very shabby correspondent &amp; run the risk of appearing ungrateful to those whose favours I value most--but I will amend &amp; pay you in quantity for the time to come--to pay you in quality I do not promise--who can?--I am not however quite to bad as I must have appeared, for I did write a note of most sincere &amp; heartfelt congratulation to you &amp; <persName ref="#Haydon_Mrs">Mrs. Haydon</persName> on your release--Did you receive it? Owing to my having unluckily mislaid your penultimate letter--Oh pedantry of pedantries! word bluer than indigo! I hope it is wrong that beautiful letter which I would not lose for an Ingot--added to my faculty of forgetting every thing in the shape of a figure (the multiplication table &amp; the English Chronology were the torments of my Schooldays--I never got beyond the Twices in one &amp; the Williams <note resp="#rct">Up until Mitford's time, there had been a total of three King Williams in England: William the Conqueror (c. 1028-1087), William II, aka William Rufus (c. 1056-1100), and William III, aka William of Orange (1650-1702).</note> in the other--from these two causes I misdirected my note putting as I believe 18 for 0 <unclear unit="number" quantity="1" reason="unclear"/>(I only wonder I came to hear) &amp; you being a new Inhabitant would most likely not receive it--Did you?--There was nothing in the blotted paper except our most sincere felicitations--&amp; that assurance of sucess which burns within me whenever I think of you--especially since your</p><pb n="2"/><p>last equally noble &amp; prudent resolutions--which are really &amp; truly in the <persName ref="#Napoleon">Napoleon</persName> spirit--his best spirit. I am so glad that we think alike of that great man--What you say of your observant is <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>hardly<add place="above">very</add></del>distressing--such ingratitude destroys the blessed faith in human Nature which is necessary to our happiness &amp; almost to our virtue.--With respect to Mr. Berrick I cannot but hope &amp; believe that you will find some extenuating circumstances--something to soften &amp; paliate--some mistake or mis-statement--I cannot will not imagine other of one who seemed so interesting &amp; amiable--so connected with the finest parts of your finest pictures--so much a part of you! Oh you will find it as I say I am me--a man's countenance cannot tell just sad fibs as his word do otherwise.--I am heartily glad to hear of Mr. Chatfield's constancy--but what fools they must be that act <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del>unkindly--their heads must be as much at fault as their hearts not to see that <add place="above"><metamark place="above" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>to have been</add>your pupils is &amp; will be their best title let them paint as well as they may. I am as me of your carrying your point, as I am of finishing this letter both events being, humanly appeatring, certain--We may each of us die first to be nice--but the chances are undoubtedly <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="2" unit="word"/></del><add place="above">a million to one</add>in favour of our accomplishing our objects. Let me know what subject you think of taking for your next picture--Where nothing in which <persName ref="#Haydon_Mrs">Mrs. Haydon</persName> &amp; the Little one could be introduced? To set models!</p><pb n="3"/><p>Pray are you a Cricketer?--We are very great Ones--I mean our Parish--of which we the feminine members act audience, &amp; "though we do not play o'erlook the" babes. When I wrote to you last I was just going to see a grand match in a fire outback near us--<placeName>Bramshill</placeName>--between <placeName>Hampshire</placeName>, with <persName ref="#Budd_EH">Mr. Budd</persName>, &amp; All <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>--anticipating great pleasure from so grand exhibition &amp; thinking like a simpleton the better the play the more the enjoyment. Oh what a mistake! there they were a set of ugly men white headed &amp; bald headed (for half of Lord's was engaged in the combat, players &amp; gentlemen <persName ref="#Ward_William">Mr. Ward</persName>&amp; <persName ref="#Beauclerk_Frederick">Lord Frederick</persName>, the veterans of the queen)--dressed in tight white jackets (the <rs type="art" ref="#Apollo_Belvedere">Apollo <choice><sic>Belvidere</sic><reg>Belvedere</reg></choice></rs> could not bear the hideous disguise of a cricketing jacket) with neckcloths <gap reason="torn" quantity="2" unit="chars"/><unclear><supplied resp="rct">pr</supplied></unclear>imly tied round their <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del> fine japan<gap reason="torn" quantity="3" unit="chars"/><unclear><supplied resp="rct">ned</supplied></unclear> shoes silk <gap reason="torn" quantity="1" unit="chars"/><unclear><supplied resp="rct">s</supplied></unclear>tockings &amp; gloves--instead of our pine village lads with their unbuttoned collars their loose waistcoats &amp; the large shirtsleeves which give an air of picturesque &amp; Italian <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del>to their glowing bounding youthfulness--there they should sailed in by their low silent, solemn, slow, playing for money making a business of the thing--grave as judges--facitious as chess players--<add place="above"><metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/>a sort of</add>dancers without music--instead of the glee, the fun, the shouts, the laughter the glorious confusion of the country game--And there were we the lookers on in tents and marquees, fine &amp; peering, dull as the players, cold as this <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del>hard summer weather, shivering &amp; yawning &amp; trying to seem pleased.</p><pb n="4"/><p>The curse of gentility on all one doing, as stupid as we could have been in a ballroom. I never was so much disappointed in my life. But every thing is spoilt when Money puts its ugly nose in. To think of playing cricket for hard cash!--Money &amp; gentility would <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del><add place="above">pish</add>any pastime under the sun. Much to my comfort (for the degrading my favourite sport in a "science" as they were pleased to call it had made me quite spiteful) the game ended undisatisfactorily to all parties--winners &amp; losers. Old <persName ref="#Beauclerk_Frederick">Lord Frederick</persName>on some real or imaginary affront took himself off in the middle of the second Innings--so that the two last <gap reason="smudged" quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear><supplied>were</supplied></unclear> played without him, by which means his <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/></del>side lost &amp; the other could hardly be said to win. So be it always when men make an affair of bettings &amp; hedgings &amp; cheating may be of the noble game of cricket.</p><closer><lb/>--And how God bless you--Kindest regards &amp; best wishes from all--Ever your's <signed><persName ref="#MRM">MR Mitford</persName></signed><lb/><address><addrLine>To</addrLine><addrLine><persName ref="#Haydon">B.R. Haydon Esqre</persName></addrLine><addrLine>8 Paddington Green</addrLine><addrLine>near the Church</addrLine><addrLine>Paddington</addrLine></address></closer></div></body><back><div type="historical_people"><listPerson type="hist"><person xml:id="Beauclerk_Frederick" sex="1"><persName>Reverend Lord Frederick Beauclerk</persName><persName><forename>Frederick</forename><surname>Beauclerk</surname></persName><birth when="1773-05-08"/><death when="1850-04-22"/><occupation>cricketer</occupation><note type="bio" resp="#rct">The fourth son of the <persName ref="#Beauclerk_Aubrey">Duke of St. Albans</persName>and a descendant of <persName ref="#Chas_II">Charles II</persName>and <persName ref="#Gwyn_Eleanor">Nell Gwyn</persName>, Lord Frederick was a first-class cricketer who played for the <orgName ref="#Marylebone_Cricket_Club">Marylebone Cricket Club</orgName>for almost thirty-five years. He was also a clergyman, the Vicar of <placeName ref="#St_Michaels_Church_St_Albans">St. Michael's Church at St. Albans</placeName>in 1828. Lord Frederick was a controversial figure during his time, notorious for his gambling and cantankerous personality.</note></person></listPerson><listPerson><person xml:id="Budd_EH" sex="1"><persName>Edward Hayward Budd</persName><persName><forename>Edward</forename><forename>Hayward</forename><surname>Budd</surname></persName><birth when="1786-02-23"/><death when="1875-03-29"/><occupation>cricketer</occupation><note type="bio" resp="#rct">Budd was a noted English cricketer, versatile in all of the positions in the sport. He made his first-class debut with the <orgName ref="#Marylebone_Cricket_Club">Marylebone Cricket Club</orgName> in 1804, continuing to play until 1831.</note></person></listPerson><listPerson><person xml:id="Ward_William" sex="1"><persName>William Ward</persName><persName><forename>William</forename><surname>Ward</surname></persName><birth when="1787-07-24"/><death when="1849-06-30"/><occupation>Member of Parliament</occupation><note type="bio" resp="#rct">Ward was a Member of Parliament for the City of <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName> from 1826 to around 1831. He was also a noted cricketer, having played with the <orgName ref="#Marylebone_Cricket_Club">Marylebone Cricket Club</orgName> from 1815 to 1840.</note></person></listPerson><listPerson><person xml:id="Beauclerk_Aubrey" sex="1"><persName>Aubrey Beauclerk, 5th Duke of St. Albans</persName><persName><forename>Aubrey</forename><surname>Beauclerk</surname></persName><birth when="1740-06-03"/><death when="1802-02-09"/><occupation>landowner</occupation><note type="bio" resp="#rct">A grandson of <persName ref="#Beauclerk_Charles_I">Charles Beauclerk, 1st Duke of St. Albans</persName>, Aubrey Beauclerk was the father of <persName ref="#Beauclerk_Frederick">Lord Frederick Beauclerk</persName>.</note></person></listPerson><listPerson><person xml:id="Gwyn_Eleanor" sex="2"><persName>Eleanor "Nell" Gwyn</persName><persName><forename>Eleanor</forename><surname>Gwyn</surname></persName><birth when="1650-02-02"/><death when="1687-11-14"/><occupation>mistress</occupation><note type="bio" resp="#rct">Nell Gwyn was a long-time mistress to <persName ref="#ChasII">Charles II of England</persName>. She was also the mother of Charles Beauclerk, 1st Duke of St. Albans.</note></person></listPerson><listPerson><person xml:id="Beauclerk_Charles_I" sex="1"><persName>Charles Beauclerk, 1st Duke of St. Albans</persName><persName><forename>Charles</forename><surname>Beauclerk</surname></persName><birth when="1670-05-08"/><death when="1726-05-10"/><occupation>duke</occupation><note type="bio" resp="#rct">The illegitimate son of <persName ref="#ChasII">Charles II</persName> and <persName ref="#Gwyn_Eleanor">Nell Gwyn</persName>, Charles Beauclerk was the first duke of St. Albans. He is the ancestor of <persName ref="#Beauclerk_Frederick">Lord Frederick Beauclerk</persName>.</note></person></listPerson></div><div type="organization"><listOrg><org xml:id="Marylebone_Cricket_Club"><orgName>Marylebone Cricket Club</orgName><note resp="#rct">Founded in <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>in 1787, the Marylebone Cricket Club is the world's largest cricket brand.</note></org></listOrg></div><div type="places"><listPlace><place xml:id="Bramshill_city"><placeName>Bramshill</placeName><note resp="#rct">A civil parish in the county of <placeName ref="#Hampshire_county">Hampshire</placeName>.</note></place></listPlace><listPlace><place xml:id="Hampshire_county"><placeName>Hampshire</placeName><note resp="#rct">The county where <persName ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</persName> was born. It is situated in the south of <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>, roughly halfway between the east and west ends of the South Coast.</note></place></listPlace><listPlace><place xml:id="St_Michaels_Church_St_Albans"><placeName>St. Michael's Church, St. Albans</placeName><note resp="#rct">A parish church located at St. Albans, a city in <placeName ref="#Hertfordshire_county">Hertfordshire</placeName>,<placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>.</note></place></listPlace><listPlace><place xml:id="Hertfordshire_county"><placeName>Hertfordshire</placeName><note resp="#rct">A county in southeast <placeName ref="#England">England</placeName>.</note></place></listPlace></div><div type="art" org="uniform" sample="complete"><list type="art"><item/><figure xml:id="Apollo_Belvedere" type="sculpture" rend="marble"><bibl><title>Apollo Belvedere</title></bibl><graphic url="http://www.pbase.com/bmcmorrow/image/115469993"/><desc/><note resp="#rct">A marble sculpture from ancient Greece, rediscovered near Rome in the late 15th century. Believed to have been created around 120-150 AD, the sculpture is a copy of the bronze original by the Greek sculptor Leochares from the 4th century B.C. It depicts the Greek god Apollo in a position of just releasing an arrow from a bow, the latter originally held in his left hand.</note></figure></list></div></back></text></TEI>