<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Haydon">B.R. Haydon</persName>, 1820 September
              1</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><editor ref="#err">Elizabeth Raisanen</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#err">Elizabeth Raisanen</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: <date/>. Proofing and corrections by: </resp><persName/></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 11 August 2014. P5.</edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>The Reading Central
                 Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                 License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">The Reading Central Library</repository><collection><!-- err: Need to find which collection these letters are from! --></collection><idno><!-- err: mansucript/collection numbers still needed. --></idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to B.R. Haydon, <date when="1820-09-01">1820
                 September 1</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One quarto sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form
                             two octavo pages, which comprise pages 1-4 of the letter. The fifth
                             page bears the end of the letter one side, and (after being folded
                             into four panels) exposes the address on the other side.</p><p>Address leaf bearing the following
                             postmarks:<!-- err: These descriptions should be checked carefully for clarity/accuracy by whomever proofreads this letter. Thanks! -->
                             1) black elliptical Receiving House stamp<stamp><unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="illegible"><supplied resp="#err">Reading</supplied></unclear><lb/><unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/><lb/><unclear unit="word" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/><lb/><unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/></stamp> 2) Sepia-colored oval
                             stamp that is split in two, appearing at opposite ends of the address
                             leaf page (the seal was divided after the letter was opened). The top
                             half of the stamp reads as follows: <stamp>10 o' Cl</stamp> The bottom
                             half of the stamp is nearly illegible: <stamp><unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/><lb/><unclear unit="word" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/></stamp></p></support><condition> </condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="pencil" medium="pencil">Someone, apparently other than Mitford
              (perhaps cataloging the letters and describing them, or marking them up while
              creating an earlier edition of Mtiford's letters), left grey pencil marks and
              numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is
              numbered "15" in the top left of the first leaf, underneath the opening line, "To B.
              R. Haydon Esqr." In what appears to be the same hand and the same pencil, the year
              "1820" appears faintly at the bottom of the fifth page of the letter. The same color
              pencil also appears as a vertical line in the lower-right margin of page 3 of the
              letter, and continues as a vertical line in the left margin of page 4 that runs from
              the top to the bottom of the page.</handNote><handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon">Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a
              different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing
              diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing wo rds overtop and perpendicularly
              across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red diagonal line is drawn from the top
              left to the bottom right of pages 2, 3, 4, and 5 of the manuscript. On the first page
              of the letter, there is a faint red line that is somewhat closer to vertical than
              diagonal drawn from the middle-right of the page down and to the left to the bottom
              of the page.</handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
              end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
              spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
              searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
              Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
              following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
              ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline>April 23rd, 1823</dateline><salute>My Dear Friend,</salute></opener><p>I am but just returned from Town, whither I have been led by one of the evil consequences of dramatic Authorship--that is to say a false report--&amp;lose not a moment in writing to you to thank you for your zealous kindness, &amp;to say how heartily we sympathise in all your feelings. I have no time to tell you the story of the strange mistake which led me to London--no heart to talk to you of plays &amp;theatres--for my very soul is sick of them all -- they mean to be kind I believe all of them -- but between the lies &amp; the quarrels &amp; <pb n="2"/> and the envy that attends merely I have fairly xx a thousand times that the play had failed. Do we tell this - that really my soul xx within me when I think of the turmoil of tumult which i have undergone -I am to undergo - for Charles Kemble will not infer the to withdraw my tragedy of the xx, and threaten he with a lawsuit if I do. In the meantime, I am xx about between him I xx like a wicked bale, xx both xx, and xx by both xx xx not come to a deadly xx with xx are imagine what a xx this is for one who valed and quietly beyond every other xx of life! - In the meantime they have spot Julian at the end of the eighth night though it was <pb n="3"/> going brilliantly to brilliant houses - &amp; (but this is quite between ourselves) not paid me for the third and sixth nights - To be sure I have Charles Kemble's personal words -- &amp;and I believe him to be an honest man - but to undergo all this misery &amp; not get my money would be terrible indeed! To xx all the xx Hamilton from xx had affronted above forty xx in my debt - oh who would be an xx! The only confront is that the xx can't go on without me, and that the very job they make is xx over xx at the theatre moved my xx there - to that if I xx there xxxx, I had in their xx something floor xxxxxx. <pb n="4"/> Children then wonder these xx does and interminable xx and this unwomanly publicity xx xx xx </p><p>Well I write xx of this xx I have nothing xx to death of xx for though I have been in town xx I have been to Englifrew Jabroubee by their distracting commons? That I have lost all conuiction of anything xx better xx How have something to send you in a month or two for I ahve been sitting for my portrait to be engraved at the desire of my Mother. I hope xx that you are all as well xx as you can be xx for everything to yourself and your brother and his xx all who are to good to know your family the may convey most? of gratitude toward Kathy and the good wishes I hope for continuing a while continue better xx has been my dear friend xx Ever your faithfully yours, </p><p><pb n="5"/>It is very strange that xx about to request you to xx your letter to the who is xx friend as to give the xx his xx is xx xx xx May forgive this lad no letter! Alas the free and happy xx when xx lead xx this. xx prattle for you are for away! Oh write they ever xx! I xx here chained to a desk, 10, 12 hours a day xx at xx of writing for xx money xx correspondence on how xx on pite the ! Pity xx very kind is under the fatigue and the anziety xx God help you my dear friend. xx Forgive this xx</p><closer><lb/>Faithfully your's<lb/><signed>xx. Mitford.</signed><lb/><address><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Edford</persName></address></closer></div></body></text></TEI>