<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Letter to <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">George Mitford</persName>, 1823 April
               3</title><author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author><author ref="#Russell_M"> Mary Mitford</author><editor ref="#tnh">Toni Hays</editor><sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor><sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor><principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal><respStmt><resp>Transcription and coding by</resp><persName ref="#tnh">Toni Hays</persName></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Date last checked: 23 February 2015<date/>. Proofing and corrections by </resp><persName>Rebecca Tang</persName><persName/></respStmt></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 11 August 2014. P5.</edition><respStmt><orgName>The Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> editors' photos from this archive are not permitted for public distribution.<!--ebb: This will be the case for most of our archive photos. We can remove the "not permitted for public distribution" phrase from Reading CL letters, since we are permitted to post these.--> Photo files: <idno>3April1823GeorgeMitford1a.JPG, 3April1823GeorgeMitford2.JPG, 3April1823GeorgeMitford3.JPG, 3April1823GeorgeMitford4.JPG</idno></resp></respStmt></editionStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority><pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace><date>2014</date><availability><p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName>The Reading Central
                  Library</placeName>.</p><licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence></availability></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><msDesc><msIdentifier><repository ref="#ReadingCL">The Reading Central Library</repository><collection><!-- err: Need to find which collection these letters are from! --></collection><idno><!-- err: mansucript/collection numbers still needed. --></idno></msIdentifier><head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to George Mitford, <date when="1823-04-03">1823
                  April 3</date>.</head><physDesc><objectDesc><supportDesc><support><p>One quarto sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form two octavo pages, which
                              comprise pages 1-4 of the letter. The fourth page exposes the address with some of Mitford's
                              mother's writing at the top of the page. The third page has a slight rip where the wax seal was
                              attached. Also, beneath the address to George Mitford is another address to a Miss Foote, an
                              actress in Mitford's play <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian.</title></p><p>Address leaf bearing the following postmarks:<!-- tnh: These descriptions of the stamps should be
                              checked carefully for clarity/accuracy by whomever proofreads this as the postage is actually
                              quite faint! -->
                              1) black circular Mileage stamp<stamp><unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="illegible"><supplied resp="#tnh">Reading</supplied></unclear><lb/><unclear unit="word" quantity="2" reason="illegible"/><supplied>AP 23</supplied><lb/><unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/><supplied>1823</supplied><lb/><unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="illegible"/></stamp> 
                              2) Red double-circle duty stamp <stamp><unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="illegible"><supplied resp="#tnh">B</supplied></unclear><lb/><unclear unit="word" quantity="3" reason="illegible"><supplied resp="#tnh">23 APR 
                                    23</supplied></unclear><lb/><unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="illegible"><supplied>1823</supplied></unclear></stamp></p><p>A large 7 denoting a fee for a single-sheet letter has been written in black ink by the postal service across the address leaf.</p></support><condition> </condition></supportDesc></objectDesc><sealDesc><p>Red wax seal.</p></sealDesc></physDesc></msDesc></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><handNotes><handNote xml:id="handshift"> Mary Russell begins her own quick note to George Mitford follwing the content of her  
               daughter's letter. The note is a quick one and extends to  page 4 of the letter--on the same side as the same 
               page used to address the letter. Mary Russell's note is particularly concerned about George Mitford's health and 
               his recovery from a cold. </handNote><handNote xml:id="rc" medium="red_crayon">Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a
               different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing
               diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly
               across Mitford's writing. On this letter, two red diagonal lines are drawn one at the top
               left and the other at middle-right of the page. On page 3, there is a red crayon mark across the page from the top left corner to the bottom right. Also on page three, lines 9 through 14 are underlined. 
               of the letter, there is a faint red line that is somewhat closer to vertical than diagonal drawn from the middle-right of the page down and to the left to the bottom of the page.</handNote><handNote> On page 3, there is a rip where the wax seal once help the letter together. This manifests as a rip through Ms. Mary Russell Mitford's signature.</handNote><handNote>On page 4 there is another address to <persName>Miss Foote</persName> at 34 Keppele Lane in Russell Square. She was an actress who originated in the breeches role of Alfonso in Mitford's play, <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian</title>.</handNote><handNote>The word written at the bottom left hand corner of the address leaf to George Mitford <unclear unit="word" quantity="1" reason="cross-out"><supplied resp="#tnh">Engle</supplied></unclear></handNote></handNotes></profileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p></editorialDecl></encodingDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div type="letter"><opener><dateline><name type="place"><placeName>Old Betty's Chop House <note resp="#tnh"><p>According to <title>Imperial London</title> by <persName>Arthur Henry Beavan</persName>, <placeName>Old Betty's Chop House</placeName> was a tavern along <placeName>the Strand</placeName>. This tavern was close to the theatres at <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre">Covent Garden</placeName> and <placeName ref="#Drury_Lane_Theatre">Drury Lane</placeName></p></note></placeName></name><date when="1823-04-03">April 3, 1823 </date></dateline><salute>At last <rs type="person" ref="#Mitford_Geo">my dearest Father</rs></salute></opener><p><persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd's</persName> answer is come--He says that we are <del rend="cross out">--</del> bound in honor &amp; and not to take the Play away from one house and give it to another--that we can not answer it to ourselves or the Publisher--un--less some very outrageous conduct on the part of the Committee or <!--tnh:which kemble is this <supplied> Charles Kemble</supplied>!--><persName> Mr. Kemble</persName> (which certainly in spite of our vexations have not occurred &amp; I hope will not occur) should afford a sufficient &amp; valid season. This is final--I only wish it had arrived two days ago --I have also a letter from <persName>Mr. Hamilton</persName>, backing out of the message which he certainly delivered to me <del rend="cross out"/> the next season--I have no doubt in spite of this letter from the few words that passed between <persName ref="#Elliston_Robt"> Mr. Elliston</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Macready_Wm"> Mr. Macready</persName>, that the Play would <!--tnh:unclear word!--> be brought out at <placeName ref="#Drury_Lane_Theatre"> Drury Lane</placeName> if we liked--<del rend="cross out"/> but after what <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">Mr. Talfourd</persName> has said it would be much better not to think of it--Indeed it is impossible to think of it, for I am sure he would feel himself offended &amp; implicated if we did-- <del rend="cross out"/> In my own part, I am heartily glad not to have again to encounter this terrible enmity &amp; malignity of Magazines &amp; newspapers--My <!--tnh:unsure of word!--> play--If we have courage &amp;<!--tnh: unsure of word!--> to another, <!--tnh: unsure of word!--> have no name, no woman to attack. I am sure that<title ref="#LondonMag">The London Magazine </title> must be very mad indeed,for <persName> Miss Andrews</persName> requesting her to sent it to me by the Postman this morning, has not sent it <note resp="#tnh">Here Mitford's premonistions are correct. In the particular edition of The London Magazine she speaks of, the critic eviscerates the performance of Mr. Marcready, while admiring the work of Mitford's writing in it of itself</note>. Can you at all guess who wrote it? <unclear unit="word" quantity="1"><supplied resp="#tnh"><persName ref="#Procter_BW">Mr. Procter</persName></supplied></unclear> used to 
            <pb n="2"/> write the dramatic article in that magazine--but we must not suspect him--even though I know how <persName>Mr. Kemble</persName> conversation suspecting him &amp; <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName>that he has joined managerial faction.--well we must endure it as we may. What you say of <persName ref="#Macready_Wm"> Mr. Macready's</persName> indisposition grieves me very much I hope if he be not quite removed that he will not think of going through the terrible fatigue of acting Julian to night. Have you given him my letter? I hope not--if you had any previous conversation with<persName>Mr. Hamilton</persName>you would not--if you have not bring it back to me.--if you have I shall write a <!--tnh: not sure of word!--> tomorrow--when I shall probably hear whether you have met. <!--tnh: code for an extended space!--> Mr. Talfourd advises that <del rend="scribbled out"/> Forscari be left for the present at <placeName ref="#Covent_Garden_Theatre"> Convent Garden</placeName> &amp; I agree that it shall--but not to be acted with <persName ref="#Macready_Wm"> Mr. Macready</persName> for the Doge--never that--he will rely on my <!--tnh: appearances?!--> on that point I know.--Pray ascertain whether the dedication copy has been sent to him &amp; whether the copies have been sent to the theatre, for all the Performers, the lady &amp; gentle--man who spoke the Prologue &amp; Epilogue--The Commitee <unclear unit="word" quantity="2"/> --all with the Author's compliments &amp; thanks--I beg you, wile also send one to <persName>Miss Howell</persName>--&gt;at I. Sheppherd's Esquire <placeName>Hampstead Heath</placeName>--one to <persName>Mr. Mar<!--tnh:not sure of the rest!--></persName>--&amp; one to <persName>Miss <unclear unit="word" quantity="1"><supplied resp="#tnh">Booth</supplied></unclear></persName> &amp; another to <persName ref="#Rowden_Fr">Mrs. Rowden</persName>through<persName>Mr. Jones</persName> if he will take charge of  them to <placeName>Paris</placeName>--And pray try to find out who wrote the Article in London--<persName>Mr. <unclear unit="word" quantity="1"><supplied resp="#tnh">Southern</supplied></unclear></persName>, at the <persName ref="#Hofland_B">Hofland's</persName> <!--tnh: Hofland's is the name of a resident, should it be a place or a person?!--> is likely to know--you will make my kindest
             <pb n="3"/>regards there of <!--tnh:not sure!-->notif you are in that neighborhood call &amp; ask after dear<persName>Miss Porden</persName> I hope your cold is better--my cough is going fast Dear<persName ref="#Russell_M">mama</persName> is better too--&amp; everything else is well I have just found out what killed my geraniums They had not been watered I am <!--tnh:not sure!--> since past them away till they come back again &amp; then the water ran through the cracked earth as hard as a rock &amp; did not good--I have been working at them all morning poor things.--We have not been the <!--tnh: not sure!--> or any one but <persName>Miss Brooke</persName> who is gone to <!--tnh:not sure!--> this morning. Pray do not forget to bring a pot of the white paint without smell &amp; another of black would really write another play to get this room made decent without offense to <persName ref="#Russell_M">Mama</persName>. God bless you my own dearest <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Father</persName>--<lb/></p><closer><lb/>Ever most fondly your's<lb/><signed> MR M <del rend="torn"/></signed><lb/><address><addrLine>To <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">George Mitford Esqre</persName></addrLine><addrLine>Old Betty's Chop House</addrLine><addrLine>No. 415 Strand</addrLine><addrLine><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName></addrLine></address></closer><postscript><p>--<persName>Miss Barnes</persName> says she wrote to me by return of post--so that she must have been lost--or perhaps misoriented for she is very abstract. She talks of being back in a fortnight but not this way--&amp; wants me to secure her a box for <emph rend="underline">them</emph>.--as if I ever dared look forward in that way. God bless you.</p><p><handShift/>The following enlightened Epistle came from <placeName ref="#Winchester_city">Winchester</placeName> by way of<placeName ref="#Coley_Berks">Coley</placeName>this morning. My dear friend on the receipt of your newspaper I immediately wrote to you <!--tnh:not sure!--> of any delight at the successful result of <title ref="#Julian_MRMplay">Julian</title>, which <!--tnh: not sure!--> I trust reached its destination. This I mention because out servant Boy might as we suppose have negelcted to put the letter in the Post. I have only to repeat out congratulation, many thanks for the Publication.</p><p>Is there a prospect of seeing you. Our best love to all</p><p>Ever yours in Haste <persName>John Woodburn</persName><placeName ref="#Winchester_city"> Winchester</placeName> March 29th I am rejoiced my dear <persName ref="#Mitford_Geo">Husband</persName>to find your cold was better you had a beautiful day for your Journey I can <pb n="4"/>We shall send in<persName>Henry</persName>in the morning for the Parcel by the Regulator. Us you may be certain we shall very axious to get it. God bless you ever &amp; ever<lb/>I cannot see most truly yours<lb/><persName ref="#Russell_M"> Mary Mitford</persName></p></postscript></div></body></text></TEI>