<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html>
   <head>
      <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
      <meta name="Description"
            content="Supported by the University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg and the Mary Russell Mitford Society."/>
      <meta name="keywords"
            content="Mitford, Mary Russell Mitford, Digital Mitford, Digital Mary Russell Mitford, Digital Mary Russell Mitford Archive, Mitford Archive, digital edition, electronic edition, electronic text, Romanticism, Romantic literature, Victorianism, Victorian literature, humanities computing, electronic editing, Beshero-Bondar"/>
      <link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="mitfordletter.css"/>
      <script type="text/javascript" src="MRMLetters.js" xml:space="preserve">...</script>
   </head>
   <body>
      <div id="title">
         <h1>Digital Mitford: Letters</h1>
         <hr/>
      </div>
      <div id="menubar">
         <h2>
            <a href="index.html">Welcome</a> | <a href="about.html">About</a> | <a href="search.html">Search</a> | <a href="literature.html">Literary
                            Works</a> | <a href="letters.html">Letters</a> | <a href="visual.html">People, Places, and Networks</a> | <a href="maps.html">Maps</a> | <a href="contact.html">Contact</a> | <a href="workshop.html">Workshop
                                        Materials</a>
         </h2>
      </div>
      <hr/>
      <div id="container">
         <div id="letterHead">
            <div id="fieldset">
               <fieldset>
                  <legend>
                     <span class="dipNorm">Our default is the Diplomatic view.<br/> Click to toggle the Normalized view</span>
                     <span class="dipNormSmall"> (shows conventional spellings;<br/> hides pagebreaks, insertion marks, and deletions):</span>
                  </legend>
                  <input type="checkbox" id="REGtoggle" style="cursor:pointer"/>
                  <br/>
               </fieldset>
            </div>
            <h3>Letter to <span class="person">Sir William Elford</span>, 22 March 1821</h3>
            <p>Edited by Lisa M. Wilson. </p>Sponsored by: <ul>
               <li>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</li>
               <li>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</li>
            </ul>
            <a href="file:/C:/Users/ebb8/Desktop/My%20Box%20Files/MRMS%20Project%20Support/Folder-of-Chaos/15-23_June-2014_NewFiles/1821-03-22-Elford.xml">First digital edition in TEI, date: 10 June 2014. P5.</a>
            <p>Published by: Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive, Greensburg, PA, USA: 2013. </p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <span class="place">Reading Central Library</span>. <p>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</p>
            <p>Repository: Reading Central Library. Shelf mark: MS number</p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
              end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
              spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
              searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
              Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
              following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
              ligatured forms are not encoded.</div>
         <div id="floatright">
            <div id="letter">
               <div id="opener">March 22.<br/> 1821.<br/>
                  <br/>
               </div>
               <p>
                  <span class="prose">Oh, my dear <span class="person">Sir William,</span> I don't suppose I shall ever have the comfort &amp; amusement of writing a long letter again! "First recover that, &amp; than thou shalt hear 'farther.'"<span id="N1" class="anchor">[1] <span class="note" id="n1">Mitford quotes from The Revenge by Edward Young (1721) (I.i.24-25. Zanoa:  "To strike thee with astonishment at once,/I hate Alonzo. First recover that,/And then thou shalt hear farther."—#lmw</span>
                     </span> I am so busy.  Since I came back from <span class="place">London</span> I have written a <span class="title">Tragedy</span> on the subject of <span class="person">Fiesco</span> the Genoese Nobleman who conspired against <span class="person">Doria</span>--the story is beautifully told in <span class="person">Robertson</span>'s <span class="title">Charles the Fifth</span>--This <span class="title">Tragedy</span> is now in <span class="person">Mr. Macready</span>'s hands--I suppose I shall hear in a day or two that its rejected--&amp; the moment I hear that I shall fall to ding dong &amp; write another.  For I have an inward consciousness that any little talent I may have is altogether dramatic and having placed before my eyes the example of <span class="person">Mr. Tobin</span> whose <span class="title">Honeymoon</span> was produced after <em>eleven</em> other Plays <span class="caret">^</span>
                     <span class="add">of his composing</span>had been rejected (I don't mean to follow his example in dying though before my successful Play is brought out) I am determined to persevere &amp; to write a good Tragedy at last even if I previously write eleven bad ones.  This I am resolved on. In the mean time I am writing for the magazines--Poetry criticism &amp; Dramatic Sketches--I work as hard as a lawyer's clerk &amp; besides the natural loathing of pen &amp; ink which that sort of drudgery cannot fail to inspire I have really at present scarcely a moment to spare even to the violets and primroses. You would laugh if you saw me puzzling over my prose--You have no notion how much difficulty I find in writing any thing at all readable.  One cause of this is my having been so egregious a letter writer--I have accustomed myself to a certain careless sauciness, a fluent incorrectness which passed very well with indulgent Friends such as yourself, my dear <span class="person">Sir William</span> but will not do at all for that tremendous Correspondent the Public--so I ponder over every <span class="del"> </span>phrase<span class="pagebreak">page 2<br/>
                     </span>--disjoint every sentence &amp; finally produce such lumps of awkwardness I really expect instead of paying me for them <span class="person">Mr. Colburn</span> &amp; <span class="person">Mr. Baldwin</span> will send me back the trash. But I will improve. This is another resolution which is as fixed as fate.--Well--I am now going to make a strange request--Will you my dear Friend have the goodness to <em>lend</em> me those letters of mine which you have taken the trouble to keep. I am not going to publish them--of that you may be sure. But without partaking of your kind delusion as to their merits I am aware that there are in them occasional passages &amp; expressions which being written in the first freshness of feeling &amp; with perfect ease &amp; unrestraint are more effervescent &amp; sparkling as well as more just than any thing I am likely to write now with the fear of the Public before my eyes. For instance I want to write an essay on <span class="person">Miss Austen</span>'s novels, which are by no means valued <span class="del"> </span>as they deserve--indeed are never mentioned or thought of amongst good writers--&amp; I am sure I should find better materials in my letters to you written just after I read them than I should be able to compound<span class="del"> </span>from my own recollection. Of course I am not going to print them in the form of letters or to have any allusion to names or persons.  All that I intend is to select any happy expressions (if I chance to find any)--or any vivid descriptions--<span class="del"> </span> to steal from myself, as it were; &amp; if you my dear <span class="person">Sir William,</span> will condescend to be an accessory before the fact in this petty larceny, I shall be most obliged to you.  You can bring the letters with you, for I shall depend on seeing you in our smoky den though I am rather ashamed of its dirt &amp; dinginess--(I <span class="pagebreak">page 3<br/>
                     </span>mean to send <span class="person">Mama</span> off to <span class="place"/>Winchester, She can't bear paint,) &amp; to have it whitened &amp; tidied up this summer)--but you must let us have a sight of you, for my going to <span class="place">Town</span> is very uncertain--It depends on my <span class="title">Play</span>, &amp; I have no hopes of its being accepted--&amp; when I give myself a few days holidays it will probably be later in the year, &amp; my head quarters will be <span class="place">Richmond</span>
                     <span class="place">Twickenham</span>
                     <span class="place">Kew</span>--I have many friends in those parts--to say nothing of <span class="person">Miss James</span>--so you must come, just to satisfy yourself that I am fatter &amp; rosier than than ever in spite of my quill driving, &amp; as gay as a lark my tragedies notwithstanding.--What you say about <span class="title">Kenilworth</span> &amp; about <span class="title">Curiosity</span> is very just &amp; true--but if the catastrophe were offered a thousand times over it would not alter the powerful impression made on my mind my such a dissection of the wicked human heart.--Have you read <span class="person">Mr. Nicholl</span>'s <span class="title">Recollections of the Reign of George the Third</span> (I am not sure that this is the title) It seems to me the most extraordinary isntance of fairness &amp; impartiality in an old party man that I ever met with &amp; is amusing to boot.  To be sure if <span class="del"> </span>a man of 76 &amp; stone blind, be not impartial one does not know where to look for that rare quality.  Of course you won't disagree with him in many points--so do I--but the general rightmindedness is astonishing.--<span class="person">Mr. Haydon</span> &amp; his bright eyes are at <span class="place">Glasgow</span>--His money ?? [lender?] was very ill--dying--So he was forced to set off at a day's warning to take care of his concerns there--leaving <span class="title">the Resurrection of Lazarus</span> to take care of itself. He has painted down to the arms in the figure of Christ in that picture--which is a great improvement in industry &amp; dispatch.--What a terrible affair this duel is! What a pity that poor <span class="person">John Scott</span> did not at once fight <span class="person">Mr. Lockhart</span>. <span class="person">Horace Smith</span> for his second, or which would have been better still <span class="add">will</span> say simply that he would not fight at all in a literary quarrel. He is now the Victim of his own contemptible second--a man who [is-- missing?]a pawnbroker on Ludgate Hill &amp; a dandy in St. James's Street--&amp;who egged <span class="pagebreak">page 4<br/>
                     </span> on his unhappy friend to gratify his own trumpery desire of notoriety.  I hope he will be severely dealt with.--Thinking of hanging--we are all talking here of a neighbour of ours a <span class="person">rich farmer's widow</span> who seems likely enough to be in that predicament. She has set fire to her premises to cheat the Insurance office--but if she has sense enough to plead lunacy I think she may escape. I must tell you one story of her. <span class="person">Her husband</span> died about three months ago &amp; desired to be buried at <span class="place">Chippenham</span>--his native place.  The disconsolate Widow mourned over the expence of a <span class="sic">Herse</span>
                     <span class="reg">hearse</span> thought it would be much cheaper to send the body by the stage &amp; set off to <span class="place">Reading</span> to <span class="sic">negociate</span>
                     <span class="reg">negotiate</span> for the carriage of the Corpse. "Carry a coffin on the outside of the Coach Ma'am! Its impossible." quoth the astonished Coachman. "Well never mind the Coffin" continued this persevering Economist "Can I pack him up some other way?"<span class="jerk">〰</span> The <span class="person"> owner of our old place</span> is farming it <span class="del"> </span> topsy turvy--he has filled up the water &amp; is going to cut down the firs--besides unheard of vagaries in the House--without he is spending two or three thousand pounds in spoiling the place, if ever he should be tried for his life I will give him as good a character for being mad--as I would to the aforesaid. I must tell you a story of him. He is a soft youth of good fortune &amp; no education, &amp; being in love with a <span class="person">young woman</span>, a clergyman's daughter contrived in pure mistake (it must have been mistake for they had neither of them any fortune) to marry her <span class="person">Aunt</span>.  Last summer the Aunt died, &amp; he out of gratitude I suppose for the release had a sort of royal funeral which cost eight or nine hundred pounds--the defunct lying in state, in such a cottage as this--&amp; with no mortal to see her but himself &amp; the Maid.  he is now going to marry his first love the niece--you know a similar accident befel <span class="person">Lord Portsmouth</span>--who after he had been married two months to his present wife found out that he had intended to marry her sister.</span>
               </p>To <span class="person">Sir William Elford Bar<span class="above-line">t</span>
               </span>
               <br/>
               <span class="place">Bickham</span>
               <br/>
               <span class="place">Plymouth</span>
               <br/>single</div>
            <hr/>
         </div>
      </div>
   </body>
</html>
