<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng"
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://digitalmitford.github.io/DM_documentation/MitfordODD/out/mitfordODD.rng" 
type="application/xml" 
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!--<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>--><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         

         <titleStmt>
            <title ref="#OV">Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title>
            <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>


            <editor ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</editor>
            <editor ref="#ad">Alexandra Drayton</editor>

            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford
               Project</orgName></sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#jmh">Jonathan M. Horanic</persName>
               <persName ref="#scw">Samantha Webb</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>This is optional, used to describe this edition, and “should contain phrases
               describing the edition or version”: First digital edition in TEI, date: 2 June 2013.
               P5.</edition>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>We can include a respStmt here.</resp>
               <persName>Who?</persName>
            </respStmt>

         </editionStmt>



         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>

         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>

         <notesStmt>
            <note>Any special notes on this text? (optional)</note>
            <note>You can have multiple notes here.</note>
         </notesStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <!--2017-01-10 ebb: We need to change this sourceDesc to indicate we’re checking each text and altering it to represent the 1824 edition as published in NCCO. -->
            <!--Notice, this is simpler than the sourceDesc we used in our Letters file.-->
            <p>Our text is based on public domain, Google-digitized text<bibl>
                  <title ref="#OV">Our Village: Sketches of Rural Character and Scenery</title><edition>Third
                     Edition</edition> by <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell
                     Mitford</author><pubPlace ref="#London_city">London</pubPlace><publisher ref="#Whittaker_GB_pub">Geo. B.
                     Whittaker</publisher><placeName>Ave Maria Lane</placeName><date>1825</date>.
               </bibl> This text appears to be identical in pagination and content to the first
               edition published in 1824. </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Describes our editorial practice.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="sketch">
            <pb n="241"/>
            <head><title level="s" ref="#Walks_Country_OV">WALKS IN THE COUNTRY</title>.<lb/><title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">NUTTING</title>.
               <!--ebb: If there’s a subtitle use an <lb/> element to separate -->
            </head>
            <p><date when="--11-26">September 26th</date>.—One of those delicious autumnal days, when the air, the sky, and the
               earth, seem lulled into an universal calm, softer and milder even than May. <persName ref="#OVNarrator #Lizzy_OV #May-Flower_OV">We</persName>
               sallied forth for a walk, in a mood congenial to the weather and the season,
               avoiding, by mutual consent, the bright and sunny common, and the gay high road, and
               stealing through shady unfrequented lanes, where we were not likely to meet any
               one,—not even the pretty family procession which in other years we used to
               contemplate with so much interest—<orgName ref="#Nutting_gleanerFamily_OV">the father, mother, and children</orgName>, returning from
               the wheat-field, the little ones laden with bristling close-tied bunches of
               <rs type="plant" ref="#wheat">wheat-ears</rs>, their own gleanings, or a bottle and a basket which had contained their
               frugal dinner, whilst the mother would carry her babe hushing and lulling it, and the
               father and an elder child trudged after with the cradle, all seeming<pb n="242"/>
               weary, and all happy. We shall not see such a procession as this to-day; for the
               harvest is nearly over, the fields are deserted, the silence may almost be felt.
               Except the wintry notes of the <rs type="animal" ref="#robin">red-breast</rs>, nature herself is mute. But how beautiful,
               how gentle, how harmonious, how rich! The rain has preserved to the herbage all the
               freshness and verdure of spring, and the world of leaves has lost nothing of its
               midsummer brightness, and the <rs type="plant" ref="#harebell">hare-bell</rs> is on the banks and the <rs type="plant" ref="#woodbine">woodbine</rs> in the
               hedges, and the low <rs type="plant" ref="#furze">furze</rs>, which the <rs type="animal" ref="#sheep">lambs</rs> cropped in the spring, has burst again
               into its golden blossoms.</p>
            <p>All is beautiful that the eye can see; perhaps the more beautiful for being shut in
               with a forest-like closeness. We have no prospect in this labyrinth of lanes,
               cross-roads, mere cart-ways, leading to the innumerable little farms into which this
               part of the parish is divided. Uphill or down, these quiet woody lanes scarcely give
               us a peep at the world, except when, leaning over a gate, we look into one of the
               small enclosures, hemmed in with hedgerows, so closely set with growing timber, that
               the meady opening looks almost like a glade in a wood, or when some cottage, planted
               at a corner of one of the little greens formed by the meeting of these cross-ways,
               almost startles us by the unexpected sight of the dwellings of men in such a
               solitude. But that we have more of hill and<pb n="243"/> dale, and that our
               cross-roads are excellent in their kind, this side of our parish would resemble the
               description given of <placeName ref="#Vendee">La Vendée</placeName>, in <persName ref="#Rochejacquelein_Victoire">Madame Laroche-jacquelin</persName>’s most interesting book
                  *.<note type="author" anchored="true">* An almost equally interesting account of
                     that very peculiar and interesting scenery, may be found in <q>“<title ref="#Maid_LaVendee_novel">The Maid of La
                        Vendée</title>,”</q> an English novel, remarkable for its simplicity and truth of painting,
                     written by <persName ref="#LeNoir_Eliz">Mrs. Le Noir</persName>, tbe daughter of <persName ref="#Smart_Chris">Christopher Smart</persName>, and inheritrix of much
                  of his talent. Her works deserve to be better known.</note> I am sure if wood can
               entitle a country to be called Le Bocage,<note resp="#scw"><emph><foreign>Bocage</foreign></emph> is a French word describing farmlands that are interspersed with hedges and trees.</note> none can have a better right to the name.
               Even this pretty snug farm-house on the hill side, with its front covered with the
               rich <rs type="plant" ref="#vine">vine</rs>, which goes wreathing up to the very top of the clustered chimney, and its
               sloping orchard full of fruit—even this pretty quiet nest can hardly peep out of its
               leaves. Ah! they are gathering in the orchard-harvest. Look at that <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_secondSon_OV">young rogue</rs> in
               the old mossy <rs type="plant" ref="#apple_tree">apple-tree</rs>—that great tree, bending with the weight of its
               golden-rennets—see how he pelts his <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_daughter_OV">little sister</rs> beneath with apples as red and as
               round as her own cheeks, while she, with her outstretched frock, is trying to catch
               them, and laughing and offering to pelt again as often as one bobs against her; and
               look at that still <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_Willy_OV">younger imp</rs>, who, as grave as a judge, is creeping on hands and
               knees under the tree, picking up the <rs type="plant" ref="#apple">apples</rs> as they fall so<pb n="244"/> deedily
               *<note type="author" anchored="true">*<q>“Deedily,”</q>—I am not quite sure that this
                  word is good English; but it is genuine <placeName ref="#Hampshire_county">Hampshire</placeName>, and is used by the most correct
                  of female writers, <persName ref="#Austen_Jane">Miss Austen</persName>.<note resp="#scw">Mitford is likely referring to Austen's use of the term <q>'deedily'</q> in <title level="m" ref="#Emma_JA">Emma</title>, where she describes an assembly of characters at the Bates home.</note> It means (and it is no small merit that it has no
                  exact synonyme) any thing done with a profound and plodding attention, an action
                  which engrosses all the powers of mind and body.</note>, and depositing them so
               honestly in the great basket on the grass, already fixed so firmly and opened so
               widely, and filled almost to overflowing by the brown rough fruitage of the golden
               rennet’s next neighbour the russeting; and see that <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_youngestChild_OV">smallest urchin of all</rs> seated
               apart in infantine state on the turfy bank, with that toothsome piece of deformity a
               crumpling in each hand, now biting from one sweet hard juicy morsel, and now from
               another.—Is not that a pretty English picture? And then, farther up the orchard, that
               bold hardy lad, the <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_eldestSon_OV">eldest-born</rs>, who has scaled (Heaven knows how!) the tall straight
               upper branch of that great <rs type="plant" ref="#pear">pear-tree</rs>, and is sitting there as securely and as
               fearlessly, in as much real safety and apparent danger, as a sailor on the top-mast.
               Now he shakes the tree with a mighty swing that brings down a pelting shower of stony
               bergamots, which <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_Mr_OV">the father</rs> gathers rapidly up, whilst <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_Mrs_OV">the mother</rs> can hardly assist
               for her motherly fear,—a fear which only spurs the <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_eldestSon_OV">spirited boy</rs> to bolder ventures.
               Is not that a pretty picture? And they are such a handsome family, too,<pb n="245"/>
               <orgName ref="#Brooker_family_OV">the Brookers</orgName>. I do not know that there is any gipsey blood, but there is the true
               gipsey complexion, richly brown, with cheeks and lips so deeply red, black hair
               curling close to their heads in short crisp rings, white shining teeth—and such
               eyes!—That sort of beauty entirely eclipses your mere roses and lilies. Even <persName ref="#Lizzy_OV">Lizzy</persName>,
               the prettiest of fair children, would look poor and watery by the side of <persName ref="#Brooker_Willy_OV">Willy
                  Brooker</persName>, the sober little personage who is picking up the apples with his small
               chubby hands, and filling the basket so orderly, next to <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_Mr_OV">his father</rs> the most useful
               man in the field. <said who="#Lizzy_OV"><quote>“Willy!”</quote></said> He hears without seeing; for we are quite hidden by the
               high bank, and a spreading <rs type="plant" ref="#hawthorn">hawthorn-bush</rs> that overtops it, though between the lower
               branches and the grass we have found a convenient peep-hole. <said who="#Lizzy_OV"><quote>“Willy!”</quote></said> The voice
               sounds to him like some fairy dream, and the black eyes are raised from the ground
               with sudden wonder, the long silky eye-lashes thrown back till they rest on the
               delicate brow, and a deeper blush is burning in those dark cheeks, and a smile is
               dimpling about those scarlet lips. But the voice is silent now, and the <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_Willy_OV">little quiet
                  boy</rs>, after a moment’s pause, is gone coolly to work again. He is indeed a most lovely
               child. I think some day or other he must marry <persName ref="#Lizzy_OV">Lizzy</persName>; I shall propose the match to
               <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_Mrs_OV #LizzysMother_OV">their respective mammas</rs>. At present the parties are rather too young for a
               wedding—the<pb n="246"/> <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_Willy_OV">intended bridegroom</rs> being, as I should judge, six, or
               thereabout, and the <rs type="person" ref="#Lizzy_OV">fair bride</rs> barely five,—but at least we might have a betrothment
               after the royal fashion,—there could be no harm in that. <persName ref="#Lizzy_OV">Miss Lizzy</persName>, I have no doubt,
               would be as demure and coquettish as if ten winters more had gone over her head, and
               poor <persName ref="#Brooker_Willy_OV">Willy</persName> would open his innocent black eyes, and wonder what was going forward.
               They would be the very <persName ref="#Oberon_WS">Oberon</persName> and <persName ref="#Titania_WS">Titania</persName> of the village, the fairy king and
               queen.</p>
            <p>Ah! here is the hedge along which the <rs type="plant" ref="#periwinkle">periwinkle</rs> wreathes and twines so profusely,
               with its ever-green leaves shining like the myrtle, and its starry blue flowers. It
               is seldom found wild in this part of England; but, when we do meet with it, it is so
               abundant and so welcome,—the very robin-redbreast of flowers, a winter friend. Unless
               in those unfrequent frosts which destroy all vegetation, it blossoms from September
               to June, surviving the last lingering <rs type="plant" ref="#geranium">crane’s-bill</rs>, forerunning the earliest
               <rs type="plant" ref="#primrose">primrose</rs>, hardier even than the <rs type="plant" ref="#daisy">mountain daisy</rs>,—peeping out from beneath the snow,
               looking at itself in the ice, smiling through the tempests of life,and yet welcoming
               and enjoying the sunbeams. Oh, to be like that flower!</p>
            <p>The little spring that has been bubbling under the hedge all along the hill-side,
               begins, now that we have mounted the eminence and are imperceptibly descending, to
               deviate into a capricious variety of clear deep<pb n="247"/> pools and channels, so
               narrow and so choked with weeds, that a child might overstep them. The hedge has also
               changed its character. It is no longer the close compact vegetable wall of <rs type="plant" ref="#hawthorn">hawthorn</rs>,
               and <rs type="plant" ref="#maple">maple</rs>, and <rs type="plant" ref="#sweet_briar">briar roses</rs>, intertwined with <rs type="plant" ref="#bramble">bramble</rs> and <rs type="plant" ref="#woodbine">woodbine</rs>, and crowned with
               large <rs type="plant" ref="#elm">elms</rs> or thickly set saplings. No! the pretty meadow which rises high above us,
               backed and almost surrounded by a tall coppice, needs no defence on our side but its
               own steep bank, garnished with tufts of <rs type="plant" ref="#broom">broom</rs>, with <rs type="plant" ref="#oak">pollard oaks</rs> wreathed with <rs type="plant" ref="#ivy">ivy</rs>,
               and here and there with long patches of <rs type="plant" ref="#hazel">hazel</rs> overhanging the water. <said who="#Brooker_Willy_OV">“Ah there are
                  still nuts on that bough!”</said> and in an instant <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_Willy_OV">my dear companion</rs>, active and eager and
               delighted as a boy, has hooked down with his walking-stick one of the lissome hazel
                  stalks, and cleared it of its tawny clusters, and in another moment he has mounted
               the bank, and is in the midst of the nuttery, now transferring the spoil from the
               lower branches into that vast variety of pockets which gentlemen carry about them,
               now bending the tall tops into the lane, holding them down by main force, so that I
               might reach them and enjoy the pleasure of collecting some of the plunder myself. A
               very great pleasure he knew it would be. I doffed my shawl, tucked up my flounces,
               turned my straw bonnet into a basket, and began gathering and scrambling—for, manage
               it how you may, nutting is scrambling work,—those boughs,<pb n="248"/> however
               tightly you may grasp them by the young fragrant twigs and the bright green leaves,
               will recoil and burst away; but there is a pleasure even in that; so on we go,
               scrambling and gathering with all our might and all our glee. Oh what an enjoyment!
               All my life long I have had a passion for that sort of seeking which implies finding,
               (the secret, I believe, of the love of field-sports, which is in man’s mind a natural
               impulse,)—therefore I love violeting,—therefore, when we had a fine garden I used to
               love to gather <rs type="plant" ref="#strawberry">strawberries</rs>, and cut <rs type="plant" ref="#asparagus">asparagus</rs>, and, above all, to collect the
               <rs type="plant" ref="#filbert">filberts</rs> from the shrubberies: but this hedge-row nutting beats that sport all to
               nothing. That was a make-believe thing, compared with this; there was no surprise, no
               suspense, no unexpectedness—it was as inferior to this wild nutting, as the turning
               out of a <rs type="animal" ref="#fox">bag-fox</rs> is to unearthing the fellow in the eyes of a stanch fox-hunter.</p>
            <p>Oh what an enjoyment this nut-gathering is! They are in such abundance, that it seems
               as if there were not a boy in the parish, nor a young man, nor a young woman,—for a
               basket of nuts is the universal tribute of country gallantry; our pretty damsel
               <persName ref="#Harriet_ShopLodger_OV">Harriet</persName> has had at least half a dozen this season; but no one has found out these.
               And they are so full too, we lose half of them from over-ripeness; they drop from the
               socket at the slightest motion. If we lose, there is one who<pb n="249"/> finds. <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>
               is as fond of nuts as a squirrel, and cracks the shell and extracts the kernel with
               equal dexterity. Her white glossy head is upturned now to watch them as they fall.
               See how her neck is thrown back like that of a swan, and how beautifully her folded
               ears quiver with expectation, and how her quick eye follows the rustling noise, and
               her light feet dance and pat the ground, and leap up with eagerness, seeming almost
               sustained in the air, just as I have seen her when <persName ref="#Brush_dog_OV">Brush</persName> is beating a hedgerow, and
               she knows from his questing that there is a <rs type="animal" ref="#hare">hare</rs> afoot. See, she has caught that <rs type="plant" ref="#hazel">nut</rs>
               just before it touched the water; but the water would have been no defence,—she
               fishes them from the bottom, she delves after them amongst the matted grass—even my
               bonnet—how beggingly she looks at that! <said who="#OVNarrator">“Oh what a pleasure nutting is!—Is it not,
                  <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>? But the pockets are almost full, and so is the basket-bonnet, and that bright
               watch the sun says it is late;—and after all it is wrong to rob the poor
               boys—<q>‘pleasant but wrong’</q><note resp="#scw">This much disseminated quote comes from <persName ref="#Foote_Samuel">Samuel Foote</persName>'s play, <title level="m" ref="#The_Minor_play">The Minor</title>, towards the end of Act 2. It is spoken by Smirk to Sir George Wealthy.</note>—is it not, <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>?”</said>—<persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName> shakes her graceful head denyingly, as
               if she understood the question—<said who="#OVNarrator">“And we must go home now—must we not? But we will come
                  nutting again some time or other—shall we not, my <persName ref="#May-flower_OV">May</persName>?”</said></p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listPerson sortKey="histPersons">
           
            
            <person xml:id="Newbery_John" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Newbery_John">John Newbery
                  <surname>Newbery</surname>
                  <forename>John</forename>
               </persName>
               <birth when="1713-07-09"><placeName>Waltham St. Lawrence</placeName></birth>
               <death when="1767-12-22"><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName></death>
               <occupation type="bookProducer" subtype="publisher"/>
               <note resp="#scw">Widely considered the most influential publisher of children's books of his time, Newbery  began his career as a printer's apprentice in <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>, working for the founder of the <title level="j" ref="#ReadingMer_per">Reading Mercury</title>, <persName>William Carnan</persName>. He later married <persName>Carnan</persName>'s widow, and adopted her three children. In <date when="1744">1744</date>, he moved his business to St. Paul's Churchyard, <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>, and opened the <orgName>Juvenile Library</orgName>, recruiting well-known authors to produce children's books that would change the face of children's literature. Some of Newbery's notable works include <title level="m">A Little Pretty Pocket Book</title>, <title level="m">The History of Margery Two-Shoes</title> and <title level="j">The Liliputian Magazine</title>. Newbery's sons and newphew carried on the business after his death. His step-daughter, <persName>Anna Maria Smart</persName> and step-granddaughter, <persName>Mary Anne Cowslade</persName> continued operating the <title level="m" ref="#ReadingMer_per">Reading Mercury</title>. His second step-granddaughter, <persName ref="#LeNoir_Eliz">Elizabeth LeNoir</persName> became a novelist.</note>
               <note><ref target="http://viaf.org/viaf/76370928"/></note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="LeNoir_Eliz" sex="f">
               <persName ref="#LeNoir_Eliz">Elizabeth Anne LeNoir
                  <surname type="married">LeNoir</surname>
                  <surname type="paternal">Smart</surname>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>   
               </persName>
               <birth notBefore="1744-01-01" notAfter="1745-12-31">1744 or 1745
                  <placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName>
               </birth>
               <death when="1841-05-06">
               <placeName>the Priory, Caversham</placeName></death>
               <occupation type="literary" subtype="novelist"/>
               <occupation type="literary" subtype="poet"/>
               <note resp="#scw">The daughter of <persName ref="#Smart_Chris">Christopher Smart</persName>, and step-granddaughter of <persName ref="#Newbery_John">John Newbery</persName>, LeNoir grew up in <placeName ref="#Ireland">Ireland</placeName> but subsequently moved with her family to <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName>in <date when="1762">1762</date>. After her father's imprisonment for debt and death, her grandfather employed her as a writer and editor at the <title ref="#ReadingMer_per">Reading Mercury</title>. On <persName ref="#Newbery_John">John Newbery</persName>'s death, she, together with <persName>her mother</persName> and her sister, <persName>Mary Anne Cowslade</persName> later inherited partial ownership of the periodical. She married French emigre, <persName>Jean Baptiste LeNoir de la Brosse</persName> in <date when="1795">1795</date>. Between <date when="1803">1803</date> and <date when="1825">1825</date>, LeNoir published five novels and one book of poetry. The novels contain original poetry, and are frequently set in rural scenes. <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> admired her works, mentioning them in <title level="m" ref="#Recollections">Recollections of a Literary Life</title>, where she says that she is personally acquainted with LeNoir's nieces. In <title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title>, <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford</persName> praises her fourth novel, <title level="a" ref="#Maid_LaVendee_novel">The Maid of La Vendee</title>. </note>
               <note><ref target="https://extra.shu.ac.uk/corvey/corinne/Corinne%20authors/Le%20Noir/Le%20Noir%20biography.htm#"/>Biography of Elizabeth LeNoir by Laura Ridley. Corvey <q>'Adopt an Author'</q></note>
               <note><ref target="http://viaf.org/viaf/98146998434618940274                "/></note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Rochejacquelein_Victoire" sex="f">
               <persName ref="#Rochejacquelein_Victoire">Victoire de Donissan de Lescure de la Rochejacquelein
                  <surname type="married">de la Rochejacquelein</surname>
                  <surname type="married">de Lescure</surname>
                  <surname type="paternal">de Donissan</surname>
                  <forename>Marie-Louise-Victoire</forename>
                  <roleName>marquise de Lescure<date from="1791" to="1793-11-04"/></roleName>
                  <roleName>marquise douaniere de Lescure<date from="1793-11-05" to="1802-03"/></roleName>
                  <roleName>marquise douaniere de Lescure, comtesse de la Rochejacquelein<date from="1802-03" to="1802-09-06"/></roleName>
                  <roleName>marquise douaniere de Lescure, marquise de la Rochejacquelein<date from="1802-09-06" to="1815-07-15"/></roleName>
                  <roleName>marquise douaniere de Lescure et de la Rochejacquelein<date from="1815-07-15" to="1857-02-15"/></roleName>
               </persName>
               <birth when="1772-10-25"><placeName>Versailles, France</placeName></birth>
               <death when="1857-02-15"><placeName>Orleans, France</placeName></death>
               <occupation type="literary" subtype="autobiographer"/>
               <note resp="#scw">French aristocrat of the Revolutionary period whose autobiography, <title level="m">Memoire de Madame de la marquise de la Rochejacquelein</title>, recounts her harrowing escape from <placeName ref="#Paris">Paris</placeName> during the Revolution, and her subsequent sufferings through the Vendeean uprisings, during which she lost her first husband, <persName>Louis Marie de Salgue</persName>, the marquis de Lescure. She later married his cousin, <persName>Louis du Vergier de la Rochejacquelein</persName>, and together they continued to advocate for royalist ascendancy in France.</note>
               <note><ref target="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Victoire_de_Donnissan_de_La_Rochejaquelein"/></note>
               <!--scw: No viaf-->
            </person>
            
            
            <person xml:id="Smart_Chris" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Smart_Chris">Christopher Smart
                  <surname>Smart</surname>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mrs. Mary Midnight</persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Ebenezer Pentweazle</persName>
               <birth when="1722-04-11"><placeName>Shipbourne, England</placeName></birth>
               <death when="1771-05-01"><placeName ref="#London_city">London</placeName></death>
               <occupation type="literary" subtype="poet"/>
               <occupation type="literary" subtype="translator"/>
               <occupation type="literary" subtype="editor"/>
               <occupation type="literary" subtype="playwright"/>
               <note resp="#scw">Smart was a prolific writer and translator of religious, lyrical, and satirical verse. He was an acquaintance of <persName ref="#Pope_Alex">Alexander Pope</persName> (whose <title>Ode to St. Cecilia</title> he translated into Latin), <persName ref="#Johnson">Samuel Johnson</persName>, and <persName ref="#Collins_Wm">William Collins</persName>, all of whom expressed admiration for his work. After attending Cambridge and becoming praelector of Philosophy and keeper of the common chest in <date when="1745">1745</date>, Smart began to write poetry and plays, but also to accumulate debts that would follow him for the rest of his life. He began contributing to the magazine <title level="m">The Student</title> under the pseudonym <persName type="pseudo">Ebenezer Pentweazle</persName>. As a result of debt and a struggle with mental illness, he lost his place at Cambridge. Smart had met and married the step-daughter of <persName ref="#Newbery_John">John Newbery</persName>, who at the time was part-owner with his wife of the <title level="m" ref="#ReadingMer_per">Reading Mercury</title>. <persName ref="#Newbery_John">Newbery</persName> employed Smart to produce material for his publishing and advertising ventures, including a periodical entitled <title level="m">The Midwife; or the Old Woman's Magazine</title>. <persName ref="#Newbery_John">Newbery</persName> also published Smart's first major work, <title level="m">Poems on Several Occasions</title>, which included his lengthy georgic, <title>The Hop Garden</title>. Smart also produced a prose translation of <persName ref="#Horace">Horace</persName>'s works. In <date when="1763">1763</date>, Smart again suffered a bout of mental illness which took the form of a sort of religious mania, and was confined to an asylum. During his confinement, he composed his most famous works, <title level="a">Song to David</title> and <title level="a">Jubilate Agno</title>. He died in the king's bench prison, where he had been imprisoned for debt. His widow, <persName>Anna Maria Smart</persName> and daughter, <persName>Mary Anne Cowslade</persName> continued to operate the <title level="j" ref="#ReadingMer_per">Reading Mercury</title> for several decades after his death, while his second daughter, <persName ref="#LeNoir_Eliz">Elizabeth LeNoir</persName> became a novelist.</note>
               <note><ref target="http://viaf.org/viaf/51703197"/></note>
            </person>
            
            
         </listPerson>
         
         <listPerson sortKey="fictPersons">
            
            <person xml:id="Brooker_daughter_OV" sex="f">
            <persName ref="#Brooker_daughter_OV">the Brookers' daughter
               <surname type="paternal">Brooker</surname>
               <forename>not given</forename>
            </persName>
               <note resp="#scw">This young girl appears in <title ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title>, where she is seen happily gathering the apples that her <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_secondSon_OV">older brother</rs> flings down from a tree.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Brooker_eldestSon_OV" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Brooker_eldestSon_OV">the Brookers' eldest son
               <surname>Brooker</surname>
               <forename>not given</forename>  
               </persName>
               <note resp="#scw">This character appears in <title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title>, in which he is shown climbing to the top of a pear-tree and shaking down the fruit during the harvest.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Brooker_Mr_OV" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Brooker_Mr_OV">Mr. Brooker
               <surname>Brooker</surname>
               <forename>not given</forename>
               </persName>
               <occupation type="trade" subtype="farmer"/>
               <note resp="#scw">This character appears in the sketch <title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title>. He farms an apple and pear orchard together with his large family.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Brooker_Mrs_OV" sex="f">
               <persName ref="#Brooker_Mrs_OV">Mrs. Brooker
               <surname type="married">Brooker</surname>
                  <surname type="paternal">not given</surname>
               <forename>not given</forename>
               </persName>
               <occupation type="trade" subtype="farmer"/>
               <note resp="#scw">This character appears in <title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title>, in which she is seen at the fruit harvest with her family.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Brooker_secondSon_OV" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Brooker_secondSon_OV">Brooker second son
                  <surname>Brooker</surname>
                  <forename>not given</forename>
               </persName>
               <note resp="#scw">This character appears in <title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title>, where he is seen pelting apples down from a tree at his <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_daughter_OV">younger sister</rs> during the harvest.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Brooker_Willy_OV" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Brooker_Willy_OV">Willy Brooker
               <surname>Brooker</surname>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <forename type="nick">Willy</forename>
               </persName>
               <note resp="#scw">This character appears in <title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title> at the fruit harvest with his family, and later gathers nuts with <persName ref="#OVNarrator">the narrator</persName>. He is said to be about six- or seven-years old, and <persName ref="#OVNarrator">the narrator</persName> imagines him betrothed to <persName ref="#Lizzy_OV">Lizzy</persName>.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Brooker_youngestChild_OV" sex="u">
               <persName ref="#Brooker_youngestChild_OV">youngest Brooker child
               <surname>Brooker</surname>
                  <forename>not given</forename>
               </persName>
               <note resp="#scw">This character, an infant, is observed in <title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title> eating some of the harvested fruit.</note>
            </person>
            
            <person xml:id="Brush_dog_OV" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Brush_dog_OV">Brush</persName>
               <note resp="#scw">A hunting dog mentioned in <title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title>.</note>
            </person>
            
            
            
            <person xml:id="Oberon_WS" sex="m">
               <persName ref="#Oberon_WS">Oberon</persName>
               <note resp="#scw">In Shakespeare's <title level="m" ref="#Tempest_play">The Tempest</title>, he is King of the Fairies, married to <persName ref="#Titania_WS">Titania</persName>. In order to win a dispute with his wife over the fate of a child, Oberon causes his wife to fall in love with a human whose head has been turned into a donkey's.</note>
            </person>
               
           
            
            <person xml:id="Titania_WS" sex="f">
               <persName ref="#Titania_WS">Titania</persName>
               <note resp="#scw">In Shakespeare's <title level="m" ref="#Tempest_play">The Tempest</title>, she is Queen of the Fairies. As a result of a marital dispute over the fate of a child, she is tricked by her husband, <persName ref="#Oberon_WS">Oberon</persName>, to fall in love with a human whose head has been transformed into that of a donkey.</note>
            </person>
            
            
         </listPerson>
         
         
         
         <listOrg sortKey="fictOrgs">
            <org xml:id="Brooker_family_OV">
               <orgName ref="#Brooker_family_OV">the Brooker family</orgName>
               <note resp="#scw">A farming family featured in <title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title> that includes <rs type="person" ref="#Brooker_Mr_OV #Brooker_Mrs_OV #Brooker_eldestSon_OV #Brooker_secondSon_OV #Brooker_daughter_OV #Brooker_Willy_OV #Brooker_youngestChild_OV">the parents and five children</rs>. They are observed harvesting their pear and apple trees.</note>
            </org>
            
            <org xml:id="Nutting_gleanerFamily_OV">
               <orgName ref="#Nutting_gleanerFamily_OV">gleaner family
               </orgName>
               <note resp="#scw">These characters are not literally seen, but recalled as ones that <persName ref="#OVNarrator">the narrator</persName> would expect to meet in <title level="a" ref="#Walks_Nutting_OV">Nutting</title>.</note>
            </org>
            
         </listOrg>
         
         <listPlace sortKey="histPlaces">
            <place xml:id="Vendee">
               <placeName ref="#Vendee">Vendee</placeName>
               <region>Pays de la Loire</region>
               <country>France</country>
               <location>
                  <geo>46.670556, -1.426667</geo>
               </location>
               <note resp="#scw">Department in western France, traditionally believed to be the birthplace of <persName>Elinor of Acquitaine</persName>. During the French Revolution, the Vendee mounted a fierce resistance to the revolutionary government and later refused to recognize <persName ref="#Napoleon">Napoleon</persName>'s legitimacy after his escape from Elba.</note>
               
            </place>
         </listPlace>
         
         <listBibl sortKey="schol">
            <bibl xml:id="The_Minor_play">
               <title level="a" ref="#The_Minor_play">The Minor</title>
               <pubPlace ref="#London_city"><placeName/></pubPlace>
               <publisher>J. Coote</publisher>
               <date when="1760">1760</date>
               <note resp="#scw">A comic play that ridiculed the Methodist preacher, <persName>George Whitefield</persName>. It was performed at <placeName ref="#Haymarket_Theatre">The Haymarket</placeName> in <date when="1760">1760</date>, and subsequently moved to <placeName ref="#Drury_Lane_Theatre">Drury Lane</placeName> later that year.</note>
               <!--scw: publication info found in:<note><ref target="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Bibliotheca_Cornubiensis_A_O/JV0vAAAAMAAJ?hl=en&gbpv=1"/>Bibliotheca Cornubiensis</note>--><!--scw: notation from google books is not accepted-->
            </bibl>
            
            <bibl xml:id="Maid_LaVendee_novel"><!--scw: Need to learn how to structure an entry containing 2 editions, different titles and and pub info-->
               <title level="m" ref="#Maid_LaVendee_novel">The Maid of La Vendee, being a second edition of Clara de Montfier</title>
               <title type="alt" level="m">Clara de Monfier; a moral tale</title>
               <author ref="#LeNoir_Eliz">Elizabeth Anne LeNoir</author>
               <publisher>A.M. Smart</publisher><!--scw: This publisher name is likely that of LeNoir's mother, Anna Maria Smart, who was a part-owner of the Reading Mercury-->
               <date when="1808">1808</date>
               <pubPlace ref="#Reading_city">Reading</pubPlace>
               <date when="1810">1810</date><!--scw: 2nd edition, acc. to Corvey website-->
               <publisher>M. Cowslade and Co.</publisher><!--scw: This publisher name is likely that of LeNoir's sister, Mary Anne, who was part owner of the Reading Mercury-->
               <note resp="#scw">The Maid of La Vendee is the re-titled second edition of Elizabeth LeNoir's <date when="1808">1808</date> novel, <title level="m" type="alt">Clara de Montfier</title>. Both editions appear to have been published by members of LeNoir's family, who owned and operated <title level="j" ref="#ReadingMer_per">the Reading Mercury</title>.</note>
               <note> <ref target="https://extra.shu.ac.uk/corvey/corinne/Corinne%20authors/Le%20Noir/Le%20Noir%20biography.htm#"/>Biography of Elizabeth LeNoir by Laura Ridley. Corvey <q>'Adopt an Author'</q></note>
               
               
               
            </bibl>
         </listBibl>
         
         <list sortKey="plants">
            
            <item xml:id="apple"/>
            <item xml:id="asparagus"/>
            <item xml:id="vine"/>
            <item xml:id="woodbine"/>
            
         </list>
         
         <list sortKey="animals">
            <item xml:id="hare"/><!--scw: Already in the siADDNEW Stubs IP file, but i include here so my file will scan properly-->
            <item xml:id="sheep"/><!--scw: Already in the siADDNEW Stubs IP file, but i include here so my file will scan properly-->
            <item xml:id="fox"/>
         </list>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>